Preface

This tutorial is a guide to developing enterprise applications for the Java Platform, Enterprise Edition 7 (Java EE 7), using GlassFish Server Open Source Edition.

GlassFish Server Open Source Edition is the leading open-source and open-community platform for building and deploying next-generation applications and services. GlassFish Server Open Source Edition, developed by the GlassFish project open-source community at https://glassfish.java.net/, is the first compatible implementation of the Java EE 7 platform specification. This lightweight, flexible, and open-source application server enables organizations not only to leverage the new capabilities introduced within the Java EE 7 specification, but also to add to their existing capabilities through a faster and more streamlined development and deployment cycle. GlassFish Server Open Source Edition is hereafter referred to as GlassFish Server.

The following topics are addressed here:

Audience

Documentation Accessibility

Before You Read This Book

Related Documentation

Conventions

Default Paths and File Names

Audience

This tutorial is intended for programmers interested in developing and deploying Java EE 7 applications. It covers the technologies comprising the Java EE platform and describes how to develop Java EE components and deploy them on the Java EE Software Development Kit (SDK).

Documentation Accessibility

For information about Oracle's commitment to accessibility, visit the Oracle Accessibility Program website at http://www.oracle.com/pls/topic/lookup?ctx=acc&id=docacc.

Before You Read This Book

Before proceeding with this tutorial, you should have a good knowledge of the Java programming language. A good way to get to that point is to work through the Java Tutorials (http://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/index.html).

Related Documentation

The GlassFish Server documentation set describes deployment planning and system installation. To obtain documentation for GlassFish Server Open Source Edition, go to https://glassfish.java.net/docs/.

The Java EE 7 API specification can be viewed at http://docs.oracle.com/javaee/7/api/ and is also provided in the Java EE 7 SDK.

Additionally, the Java EE Specifications at http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javaee/tech/index.html might be useful.

For information about creating enterprise applications in the NetBeans Integrated Development Environment (IDE), see http://www.netbeans.org/kb/.

For information about the Java DB database for use with GlassFish Server, see http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javadb/overview/index.html.

The GlassFish Samples project is a collection of sample applications that demonstrate a broad range of Java EE technologies. The GlassFish Samples are bundled with the Java EE Software Development Kit (SDK) and are also available from the GlassFish Samples project page at https://glassfish-samples.java.net/.

Conventions

The following table describes the typographic conventions that are used in this book.

Convention | Meaning | Example

Boldface

|

Boldface type indicates graphical user interface elements associated with an action or terms defined in text.

|

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

A cache is a copy that is stored locally.

Monospace

|

Monospace type indicates the names of files and directories, commands within a paragraph, URLs, code in examples, text that appears on the screen, or text that you enter.

|

Edit your .login file.

Use ls -a to list all files.

machine_name% you have mail.

Italic

|

Italic type indicates book titles, emphasis, or placeholder variables for which you supply particular values.

|

Read Chapter 6 in the User's Guide.

Do not save the file.

The command to remove a file is rm filename.

Default Paths and File Names

The following table describes the default paths and file names that are used in this book.

Placeholder | Description | Default Value

as-install

|

Represents the base installation directory for GlassFish Server or the SDK of which GlassFish Server is a part.

|

Installations on the Solaris operating system, Linux operating system, and Mac operating system:

user's-home-directory/glassfish4/glassfish

Windows, all installations:

SystemDrive:\glassfish4\glassfish

as-install-parent

|

Represents the parent of the base installation directory for GlassFish Server.

|

Installations on the Solaris operating system, Linux operating system, and Mac operating system:

user's-home-directory/glassfish4

Windows, all installations:

SystemDrive:\glassfish4

tut-install

|

Represents the base installation directory for the Java EE Tutorial after you install GlassFish Server or the SDK and run the Update Tool.

|

as-install-parent/docs/javaee-tutorial

domain-dir

|

Represents the directory in which a domain's configuration is stored.

|

as-install/domains/domain1

21 Introduction to Bean Validation

Validating input received from the user to maintain data integrity is an important part of application logic. Validation of data can take place at different layers in even the simplest of applications, as shown in Developing a Simple Facelets Application: The guessnumber-jsf Example Application. The guessnumber-jsf example application validates the user input (in the h:inputText tag) for numerical data at the presentation layer and for a valid range of numbers at the business layer.

The Java API for JavaBean Validation ("Bean Validation") provides a facility for validating objects, object members, methods, and constructors. In Java EE environments, Bean Validation integrates with Java EE containers and services to allow developers to easily define and enforce validation constraints. Bean Validation is available as part of the Java EE 7 platform.

The following topics are addressed here:

Using Bean Validation Constraints

Validating Null and Empty Strings

Validating Constructors and Methods

Further Information about Bean Validation

21.1 Using Bean Validation Constraints

The Bean Validation model is supported by constraints in the form of annotations placed on a field, method, or class of a JavaBeans component, such as a managed bean.

Constraints can be built in or user defined. User-defined constraints are called custom constraints. Several built-in constraints are available in the javax.validation.constraints package. Table 21-1 lists all the built-in constraints. See Creating Custom Constraints for information on creating custom constraints.

Table 21-1 Built-In Bean Validation Constraints

Constraint | Description | Example

@AssertFalse

|

The value of the field or property must be false.

|

@AssertFalse
boolean isUnsupported;

@AssertTrue

|

The value of the field or property must be true.

|

@AssertTrue
boolean isActive;

@DecimalMax

|

The value of the field or property must be a decimal value lower than or equal to the number in the value element.

|

@DecimalMax("30.00")
BigDecimal discount;

@DecimalMin

|

The value of the field or property must be a decimal value greater than or equal to the number in the value element.

|

@DecimalMin("5.00")
BigDecimal discount;

@Digits

|

The value of the field or property must be a number within a specified range. The integer element specifies the maximum integral digits for the number, and the fraction element specifies the maximum fractional digits for the number.

|

@Digits(integer=6, fraction=2)
BigDecimal price;

@Future

|

The value of the field or property must be a date in the future.

|

@Future
Date eventDate;

@Max

|

The value of the field or property must be an integer value lower than or equal to the number in the value element.

|

@Max(10)
int quantity;

@Min

|

The value of the field or property must be an integer value greater than or equal to the number in the value element.

|

@Min(5)
int quantity;

@NotNull

|

The value of the field or property must not be null.

|

@NotNull
String username;

@Null

|

The value of the field or property must be null.

|

@Null
String unusedString;

@Past

|

The value of the field or property must be a date in the past.

|

@Past
Date birthday;

@Pattern

|

The value of the field or property must match the regular expression defined in the regexp element.

|

@Pattern(regexp="\\(\\d{3}\\)\\d{3}-\\d{4}")
String phoneNumber;

@Size

|

The size of the field or property is evaluated and must match the specified boundaries. If the field or property is a String, the size of the string is evaluated. If the field or property is a Collection, the size of the Collection is evaluated. If the field or property is a Map, the size of the Map is evaluated. If the field or property is an array, the size of the array is evaluated. Use one of the optional max or min elements to specify the boundaries.

|

@Size(min=2, max=240)
String briefMessage;

In the following example, a constraint is placed on a field using the built-in @NotNull constraint:

public class Name {
    @NotNull 
    private String firstname;

    @NotNull 
    private String lastname;
    ...
}

You can also place more than one constraint on a single JavaBeans component object. For example, you can place an additional constraint for size of field on the firstname and the lastname fields:

public class Name {
    @NotNull
    @Size(min=1, max=16)
    private String firstname;

    @NotNull 
    @Size(min=1, max=16)
    private String lastname;
    ...
}

The following example shows a method with a user-defined constraint that checks for a predefined email address pattern, such as a corporate email account:

@ValidEmail 
public String getEmailAddress() {
    return emailAddress;
}

For a built-in constraint, a default implementation is available. A user-defined or custom constraint needs a validation implementation. In the preceding example, the @ValidEmail custom constraint needs an implementation class.

Any validation failures are gracefully handled and can be displayed by the h:messages tag.

Any managed bean that contains Bean Validation annotations automatically gets validation constraints placed on the fields on a JavaServer Faces application's web pages.

For more information on using validation constraints, see the following:

Chapter 22, "Bean Validation: Advanced Topics"

Validating Resource Data with Bean Validation

Validating Persistent Fields and Properties

21.2 Validating Null and Empty Strings

The Java programming language distinguishes between null and empty strings. An empty string is a string instance of zero length, whereas a null string has no value at all.

An empty string is represented as "". It is a character sequence of zero characters. A null string is represented by null. It can be described as the absence of a string instance.

Managed bean elements represented as a JavaServer Faces text component such as inputText are initialized with the value of the empty string by the JavaServer Faces implementation. Validating these strings can be an issue when user input for such fields is not required. Consider the following example, in which the string testString is a bean variable that will be set using input entered by the user. In this case, the user input for the field is not required.

if (testString==null) {
    doSomething();
} else {
    doAnotherThing();
}

By default, the doAnotherThing method is called even when the user enters no data, because the testString element has been initialized with the value of an empty string.

In order for the Bean Validation model to work as intended, you must set the context parameter javax.faces.INTERPRET_EMPTY_STRING_SUBMITTED_VALUES_AS_NULL to true in the web deployment descriptor file, web.xml:

<context-param>
    <param-name>
        javax.faces.INTERPRET_EMPTY_STRING_SUBMITTED_VALUES_AS_NULL
    </param-name>
    <param-value>true</param-value>
</context-param>

This parameter enables the JavaServer Faces implementation to treat empty strings as null.

Suppose, on the other hand, that you have a @NotNull constraint on an element, meaning that input is required. In this case, an empty string will pass this validation constraint. However, if you set the context parameter javax.faces.INTERPRET_EMPTY_STRING_SUBMITTED_VALUES_AS_NULL to true, the value of the managed bean attribute is passed to the Bean Validation runtime as a null value, causing the @NotNull constraint to fail.

21.3 Validating Constructors and Methods

Bean Validation constraints may be placed on the parameters of nonstatic methods and constructors and on the return values of nonstatic methods. Static methods and constructors will not be validated.

public class Employee {
...
  public Employee (@NotNull String name) { ... }

  public void setSalary(
      @NotNull 
      @Digits(integer=6, fraction=2) BigDecimal salary,
      @NotNull
      @ValidCurrency
      String currencyType) {
    ...
  }
...
}

In this example, the Employee class has a constructor constraint requiring a name and has two sets of method parameter constraints. The amount of the salary for the employee must not be null, cannot be greater than six digits to the left of the decimal point, and cannot have more than two digits to the right of the decimal place. The currency type must not be null and is validated using a custom constraint.

If you add method constraints to classes in an object hierarchy, special care must be taken to avoid unintended behavior by subtypes. See Using Method Constraints in Type Hierarchies for more information.

21.3.1 Cross-Parameter Constraints

Constraints that apply to multiple parameters are called cross-parameter constraints, and may be applied at the method or constructor level.

@ConsistentPhoneParameters
@NotNull
public Employee (String name, String officePhone, String mobilePhone) {
  ...
}

In this example, a custom cross-parameter constraint, @ConsistentPhoneParameters, validates that the format of the phone numbers passed into the constructor match. The @NotNull constraint applies to all the parameters in the constructor.

Tip:

Cross-parameter constraint annotations are applied directly to the method or constructor. Return value constraints are also applied directly to the method or constructor. To avoid confusion as to where the constraint applies, parameter or return value, choose a name for any custom constraints that identifies where the constraint applies. For instance, the preceding example applies a custom constraint, @ConsistentPhoneParameters, that indicates that it applies to the parameters of the method or constructor.

When you create a custom constraint that applies to both method parameters and return values, the validationAppliesTo element of the constraint annotation may be set to ConstraintTarget.RETURN_VALUE or ConstraintTarget.PARAMETERS to explicitly set the target of the validation constraint.

21.3.2 Identifying Parameter Constraint Violations

If a ConstraintViolationException occurs during a method call, the Bean Validation runtime returns a parameter index to identify which parameter caused the constraint violation. The parameter index is in the form argPARAMETER_INDEX, where PARAMETER_INDEX is an integer that starts at 0 for the first parameter of the method or constructor.

21.3.3 Adding Constraints to Method Return Values

To validate the return value for a method, you can apply constraints directly to the method or constructor declaration.

@NotNull
public Employee getEmployee() { ... }

Cross-parameter constraints are also applied at the method level. Custom constraints that could be applied to both the return value and the method parameters have an ambiguous constraint target. To avoid this ambiguity, add a validationAppliesTo element to the constraint annotation definition with the default set to either ConstraintTarget.RETURN_VALUE or ConstraintTarget.PARAMETERS to explicitly set the target of the validation constraint.

@Manager(validationAppliesTo=ConstraintTarget.RETURN_VALUE)
public Employee getManager(Employee employee) { ... }

See Removing Ambiguity in Constraint Targets for more information.

21.4 Further Information about Bean Validation

For more information on Bean Validation, see

Bean Validation 1.1 Specification:

http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=349

Bean Validation Specification website:

http://beanvalidation.org/

22 Bean Validation: Advanced Topics

This chapter describes how to create custom constraints, custom validator messages, and constraint groups using the Java API for JavaBeans Validation (Bean Validation).

The following topics are addressed here:

Creating Custom Constraints

Customizing Validator Messages

Grouping Constraints

Using Method Constraints in Type Hierarchies

22.1 Creating Custom Constraints

Bean Validation defines annotations, interfaces, and classes to allow developers to create custom constraints.

22.1.1 Using the Built-In Constraints to Make a New Constraint

Bean Validation includes several built-in constraints that can be combined to create new, reusable constraints. This can simplify constraint definition by allowing developers to define a custom constraint made up of several built-in constraints that may then be applied to component attributes with a single annotation.

@Pattern.List({
  @Pattern(regexp = "[a-z0-9!#$%&'*+/=?^_`{|}~-]+(?:\\."
    +"[a-z0-9!#$%&'*+/=?^_`{|}~-]+)*"
    +"@(?:[a-z0-9](?:[a-z0-9-]*[a-z0-9])?\\.)+[a-z0-9](?:[a-z0-9-]*[a-z0-9])?")
})
@Constraint(validatedBy = {})
@Documented
@Target({ElementType.METHOD,
    ElementType.FIELD,
    ElementType.ANNOTATION_TYPE,
    ElementType.CONSTRUCTOR,
    ElementType.PARAMETER})
@Retention(RetentionPolicy.RUNTIME)
public @interface Email {

    String message() default "{invalid.email}";

    Class<?>[] groups() default {};

    Class<? extends Payload>[] payload() default {};

    @Target({ElementType.METHOD,
        ElementType.FIELD,
        ElementType.ANNOTATION_TYPE,
        ElementType.CONSTRUCTOR,
        ElementType.PARAMETER})
    @Retention(RetentionPolicy.RUNTIME)
    @Documented
    @interface List {
        Email[] value();
    }
}

This custom constraint can then be applied to an attribute.

...
@Email
protected String email;
...

22.1.2 Removing Ambiguity in Constraint Targets

Custom constraints that can be applied to both return values and method parameters require a validationAppliesTo element to identify the target of the constraint.

@Constraint(validatedBy=MyConstraintValidator.class)
@Target({ METHOD, FIELD, TYPE, ANNOTATION_TYPE, CONSTRUCTOR, PARAMETER })
@Retention(RUNTIME)
public @interface MyConstraint {
  String message() default "{com.example.constraint.MyConstraint.message}";
  Class<?>[] groups() default {};
  ConstraintTarget validationAppliesTo() default ConstraintTarget.PARAMETERS;
...
}

This constraint sets the validationAppliesTo target by default to the method parameters.

@MyConstraint(validationAppliesTo=ConstraintTarget.RETURN_TYPE)
public String doSomething(String param1, String param2) { ... }

In the preceding example, the target is set to the return value of the method.

22.2 Customizing Validator Messages

Bean Validation includes a resource bundle of default messages for the built-in constraints. These messages can be customized and can be localized for non-English-speaking locales.

22.2.1 The ValidationMessages Resource Bundle

The ValidationMessages resource bundle and the locale variants of this resource bundle contain strings that override the default validation messages. The ValidationMessages resource bundle is typically a properties file, ValidationMessages.properties, in the default package of an application.

22.2.1.1 Localizing Validation Messages

Locale variants of ValidationMessages.properties are added by appending an underscore and the locale prefix to the base name of the file. For example, the Spanish locale variant resource bundle would be ValidationMessages_es.properties.

22.3 Grouping Constraints

Constraints may be added to one or more groups. Constraint groups are used to create subsets of constraints so that only certain constraints will be validated for a particular object. By default, all constraints are included in the Default constraint group.

Constraint groups are represented by interfaces.

public interface Employee {}

public interface Contractor {}

Constraint groups can inherit from other groups.

public interface Manager extends Employee {}

When a constraint is added to an element, the constraint declares the groups to which that constraint belongs by specifying the class name of the group interface name in the groups element of the constraint.

@NotNull(groups=Employee.class)
Phone workPhone;

Multiple groups can be declared by surrounding the groups with braces ({ and }) and separating the groups' class names with commas.

@NotNull(groups={ Employee.class, Contractor.class })
Phone workPhone;

If a group inherits from another group, validating that group results in validating all constraints declared as part of the supergroup. For example, validating the Manager group results in the workPhone field being validated, because Employee is a superinterface of Manager.

22.3.1 Customizing Group Validation Order

By default, constraint groups are validated in no particular order. There are cases in which some groups should be validated before others. For example, in a particular class, basic data should be validated before more advanced data.

To set the validation order for a group, add a javax.validation.GroupSequence annotation to the interface definition, listing the order in which the validation should occur.

@GroupSequence({Default.class, ExpensiveValidationGroup.class})
public interface FullValidationGroup {}

When validating FullValidationGroup, first the Default group is validated. If all the data passes validation, then the ExpensiveValidationGroup group is validated. If a constraint is part of both the Default and the ExpensiveValidationGroup groups, the constraint is validated as part of the Default group and will not be validated on the subsequent ExpensiveValidationGroup pass.

22.4 Using Method Constraints in Type Hierarchies

If you add validation constraints to objects in an inheritance hierarchy, take special care to avoid unintended errors when using subtypes.

For a given type, subtypes should be able to be substituted without encountering errors. For example, if you have a Person class and an Employee subclass that extends Person, you should be able to use Employee instances wherever you might use Person instances. If Employee overrides a method in Person by adding method parameter constraints, code that works correctly with Person objects may throw validation exceptions with Employee objects.

The following code shows an incorrect use of method parameter constraints within a class hierarchy:

public class Person {
...
  public void setEmail(String email) { ... }
}

public class Employee extends Person {
...
  @Override
  public void setEmail(@Verified String email) { ... }
}

By adding the @Verified constraint to Employee.setEmail, parameters that were valid with Person.setEmail will not be valid with Employee.setEmail. This is called strengthening the preconditions (that is, the method parameters) of a subtype's method. You may not strengthen the preconditions of subtype method calls.

Similarly, the return values from method calls should not be weakened in subtypes. The following code shows an incorrect use of constraints on method return values in a class hierarchy:

public class Person {
...
  @Verified
  public Email getEmail() { ... }
}

public class Employee extends Person {
...
  @Override
  public Email getEmail() { ... }
}

In this example, the Employee.getEmail method removes the @Verified constraint on the return value. Return values that would be not pass validation when calling Person.getEmail are allowed when calling Employee.getEmail. This is called weakening the postconditions (that is, return values) of a subtype. You may not weaken the postconditions of a subtype method call.

If your type hierarchy strengthens the preconditions or weakens the postconditions of subtype method calls, a javax.validation.ConstraintDeclarationException will be thrown by the Bean Validation runtime.

Classes that implement several interfaces that each have the same method signature, known as parallel types, need to be aware of the constraints applied to the interfaces that they implement to avoid strengthening the preconditions. For example:

public interface PaymentService {
  void processOrder(Order order, double amount);
...
}

public interface CreditCardPaymentService {
  void processOrder(@NotNull Order order, @NotNull double amount);
...
}

public class MyPaymentService implements PaymentService,
        CreditCardPaymentService {

  @Override
  public void processOrder(Order order, double amount) { ... }
...
}

In this case, MyPaymentService has the constraints from the processOrder method in CreditCardPaymentService, but client code that calls PaymentService.processOrder doesn't expect these constraints. This is another example of strengthening the preconditions of a subtype and will result in a ConstraintDeclarationException.

22.4.1 Rules for Using Method Constraints in Type Hierarchies

The following rules define how method validation constraints should be used in type hierarchies.

Do not add method parameter constraints to overridden or implemented methods in a subtype.

Do not add method parameter constraints to overridden or implemented methods in a subtype that was originally declared in several parallel types.

You may add return value constraints to an overridden or implemented method in a subtype.

25 Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE: Advanced Topics

This chapter describes more advanced features of Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE (CDI). Specifically, it covers additional features CDI provides to enable loose coupling of components with strong typing, in addition to those described in Overview of CDI.

The following topics are addressed here:

Packaging CDI Applications

Using Alternatives in CDI Applications

Using Producer Methods, Producer Fields, and Disposer Methods in CDI Applications

Using Predefined Beans in CDI Applications

Using Events in CDI Applications

Using Interceptors in CDI Applications

Using Decorators in CDI Applications

Using Stereotypes in CDI Applications

25.1 Packaging CDI Applications

When you deploy a Java EE application, CDI looks for beans inside bean archives. A bean archive is any module that contains beans that the CDI runtime can manage and inject. There are two kinds of bean archives: explicit bean archives and implicit bean archives.

An explicit bean archive is an archive that contains a beans.xml deployment descriptor, which can be an empty file, contain no version number, or contain the version number 1.1 with the bean-discovery-mode attribute set to all. For example:

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<beans xmlns="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee"
       xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
       xsi:schemaLocation="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee 
                           http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee/beans_1_1.xsd"
       version="1.1" bean-discovery-mode="all">
    ...
</beans>

CDI can manage and inject any bean in an explicit archive, except those annotated with @Vetoed.

An implicit bean archive is an archive that contains some beans annotated with a scope type, contains no beans.xml deployment descriptor, or contains a beans.xml deployment descriptor with the bean-discovery-mode attribute set to annotated.

In an implicit archive, CDI can only manage and inject beans annotated with a scope type.

For a web application, the beans.xml deployment descriptor, if present, must be in the WEB-INF directory. For EJB modules or JAR files, the beans.xml deployment descriptor, if present, must be in the META-INF directory.

25.2 Using Alternatives in CDI Applications

When you have more than one version of a bean that you use for different purposes, you can choose between them during the development phase by injecting one qualifier or another, as shown in The simplegreeting CDI Example.

Instead of having to change the source code of your application, however, you can make the choice at deployment time by using alternatives.

Alternatives are commonly used for purposes such as the following:

To handle client-specific business logic that is determined at runtime

To specify beans that are valid for a particular deployment scenario (for example, when country-specific sales tax laws require country-specific sales tax business logic)

To create dummy (mock) versions of beans to be used for testing

To make a bean available for lookup, injection, or EL resolution using this mechanism, give it a javax.enterprise.inject.Alternative annotation and then use the alternatives element to specify it in the beans.xml file.

For example, you might want to create a full version of a bean and also a simpler version that you use only for certain kinds of testing. The example described in The encoder Example: Using Alternatives contains two such beans, CoderImpl and TestCoderImpl. The test bean is annotated as follows:

@Alternative
public class TestCoderImpl implements Coder { ... }

The full version is not annotated:

public class CoderImpl implements Coder { ... }

The managed bean injects an instance of the Coder interface:

@Inject
Coder coder;

The alternative version of the bean is used by the application only if that version is declared as follows in the beans.xml file:

<beans ...>
    <alternatives>
        <class>javaeetutorial.encoder.TestCoderImpl</class>
    </alternatives>
</beans>

If the alternatives element is commented out in the beans.xml file, the CoderImpl class is used.

You can also have several beans that implement the same interface, all annotated @Alternative. In this case, you must specify in the beans.xml file which of these alternative beans you want to use. If CoderImpl were also annotated @Alternative, one of the two beans would always have to be specified in the beans.xml file.

The alternatives that you specify in the beans.xml file apply only to classes in the same archive. Use the @Priority annotation to specify alternatives globally for an application that consists of multiple modules, as in the following example:

@Alternative
@Priority(Interceptor.Priority.APPLICATION+10)
public class TestCoderImpl implements Coder { ... }

The alternative with higher priority value is selected if several alternative beans that implement the same interface are annotated with @Priority. You do not need to specify the alternative in the beans.xml file when you use the @Priority annotation.

25.2.1 Using Specialization

Specialization has a function similar to that of alternatives in that it allows you to substitute one bean for another. However, you might want to make one bean override the other in all cases. Suppose you defined the following two beans:

@Default @Asynchronous
public class AsynchronousService implements Service { ... }

@Alternative
public class MockAsynchronousService extends AsynchronousService { ... }

If you then declared MockAsynchronousService as an alternative in your beans.xml file, the following injection point would resolve to MockAsynchronousService:

@Inject Service service;

The following, however, would resolve to AsynchronousService rather than MockAsynchronousService, because MockAsynchronousService does not have the @Asynchronous qualifier:

@Inject @Asynchronous Service service;

To make sure that MockAsynchronousService was always injected, you would have to implement all bean types and bean qualifiers of AsynchronousService. However, if AsynchronousService declared a producer method or observer method, even this cumbersome mechanism would not ensure that the other bean was never invoked. Specialization provides a simpler mechanism.

Specialization happens at development time as well as at runtime. If you declare that one bean specializes another, it extends the other bean class, and at runtime the specialized bean completely replaces the other bean. If the first bean is produced by means of a producer method, you must also override the producer method.

You specialize a bean by giving it the javax.enterprise.inject.Specializes annotation. For example, you might declare a bean as follows:

@Specializes
public class MockAsynchronousService extends AsynchronousService { ... }

In this case, the MockAsynchronousService class will always be invoked instead of the AsynchronousService class.

Usually, a bean marked with the @Specializes annotation is also an alternative and is declared as an alternative in the beans.xml file. Such a bean is meant to stand in as a replacement for the default implementation, and the alternative implementation automatically inherits all qualifiers of the default implementation as well as its EL name, if it has one.

25.3 Using Producer Methods, Producer Fields, and Disposer Methods in CDI Applications

A producer method generates an object that can then be injected. Typically, you use producer methods in the following situations:

When you want to inject an object that is not itself a bean

When the concrete type of the object to be injected may vary at runtime

When the object requires some custom initialization that the bean constructor does not perform

For more information on producer methods, see Injecting Objects by Using Producer Methods.

A producer field is a simpler alternative to a producer method; it is a field of a bean that generates an object. It can be used instead of a simple getter method. Producer fields are particularly useful for declaring Java EE resources such as data sources, JMS resources, and web service references.

A producer method or field is annotated with the javax.enterprise.inject.Produces annotation.

25.3.1 Using Producer Methods

A producer method can allow you to select a bean implementation at runtime instead of at development time or deployment time. For example, in the example described in The producermethods Example: Using a Producer Method to Choose a Bean Implementation, the managed bean defines the following producer method:

@Produces
@Chosen
@RequestScoped
public Coder getCoder() {

    switch (coderType) {
        case TEST:
            return new TestCoderImpl();
        case SHIFT:
            return new CoderImpl();
        default:
            return null;
    }
}

Here, getCoder becomes in effect a getter method, and when the coder property is injected with the same qualifier and other annotations as the method, the selected version of the interface is used.

@Inject
@Chosen
@RequestScoped
Coder coder;

Specifying the qualifier is essential: It tells CDI which Coder to inject. Without it, the CDI implementation would not be able to choose between CoderImpl, TestCoderImpl, and the one returned by getCoder and would cancel deployment, informing the user of the ambiguous dependency.

25.3.2 Using Producer Fields to Generate Resources

A common use of a producer field is to generate an object such as a JDBC DataSource or a Java Persistence API EntityManager (see Chapter 37, "Introduction to the Java Persistence API," for more information). The object can then be managed by the container. For example, you could create a @UserDatabase qualifier and then declare a producer field for an entity manager as follows:

@Produces
@UserDatabase
@PersistenceContext
private EntityManager em;

The @UserDatabase qualifier can be used when you inject the object into another bean, RequestBean, elsewhere in the application:

    @Inject
    @UserDatabase
    EntityManager em;
    ...

The producerfields Example: Using Producer Fields to Generate Resources shows how to use producer fields to generate an entity manager. You can use a similar mechanism to inject @Resource, @EJB, or @WebServiceRef objects.

To minimize the reliance on resource injection, specify the producer field for the resource in one place in the application, and then inject the object wherever in the application you need it.

25.3.3 Using a Disposer Method

You can use a producer method or a producer field to generate an object that needs to be removed when its work is completed. If you do, you need a corresponding disposer method, annotated with a @Disposes annotation. For example, you can close the entity manager as follows:

public void close(@Disposes @UserDatabase EntityManager em) {
    em.close();
}

The disposer method is called automatically when the context ends (in this case, at the end of the conversation, because RequestBean has conversation scope), and the parameter in the close method receives the object produced by the producer field.

25.4 Using Predefined Beans in CDI Applications

Java EE provides predefined beans that implement the following interfaces.

javax.transaction.UserTransaction: A Java Transaction API (JTA) user transaction.

java.security.Principal: The abstract notion of a principal, which represents any entity, such as an individual, a corporation, or a login ID. Whenever the injected principal is accessed, it always represents the identity of the current caller. For example, a principal is injected into a field at initialization. Later, a method that uses the injected principal is called on the object into which the principal was injected. In this situation, the injected principal represents the identity of the current caller when the method is run.

javax.validation.Validator: A validator for bean instances. The bean that implements this interface enables a Validator object for the default bean validation object ValidatorFactory to be injected.

javax.validation.ValidatorFactory: A factory class for returning initialized Validator instances. The bean that implements this interface enables the default bean validation ValidatorFactory object to be injected.

javax.servlet.http.HttpServletRequest: An HTTP request from a client. The bean that implements this interface enables a servlet to obtain all the details of a request.

javax.servlet.http.HttpSession: An HTTP session between a client and a server. The bean that implements this interface enables a servlet to access information about a session and to bind objects to a session.

javax.servlet.ServletContext: A context object that servlets can use to communicate with the servlet container.

To inject a predefined bean, create an injection point to obtain an instance of the bean by using the javax.annotation.Resource annotation for resources or the javax.inject.Inject annotation for CDI beans. For the bean type, specify the class name of the interface the bean implements.

Table 25-1 Injection of Predefined Beans

Predefined Bean | Resource or CDI Bean | Injection Example

UserTransaction

|

Resource

|

@Resource UserTransaction transaction;

Principal

|

Resource

|

@Resource Principal principal;

Validator

|

Resource

|

@Resource Validator validator;

ValidatorFactory

|

Resource

|

@Resource ValidatorFactory factory;

HttpServletRequest

|

CDI bean

|

@Inject HttpServletRequest req;

HttpSession

|

CDI bean

|

@Inject HttpSession session;

ServletContext

|

CDI bean

|

@Inject ServletContext context;

Predefined beans are injected with dependent scope and the predefined default qualifier @Default.

For more information about injecting resources, see Resource Injection.

The following code snippet shows how to use the @Resource and @Inject annotations to inject predefined beans. This code snippet injects a user transaction and a context object into the servlet class TransactionServlet. The user transaction is an instance of the predefined bean that implements the javax.transaction.UserTransaction interface. The context object is an instance of the predefined bean that implements the javax.servlet.ServletContext interface.

import javax.annotation.Resource;
import javax.inject.Inject;
import javax.servlet.http.HttpServlet;
import javax.transaction.UserTransaction;
...
public class TransactionServlet extends HttpServlet {
    @Resource UserTransaction transaction;
    @Inject ServletContext context;
    ...
}

25.5 Using Events in CDI Applications

Events allow beans to communicate without any compile-time dependency. One bean can define an event, another bean can fire the event, and yet another bean can handle the event. The beans can be in separate packages and even in separate tiers of the application.

25.5.1 Defining Events

An event consists of the following:

The event object, a Java object

Zero or more qualifier types, the event qualifiers

For example, in the billpayment example described in The billpayment Example: Using Events and Interceptors, a PaymentEvent bean defines an event using three properties, which have setter and getter methods:

    public String paymentType;
    public BigDecimal value;
    public Date datetime;

    public PaymentEvent() {
    }

The example also defines qualifiers that distinguish between two kinds of PaymentEvent. Every event also has the default qualifier @Any.

25.5.2 Using Observer Methods to Handle Events

An event handler uses an observer method to consume events.

Each observer method takes as a parameter an event of a specific event type that is annotated with the @Observes annotation and with any qualifiers for that event type. The observer method is notified of an event if the event object matches the event type and if all the qualifiers of the event match the observer method event qualifiers.

The observer method can take other parameters in addition to the event parameter. The additional parameters are injection points and can declare qualifiers.

The event handler for the billpayment example, PaymentHandler, defines two observer methods, one for each type of PaymentEvent:

public void creditPayment(@Observes @Credit PaymentEvent event) {
    ...
}

public void debitPayment(@Observes @Debit PaymentEvent event) {
    ...
}

Observer methods can also be conditional or transactional:

A conditional observer method is notified of an event only if an instance of the bean that defines the observer method already exists in the current context. To declare a conditional observer method, specify notifyObserver=IF_EXISTS as an argument to @Observes:

@Observes(notifyObserver=IF_EXISTS)

To obtain the default unconditional behavior, you can specify @Observes(notifyObserver=ALWAYS).

A transactional observer method is notified of an event during the before-completion or after-completion phase of the transaction in which the event was fired. You can also specify that the notification is to occur only after the transaction has completed successfully or unsuccessfully. To specify a transactional observer method, use any of the following arguments to @Observes:

@Observes(during=BEFORE_COMPLETION)

@Observes(during=AFTER_COMPLETION)

@Observes(during=AFTER_SUCCESS)

@Observes(during=AFTER_FAILURE)

To obtain the default nontransactional behavior, specify @Observes(during=IN_PROGRESS).

An observer method that is called before completion of a transaction may call the setRollbackOnly method on the transaction instance to force a transaction rollback.

Observer methods may throw exceptions. If a transactional observer method throws an exception, the exception is caught by the container. If the observer method is nontransactional, the exception terminates processing of the event, and no other observer methods for the event are called.

25.5.3 Firing Events

To activate an event, call the javax.enterprise.event.Event.fire method. This method fires an event and notifies any observer methods.

In the billpayment example, a managed bean called PaymentBean fires the appropriate event by using information it receives from the user interface. There are actually four event beans, two for the event object and two for the payload. The managed bean injects the two event beans. The pay method uses a switch statement to choose which event to fire, using new to create the payload.

    @Inject
    @Credit
    Event<PaymentEvent> creditEvent;

    @Inject
    @Debit
    Event<PaymentEvent> debitEvent;

    private static final int DEBIT = 1;
    private static final int CREDIT = 2;
    private int paymentOption = DEBIT;
    ...

    @Logged
    public String pay() {
        ...
        switch (paymentOption) {
            case DEBIT:
                PaymentEvent debitPayload = new PaymentEvent();
                // populate payload ... 
                debitEvent.fire(debitPayload);
                break;
            case CREDIT:
                PaymentEvent creditPayload = new PaymentEvent();
                // populate payload ... 
                creditEvent.fire(creditPayload);
                break;
            default:
                logger.severe("Invalid payment option!");
        }
        ...
    }

The argument to the fire method is a PaymentEvent that contains the payload. The fired event is then consumed by the observer methods.

25.6 Using Interceptors in CDI Applications

An interceptor is a class used to interpose in method invocations or lifecycle events that occur in an associated target class. The interceptor performs tasks, such as logging or auditing, that are separate from the business logic of the application and are repeated often within an application. Such tasks are often called cross-cutting tasks. Interceptors allow you to specify the code for these tasks in one place for easy maintenance. When interceptors were first introduced to the Java EE platform, they were specific to enterprise beans. On the Java EE 7 platform, you can use them with Java EE managed objects of all kinds, including managed beans.

For information on Java EE interceptors, see Chapter 54, "Using Java EE Interceptors".

An interceptor class often contains a method annotated @AroundInvoke, which specifies the tasks the interceptor will perform when intercepted methods are invoked. It can also contain a method annotated @PostConstruct, @PreDestroy, @PrePassivate, or @PostActivate, to specify lifecycle callback interceptors, and a method annotated @AroundTimeout, to specify EJB timeout interceptors. An interceptor class can contain more than one interceptor method, but it must have no more than one method of each type.

Along with an interceptor, an application defines one or more interceptor binding types, which are annotations that associate an interceptor with target beans or methods. For example, the billpayment example contains an interceptor binding type named @Logged and an interceptor named LoggedInterceptor. The interceptor binding type declaration looks something like a qualifier declaration, but it is annotated with javax.interceptor.InterceptorBinding:

@Inherited
@InterceptorBinding
@Retention(RUNTIME)
@Target({METHOD, TYPE})
public @interface Logged {
}

An interceptor binding also has the java.lang.annotation.Inherited annotation, to specify that the annotation can be inherited from superclasses. The @Inherited annotation also applies to custom scopes (not discussed in this tutorial) but does not apply to qualifiers.

An interceptor binding type may declare other interceptor bindings.

The interceptor class is annotated with the interceptor binding as well as with the @Interceptor annotation. For an example, see The LoggedInterceptor Interceptor Class.

Every @AroundInvoke method takes a javax.interceptor.InvocationContext argument, returns a java.lang.Object, and throws an Exception. It can call InvocationContext methods. The @AroundInvoke method must call the proceed method, which causes the target class method to be invoked.

Once an interceptor and binding type are defined, you can annotate beans and individual methods with the binding type to specify that the interceptor is to be invoked either on all methods of the bean or on specific methods. For example, in the billpayment example, the PaymentHandler bean is annotated @Logged, which means that any invocation of its business methods will cause the interceptor's @AroundInvoke method to be invoked:

@Logged
@SessionScoped
public class PaymentHandler implements Serializable {...}

However, in the PaymentBean bean, only the pay and reset methods have the @Logged annotation, so the interceptor is invoked only when these methods are invoked:

@Logged
public String pay() {...}

@Logged
public void reset() {...}

In order for an interceptor to be invoked in a CDI application, it must, like an alternative, be specified in the beans.xml file. For example, the LoggedInterceptor class is specified as follows:

<interceptors>
    <class>javaeetutorial.billpayment.interceptors.LoggedInterceptor</class>
</interceptors>

If an application uses more than one interceptor, the interceptors are invoked in the order specified in the beans.xml file.

The interceptors that you specify in the beans.xml file apply only to classes in the same archive. Use the @Priority annotation to specify interceptors globally for an application that consists of multiple modules, as in the following example:

@Logged
@Interceptor
@Priority(Interceptor.Priority.APPLICATION)
public class LoggedInterceptor implements Serializable { ... }

Interceptors with lower priority values are called first. You do not need to specify the interceptor in the beans.xml file when you use the @Priority annotation.

25.7 Using Decorators in CDI Applications

A decorator is a Java class that is annotated javax.decorator.Decorator and that has a corresponding decorators element in the beans.xml file.

A decorator bean class must also have a delegate injection point, which is annotated javax.decorator.Delegate. This injection point can be a field, a constructor parameter, or an initializer method parameter of the decorator class.

Decorators are outwardly similar to interceptors. However, they actually perform tasks complementary to those performed by interceptors. Interceptors perform cross-cutting tasks associated with method invocation and with the lifecycles of beans, but cannot perform any business logic. Decorators, on the other hand, do perform business logic by intercepting business methods of beans. This means that instead of being reusable for different kinds of applications, as are interceptors, their logic is specific to a particular application.

For example, instead of using an alternative TestCoderImpl class for the encoder example, you could create a decorator as follows:

@Decorator
public abstract class CoderDecorator implements Coder {
    
    @Inject
    @Delegate
    @Any
    Coder coder;
    
    public String codeString(String s, int tval) {
        int len = s.length();

        return "\"" + s + "\" becomes " + "\"" + coder.codeString(s, tval)
                + "\", " + len + " characters in length";
    }
}

See The decorators Example: Decorating a Bean for an example that uses this decorator.

This simple decorator returns more detailed output than the encoded string returned by the CoderImpl.codeString method. A more complex decorator could store information in a database or perform some other business logic.

A decorator can be declared as an abstract class so that it does not have to implement all the business methods of the interface.

In order for a decorator to be invoked in a CDI application, it must, like an interceptor or an alternative, be specified in the beans.xml file. For example, the CoderDecorator class is specified as follows:

<decorators>
    <class>javaeetutorial.decorators.CoderDecorator</class>
</decorators>

If an application uses more than one decorator, the decorators are invoked in the order in which they are specified in the beans.xml file.

If an application has both interceptors and decorators, the interceptors are invoked first. This means, in effect, that you cannot intercept a decorator.

The decorators that you specify in the beans.xml file apply only to classes in the same archive. Use the @Priority annotation to specify decorators globally for an application that consists of multiple modules, as in the following example:

@Decorator
@Priority(Interceptor.Priority.APPLICATION)
public abstract class CoderDecorator implements Coder { ... }

Decorators with lower priority values are called first. You do not need to specify the decorator in the beans.xml when you use the @Priority annotation.

25.8 Using Stereotypes in CDI Applications

A stereotype is a kind of annotation, applied to a bean, that incorporates other annotations. Stereotypes can be particularly useful in large applications in which you have a number of beans that perform similar functions. A stereotype is a kind of annotation that specifies the following:

A default scope

Zero or more interceptor bindings

Optionally, a @Named annotation, guaranteeing default EL naming

Optionally, an @Alternative annotation, specifying that all beans with this stereotype are alternatives

A bean annotated with a particular stereotype will always use the specified annotations, so you do not have to apply the same annotations to many beans.

For example, you might create a stereotype named Action, using the javax.enterprise.inject.Stereotype annotation:

@RequestScoped
@Secure
@Transactional
@Named
@Stereotype
@Target(TYPE)
@Retention(RUNTIME)
public @interface Action {}

All beans annotated @Action will have request scope, use default EL naming, and have the interceptor bindings @Transactional and @Secure.

You could also create a stereotype named Mock:

@Alternative
@Stereotype
@Target(TYPE)
@Retention(RUNTIME)
public @interface Mock {}

All beans with this annotation are alternatives.

It is possible to apply multiple stereotypes to the same bean, so you can annotate a bean as follows:

@Action
@Mock
public class MockLoginAction extends LoginAction { ... }

It is also possible to override the scope specified by a stereotype, simply by specifying a different scope for the bean. The following declaration gives the MockLoginAction bean session scope instead of request scope:

@SessionScoped
@Action
@Mock
public class MockLoginAction extends LoginAction { ... }

CDI makes available a built-in stereotype called Model, which is intended for use with beans that define the model layer of a model-view-controller application architecture. This stereotype specifies that a bean is both @Named and @RequestScoped:

@Named
@RequestScoped
@Stereotype
@Target({TYPE, METHOD, FIELD})
@Retention(RUNTIME)
public @interface Model {}

26 Running the Advanced Contexts and Dependency Injection Examples

This chapter describes in detail how to build and run several advanced examples that use CDI. The examples are in the tut-install/examples/cdi/ directory.

To build and run the examples, you will do the following.

Use NetBeans IDE or the Maven tool to compile, package, and deploy the example.

Run the example in a web browser.

See Chapter 2, "Using the Tutorial Examples", for basic information on installing, building, and running the examples.

The following topics are addressed here:

The encoder Example: Using Alternatives

The producermethods Example: Using a Producer Method to Choose a Bean Implementation

The producerfields Example: Using Producer Fields to Generate Resources

The billpayment Example: Using Events and Interceptors

The decorators Example: Decorating a Bean

26.1 The encoder Example: Using Alternatives

The encoder example shows how to use alternatives to choose between two beans at deployment time, as described in Using Alternatives in CDI Applications. The example includes an interface and two implementations of it, a managed bean, a Facelets page, and configuration files.

The source files are located in the tut-install/examples/cdi/encoder/src/main/java/javaeetutorial/encoder/ directory.

26.1.1 The Coder Interface and Implementations

The Coder interface contains just one method, codeString, that takes two arguments: a string, and an integer value that specifies how the letters in the string should be transposed.

public interface Coder {
    public String codeString(String s, int tval);
}

The interface has two implementation classes, CoderImpl and TestCoderImpl. The implementation of codeString in CoderImpl shifts the string argument forward in the alphabet by the number of letters specified in the second argument; any characters that are not letters are left unchanged. (This simple shift code is known as a Caesar cipher because Julius Caesar reportedly used it to communicate with his generals.) The implementation in TestCoderImpl merely displays the values of the arguments. The TestCoderImpl implementation is annotated @Alternative:

import javax.enterprise.inject.Alternative;

@Alternative
public class TestCoderImpl implements Coder {

    @Override
    public String codeString(String s, int tval) {
        return ("input string is " + s + ", shift value is " + tval);
    }
}

The beans.xml file for the encoder example contains an alternatives element for the TestCoderImpl class, but by default the element is commented out:

<beans ...>
    <!--<alternatives>
        <class>javaeetutorial.encoder.TestCoderImpl</class>
    </alternatives>-->
</beans>

This means that by default, the TestCoderImpl class, annotated @Alternative, will not be used. Instead, the CoderImpl class will be used.

26.1.2 The encoder Facelets Page and Managed Bean

The simple Facelets page for the encoder example, index.xhtml, asks the user to enter the string and integer values and passes them to the managed bean, CoderBean, as coderBean.inputString and coderBean.transVal:

<html lang="en"
      xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:h="http://java.sun.com/jsf/html">
    <h:head>
        <h:outputStylesheet library="css" name="default.css"/>
        <title>String Encoder</title>
    </h:head>
    <h:body>
        <h2>String Encoder</h2>
        <p>Type a string and an integer, then click Encode.</p>
        <p>Depending on which alternative is enabled, the coder bean
            will either display the argument values or return a string that
            shifts the letters in the original string by the value you
            specify. The value must be between 0 and 26.</p>
        <h:form id="encodeit">
            <p><h:outputLabel value="Enter a string: " for="inputString"/>
                <h:inputText id="inputString"
                             value="#{coderBean.inputString}"/>
                <h:outputLabel value="Enter the number of letters to shift by: "
                               for="transVal"/>
                <h:inputText id="transVal" value="#{coderBean.transVal}"/></p>
            <p><h:commandButton value="Encode"
                                action="#{coderBean.encodeString()}"/></p>
            <p><h:outputLabel value="Result: " for="outputString"/>
                <h:outputText id="outputString"
                              value="#{coderBean.codedString}"
                              style="color:blue"/></p>
            <p><h:commandButton value="Reset"
                                action="#{coderBean.reset}"/></p>
        </h:form>
        ...
    </h:body>
</html>

When the user clicks the Encode button, the page invokes the managed bean's encodeString method and displays the result, coderBean.codedString, in blue. The page also has a Reset button that clears the fields.

The managed bean, CoderBean, is a @RequestScoped bean that declares its input and output properties. The transVal property has three Bean Validation constraints that enforce limits on the integer value, so that if the user enters an invalid value, a default error message appears on the Facelets page. The bean also injects an instance of the Coder interface:

@Named
@RequestScoped
public class CoderBean {

    private String inputString;
    private String codedString;
    @Max(26)
    @Min(0)
    @NotNull
    private int transVal;

    @Inject
    Coder coder;
    ...

In addition to simple getter and setter methods for the three properties, the bean defines the encodeString action method called by the Facelets page. This method sets the codedString property to the value returned by a call to the codeString method of the Coder implementation:

    public void encodeString() {
        setCodedString(coder.codeString(inputString, transVal));
    }

Finally, the bean defines the reset method to empty the fields of the Facelets page:

    public void reset() {
        setInputString("");
        setTransVal(0);
    }

26.1.3 Running the encoder Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the encoder application.

26.1.3.1 To Build, Package, and Deploy the encoder Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/cdi

Select the encoder folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the encoder project and select Build.

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, encoder.war, located in the target directory, and then deploys it to GlassFish Server.

26.1.3.2 To Run the encoder Example Using NetBeans IDE

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/encoder

On the String Encoder page, enter a string and the number of letters to shift by, and then click Encode.

The encoded string appears in blue on the Result line. For example, if you enter Java and 4, the result is Neze.

Now, edit the beans.xml file to enable the alternative implementation of Coder.

In the Projects tab, under the encoder project, expand the Web Pages node, then expand the WEB-INF node.

Double-click the beans.xml file to open it.

Remove the comment characters that surround the alternatives element, so that it looks like this:

<alternatives>
    <class>javaeetutorial.encoder.TestCoderImpl</class>
</alternatives>

Save the file.

Right-click the encoder project and select Clean and Build.

In the web browser, reenter the URL to show the String Encoder page for the redeployed project:

http://localhost:8080/encoder/

Enter a string and the number of letters to shift by, and then click Encode.

This time, the Result line displays your arguments. For example, if you enter Java and 4, the result is:

Result: input string is Java, shift value is 4

26.1.3.3 To Build, Package, and Deploy the encoder Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/cdi/encoder/

Enter the following command to deploy the application:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, encoder.war, located in the target directory, and then deploys it to GlassFish Server.

26.1.3.4 To Run the encoder Example Using Maven

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/encoder/

The String Encoder page opens.

Enter a string and the number of letters to shift by, and then click Encode.

The encoded string appears in blue on the Result line. For example, if you enter Java and 4, the result is Neze.

Now, edit the beans.xml file to enable the alternative implementation of Coder.

In a text editor, open the following file:

tut-install/examples/cdi/encoder/src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/beans.xml

Remove the comment characters that surround the alternatives element, so that it looks like this:

<alternatives>
    <class>javaeetutorial.encoder.TestCoderImpl</class>
</alternatives>

Save and close the file.

Enter the following command:

mvn clean install

In the web browser, reenter the URL to show the String Encoder page for the redeployed project:

http://localhost:8080/encoder

Enter a string and the number of letters to shift by, and then click Encode.

This time, the Result line displays your arguments. For example, if you enter Java and 4, the result is:

Result: input string is Java, shift value is 4

26.2 The producermethods Example: Using a Producer Method to Choose a Bean Implementation

The producermethods example shows how to use a producer method to choose between two beans at runtime, as described in Using Producer Methods, Producer Fields, and Disposer Methods in CDI Applications. It is very similar to the encoder example described in The encoder Example: Using Alternatives. The example includes the same interface and two implementations of it, a managed bean, a Facelets page, and configuration files. It also contains a qualifier type. When you run it, you do not need to edit the beans.xml file and redeploy the application to change its behavior.

26.2.1 Components of the producermethods Example

The components of producermethods are very much like those for encoder, with some significant differences.

Neither implementation of the Coder bean is annotated @Alternative, and there is no beans.xml file, because it is not needed.

The Facelets page and the managed bean, CoderBean, have an additional property, coderType, that allows the user to specify at runtime which implementation to use. In addition, the managed bean has a producer method that selects the implementation using a qualifier type, @Chosen.

The bean declares two constants that specify whether the coder type is the test implementation or the implementation that actually shifts letters:

    private final static int TEST = 1;
    private final static int SHIFT = 2;
    private int coderType = SHIFT; // default value

The producer method, annotated with @Produces and @Chosen as well as @RequestScoped (so that it lasts only for the duration of a single request and response), returns one of the two implementations based on the coderType supplied by the user.

    @Produces
    @Chosen
    @RequestScoped
    public Coder getCoder() {

        switch (coderType) {
            case TEST:
                return new TestCoderImpl();
            case SHIFT:
                return new CoderImpl();
            default:
                return null;
        }
    }

Finally, the managed bean injects the chosen implementation, specifying the same qualifier as that returned by the producer method to resolve ambiguities:

    @Inject
    @Chosen
    @RequestScoped
    Coder coder;

The Facelets page contains modified instructions and a pair of options whose selected value is assigned to the property coderBean.coderType:

    <h2>String Encoder</h2>
        <p>Select Test or Shift, type a string and an integer, then click
            Encode.</p>
        <p>If you select Test, the TestCoderImpl bean will display the
            argument values.</p>
        <p>If you select Shift, the CoderImpl bean will return a string that
            shifts the letters in the original string by the value you specify.
            The value must be between 0 and 26.</p>
        <h:form id="encodeit">
            <h:selectOneRadio id="coderType"
                              required="true"
                              value="#{coderBean.coderType}">
                <f:selectItem
                    itemValue="1"
                    itemLabel="Test"/>
                <f:selectItem
                    itemValue="2"
                    itemLabel="Shift Letters"/>
            </h:selectOneRadio>
            ...

26.2.2 Running the producermethods Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the producermethods application.

26.2.2.1 To Build, Package, and Deploy the producermethods Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/cdi

Select the producermethods folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the producermethods project and select Build.

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, producermethods.war, located in the target directory, and then deploys it to GlassFish Server.

26.2.2.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the producermethods Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/cdi/producermethods/

Enter the following command to deploy the application:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, producermethods.war, located in the target directory, and then deploys it to GlassFish Server.

26.2.2.3 To Run the producermethods Example

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/producermethods

On the String Encoder page, select either the Test or Shift Letters option, enter a string and the number of letters to shift by, and then click Encode.

Depending on your selection, the Result line displays either the encoded string or the input values you specified.

26.3 The producerfields Example: Using Producer Fields to Generate Resources

The producerfields example, which allows you to create a to-do list, shows how to use a producer field to generate objects that can then be managed by the container. This example generates an EntityManager object, but resources such as JDBC connections and datasources can also be generated this way.

The producerfields example is the simplest possible entity example. It also contains a qualifier and a class that generates the entity manager. It also contains a single entity, a stateful session bean, a Facelets page, and a managed bean.

The source files are located in the tut-install/examples/cdi/producerfields/src/main/java/javaeetutorial/producerfields/ directory.

26.3.1 The Producer Field for the producerfields Example

The most important component of the producerfields example is the smallest, the db.UserDatabaseEntityManager class, which isolates the generation of the EntityManager object so it can easily be used by other components in the application. The class uses a producer field to inject an EntityManager annotated with the @UserDatabase qualifier, also defined in the db package:

@Singleton
public class UserDatabaseEntityManager {

    @Produces
    @PersistenceContext
    @UserDatabase
    private EntityManager em;
    ...
}

The class does not explicitly produce a persistence unit field, but the application has a persistence.xml file that specifies a persistence unit. The class is annotated javax.inject.Singleton to specify that the injector should instantiate it only once.

The db.UserDatabaseEntityManager class also contains commented-out code that uses create and close methods to generate and remove the producer field:

 /* @PersistenceContext
    private EntityManager em;

    @Produces
    @UserDatabase
    public EntityManager create() {
        return em;
    } */

    public void close(@Disposes @UserDatabase EntityManager em) {
        em.close();
    }

You can remove the comment indicators from this code and place them around the field declaration to test how the methods work. The behavior of the application is the same with either mechanism.

The advantage of producing the EntityManager in a separate class rather than simply injecting it into an enterprise bean is that the object can easily be reused in a typesafe way. Also, a more complex application can create multiple entity managers using multiple persistence units, and this mechanism isolates this code for easy maintenance, as in the following example:

@Singleton
public class JPAResourceProducer {
    @Produces 
    @PersistenceUnit(unitName="pu3")
    @TestDatabase 
    EntityManagerFactory customerDatabasePersistenceUnit;

    @Produces 
    @PersistenceContext(unitName="pu3")
    @TestDatabase 
    EntityManager customerDatabasePersistenceContext;
    
    @Produces 
    @PersistenceUnit(unitName="pu4")
    @Documents
    EntityManagerFactory customerDatabasePersistenceUnit;

    @Produces 
    @PersistenceContext(unitName="pu4")
    @Documents 
    EntityManager docDatabaseEntityManager;
}

The EntityManagerFactory declarations also allow applications to use an application-managed entity manager.

26.3.2 The producerfields Entity and Session Bean

The producerfields example contains a simple entity class, entity.ToDo, and a stateful session bean, ejb.RequestBean, that uses it.

The entity class contains three fields: an autogenerated id field, a string specifying the task, and a timestamp. The timestamp field, timeCreated, is annotated with @Temporal, which is required for persistent Date fields.

@Entity
public class ToDo implements Serializable {

    ...
    @Id
    @GeneratedValue(strategy = GenerationType.AUTO)
    private Long id;
    protected String taskText;
    @Temporal(TIMESTAMP)
    protected Date timeCreated;

    public ToDo() {
    }

    public ToDo(Long id, String taskText, Date timeCreated) {
        this.id = id;
        this.taskText = taskText;
        this.timeCreated = timeCreated;
    }
    ...

The remainder of the ToDo class contains the usual getters, setters, and other entity methods.

The RequestBean class injects the EntityManager generated by the producer method, annotated with the @UserDatabase qualifier:

@ConversationScoped
@Stateful
public class RequestBean {

    @Inject
    @UserDatabase
    EntityManager em;

It then defines two methods, one that creates and persists a single ToDo list item, and another that retrieves all the ToDo items created so far by creating a query:

    public ToDo createToDo(String inputString) {
        ToDo toDo = null;
        Date currentTime = Calendar.getInstance().getTime();

        try {
            toDo = new ToDo();
            toDo.setTaskText(inputString);
            toDo.setTimeCreated(currentTime);
            em.persist(toDo);
            return toDo;
        } catch (Exception e) {
            throw new EJBException(e.getMessage());
        }
    }

    public List<ToDo> getToDos() {
        try {
             List<ToDo> toDos =
                    (List<ToDo>) em.createQuery(
                    "SELECT t FROM ToDo t ORDER BY t.timeCreated")
                    .getResultList();
            return toDos;
        } catch (Exception e) {
            throw new EJBException(e.getMessage());
        }
    }

26.3.3 The producerfields Facelets Pages and Managed Bean

The producerfields example has two Facelets pages, index.xhtml and todolist.xhtml. The simple form on the index.xhtml page asks the user only for the task. When the user clicks the Submit button, the listBean.createTask method is called. When the user clicks the Show Items button, the action specifies that the todolist.xhtml file should be displayed:

    <h:body>
        <h2>To Do List</h2>
        <p>Enter a task to be completed.</p>
        <h:form id="todolist">
            <p><h:outputLabel value="Enter a string: " for="inputString"/>
                <h:inputText id="inputString"
                             value="#{listBean.inputString}"/></p>
            <p><h:commandButton value="Submit"
                                action="#{listBean.createTask()}"/></p>
            <p><h:commandButton value="Show Items"
                                action="todolist"/></p>
        </h:form>
        ...
    </h:body>

The managed bean, web.ListBean, injects the ejb.RequestBean session bean. It declares the entity.ToDo entity and a list of the entity along with the input string that it passes to the session bean. The inputString is annotated with the @NotNull Bean Validation constraint, so an attempt to submit an empty string results in an error.

@Named
@ConversationScoped
public class ListBean implements Serializable {

    ...
    @EJB
    private RequestBean request;
    @NotNull
    private String inputString;
    private ToDo toDo;
    private List<ToDo> toDos;

The createTask method called by the Submit button calls the createToDo method of RequestBean:

    public void createTask() {
        this.toDo = request.createToDo(inputString);
    }

The getToDos method, which is called by the todolist.xhtml page, calls the getToDos method of RequestBean:

    public List<ToDo> getToDos() {
        return request.getToDos();
    }

To force the Facelets page to recognize an empty string as a null value and return an error, the web.xml file sets the context parameter javax.faces.INTERPRET_EMPTY_STRING_SUBMITTED_VALUES_AS_NULL to true:

<context-param>
  <param-name>javax.faces.INTERPRET_EMPTY_STRING_SUBMITTED_VALUES_AS_NULL</param-name>
  <param-value>true</param-value>
</context-param>

The todolist.xhtml page is a little more complicated than the index.html page. It contains a dataTable element that displays the contents of the ToDo list. The body of the page looks like this:

    <body>
        <h2>To Do List</h2>
        <h:form id="showlist">
            <h:dataTable var="toDo"
                         value="#{listBean.toDos}"
                         rules="all"
                         border="1"
                         cellpadding="5">
                <h:column>
                    <f:facet name="header">
                        <h:outputText value="Time Stamp" />
                    </f:facet>
                    <h:outputText value="#{toDo.timeCreated}" />
                </h:column>
                <h:column>
                    <f:facet name="header">
                        <h:outputText value="Task" />
                    </f:facet>
                    <h:outputText value="#{toDo.taskText}" />
                </h:column>
            </h:dataTable>
            <p><h:commandButton id="back" value="Back" action="index" /></p>
        </h:form>
    </body>

The value of the dataTable is listBean.toDos, the list returned by the managed bean's getToDos method, which in turn calls the session bean's getToDos method. Each row of the table displays the timeCreated and taskText fields of the individual task. Finally, a Back button returns the user to the index.xhtml page.

26.3.4 Running the producerfields Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the producerfields application.

26.3.4.1 To Build, Package, and Deploy the producerfields Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

If the database server is not already running, start it by following the instructions in Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server.

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/cdi

Select the producerfields folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the producerfields project and select Build.

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, producerfields.war, located in the target directory, and then deploys it to GlassFish Server.

26.3.4.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the producerfields Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

If the database server is not already running, start it by following the instructions in Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server.

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/cdi/producerfields/

Enter the following command to deploy the application:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, producerfields.war, located in the target directory, and then deploys it to GlassFish Server.

26.3.4.3 To Run the producerfields Example

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/producerfields

On the Create To Do List page, enter a string in the field and click Submit.

You can enter additional strings and click Submit to create a task list with multiple items.

Click Show Items.

The To Do List page opens, showing the timestamp and text for each item you created.

Click Back to return to the Create To Do List page.

On this page, you can enter more items in the list.

26.4 The billpayment Example: Using Events and Interceptors

The billpayment example shows how to use both events and interceptors.

The example simulates paying an amount using a debit card or credit card. When the user chooses a payment method, the managed bean creates an appropriate event, supplies its payload, and fires it. A simple event listener handles the event using observer methods.

The example also defines an interceptor that is set on a class and on two methods of another class.

The source files are located in the tut-install/examples/cdi/billpayment/src/main/java/javaeetutorial/billpayment/ directory.

26.4.1 The PaymentEvent Event Class

The event class, event.PaymentEvent, is a simple bean class that contains a no-argument constructor. It also has a toString method and getter and setter methods for the payload components: a String for the payment type, a BigDecimal for the payment amount, and a Date for the timestamp.

    ...
    public String paymentType;
    public BigDecimal value;
    public Date datetime;

    public PaymentEvent() {
    }

    @Override
    public String toString() {
        return this.paymentType
                + " = $" + this.value.toString()
                + " at " + this.datetime.toString();
    }
    ...

The event class is a simple bean that is instantiated by the managed bean using new and then populated. For this reason, the CDI container cannot intercept the creation of the bean, and hence it cannot allow interception of its getter and setter methods.

26.4.2 The PaymentHandler Event Listener

The event listener, listener.PaymentHandler, contains two observer methods, one for each of the two event types:

@Logged
@SessionScoped
public class PaymentHandler implements Serializable {

    ...
    public void creditPayment(@Observes @Credit PaymentEvent event) {
        logger.log(Level.INFO, "PaymentHandler - Credit Handler: {0}",
                event.toString());

        // call a specific Credit handler class...
    }

    public void debitPayment(@Observes @Debit PaymentEvent event) {
        logger.log(Level.INFO, "PaymentHandler - Debit Handler: {0}",
                event.toString());
 
        // call a specific Debit handler class...
    }
}

Each observer method takes as an argument the event, annotated with @Observes and with the qualifier for the type of payment. In a real application, the observer methods would pass the event information on to another component that would perform business logic on the payment.

The qualifiers are defined in the payment package, described in The billpayment Facelets Pages and Managed Bean.

The PaymentHandler bean is annotated @Logged so that all its methods can be intercepted.

26.4.3 The billpayment Facelets Pages and Managed Bean

The billpayment example contains two Facelets pages, index.xhtml and the very simple response.xhtml. The body of index.xhtml looks like this:

    <h:body>
        <h3>Bill Payment Options</h3>
        <p>Enter an amount, select Debit Card or Credit Card, 
            then click Pay.</p>
        <h:form>
            <p>
            <h:outputLabel value="Amount: $" for="amt"/>
            <h:inputText id="amt" value="#{paymentBean.value}"
                         required="true"
                         requiredMessage="An amount is required."
                         maxlength="15" />
            </p>
            <h:outputLabel value="Options:" for="opt"/>
            <h:selectOneRadio id="opt" value="#{paymentBean.paymentOption}">
                <f:selectItem id="debit" itemLabel="Debit Card"
                              itemValue="1"/>
                <f:selectItem id="credit" itemLabel="Credit Card"
                              itemValue="2" />
            </h:selectOneRadio>
            <p><h:commandButton id="submit" value="Pay"
                                action="#{paymentBean.pay}" /></p>
            <p><h:commandButton value="Reset" 
                                action="#{paymentBean.reset}" /></p>
        </h:form>
        ...
    </h:body>

The input field takes a payment amount, passed to paymentBean.value. Two options ask the user to select a Debit Card or Credit Card payment, passing the integer value to paymentBean.paymentOption. Finally, the Pay command button's action is set to the method paymentBean.pay, and the Reset button's action is set to the paymentBean.reset method.

The payment.PaymentBean managed bean uses qualifiers to differentiate between the two kinds of payment event:

@Named
@SessionScoped
public class PaymentBean implements Serializable {

   ...
    @Inject
    @Credit
    Event<PaymentEvent> creditEvent;

    @Inject
    @Debit
    Event<PaymentEvent> debitEvent;

The qualifiers, @Credit and @Debit, are defined in the payment package along with PaymentBean.

Next, the PaymentBean defines the properties it obtains from the Facelets page and will pass on to the event:

    public static final int DEBIT = 1;
    public static final int CREDIT = 2;
    private int paymentOption = DEBIT;
    
    @Digits(integer = 10, fraction = 2, message = "Invalid value")
    private BigDecimal value;

    private Date datetime;

The paymentOption value is an integer passed in from the option component; the default value is DEBIT. The value is a BigDecimal with a Bean Validation constraint that enforces a currency value with a maximum number of digits. The timestamp for the event, datetime, is a Date object initialized when the pay method is called.

The pay method of the bean first sets the timestamp for this payment event. It then creates and populates the event payload, using the constructor for the PaymentEvent and calling the event's setter methods, using the bean properties as arguments. It then fires the event.

    @Logged
    public String pay() {
        this.setDatetime(Calendar.getInstance().getTime());
        switch (paymentOption) {
            case DEBIT:
                PaymentEvent debitPayload = new PaymentEvent();
                debitPayload.setPaymentType("Debit");
                debitPayload.setValue(value);
                debitPayload.setDatetime(datetime);
                debitEvent.fire(debitPayload);
                break;
            case CREDIT:
                PaymentEvent creditPayload = new PaymentEvent();
                creditPayload.setPaymentType("Credit");
                creditPayload.setValue(value);
                creditPayload.setDatetime(datetime);
                creditEvent.fire(creditPayload);
                break;
            default:
                logger.severe("Invalid payment option!");
        }
        return "response";
    }

The pay method returns the page to which the action is redirected, response.xhtml.

The PaymentBean class also contains a reset method that empties the value field on the index.xhtml page and sets the payment option to the default:

    @Logged
    public void reset() {
        setPaymentOption(DEBIT);
        setValue(BigDecimal.ZERO);
    }

In this bean, only the pay and reset methods are intercepted.

The response.xhtml page displays the amount paid. It uses a rendered expression to display the payment method:

    <h:body>
        <h:form>
            <h2>Bill Payment: Result</h2>
            <h3>Amount Paid with
                <h:outputText id="debit" value="Debit Card: "
                              rendered="#{paymentBean.paymentOption eq 1}" />
                <h:outputText id="credit" value="Credit Card: "
                              rendered="#{paymentBean.paymentOption eq 2}" />
                <h:outputText id="result" value="#{paymentBean.value}">
                    <f:convertNumber type="currency"/>
                </h:outputText>
            </h3>
            <p><h:commandButton id="back" value="Back" action="index" /></p>
        </h:form>
    </h:body>

26.4.4 The LoggedInterceptor Interceptor Class

The interceptor class, LoggedInterceptor, and its interceptor binding, Logged, are both defined in the interceptor package. The Logged interceptor binding is defined as follows:

@Inherited
@InterceptorBinding
@Retention(RUNTIME)
@Target({METHOD, TYPE})
public @interface Logged {
}

The LoggedInterceptor class looks like this:

@Logged
@Interceptor
public class LoggedInterceptor implements Serializable {

    ...

    public LoggedInterceptor() {
    }

    @AroundInvoke
    public Object logMethodEntry(InvocationContext invocationContext)
            throws Exception {
        System.out.println("Entering method: "
                + invocationContext.getMethod().getName() + " in class "
                + invocationContext.getMethod().getDeclaringClass().getName());

        return invocationContext.proceed();
    }
}

The class is annotated with both the @Logged and the @Interceptor annotations. The @AroundInvoke method, logMethodEntry, takes the required InvocationContext argument and calls the required proceed method. When a method is intercepted, logMethodEntry displays the name of the method being invoked as well as its class.

To enable the interceptor, the beans.xml file defines it as follows:

<interceptors>
    <class>javaeetutorial.billpayment.interceptor.LoggedInterceptor</class>
</interceptors>

In this application, the PaymentEvent and PaymentHandler classes are annotated @Logged, so all their methods are intercepted. In PaymentBean, only the pay and reset methods are annotated @Logged, so only those methods are intercepted.

26.4.5 Running the billpayment Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the billpayment application.

26.4.5.1 To Build, Package, and Deploy the billpayment Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/cdi

Select the billpayment folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the billpayment project and select Build.

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, billpayment.war, located in the target directory, and then deploys it to GlassFish Server.

26.4.5.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the billpayment Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/cdi/billpayment/

Enter the following command to deploy the application:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, billpayment.war, located in the target directory, and then deploys it to GlassFish Server.

26.4.5.3 To Run the billpayment Example

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/billpayment

On the Bill Payment Options page, enter a value in the Amount field.

The amount can contain up to 10 digits and include up to two decimal places. For example:

9876.54

Select Debit Card or Credit Card and click Pay.

The Bill Payment: Result page opens, displaying the amount paid and the method of payment:

Amount Paid with Credit Card: $9,876.34

Click Back to return to the Bill Payment Options page.

You can also click Reset to return to the initial page values.

Examine the server log output.

In NetBeans IDE, the output is visible in the GlassFish Server Output tab. Otherwise, view domain-dir/logs/server.log.

The output from each interceptor appears in the log, followed by the additional logger output defined by the constructor and methods:

INFO: Entering method: pay in class billpayment.payment.PaymentBean
INFO: PaymentHandler created.
INFO: Entering method: debitPayment in class billpayment.listener.PaymentHandler
INFO: PaymentHandler - Debit Handler: Debit = $1234.56 at Tue Dec 14 14:50:28 EST 2010

26.5 The decorators Example: Decorating a Bean

The decorators example, which is yet another variation on the encoder example, shows how to use a decorator to implement additional business logic for a bean. Instead of having the user choose between two alternative implementations of an interface at deployment time or runtime, a decorator adds some additional logic to a single implementation of the interface.

The example includes an interface, an implementation of it, a decorator, an interceptor, a managed bean, a Facelets page, and configuration files.

The source files are located in the tut-install/examples/cdi/decorators/src/main/java/javaeetutorial/decorators/ directory.

26.5.1 Components of the decorators Example

The decorators example is very similar to the encoder example described in The encoder Example: Using Alternatives. Instead of providing two implementations of the Coder interface, however, this example provides only the CoderImpl class. The decorator class, CoderDecorator, rather than simply return the coded string, displays the input and output strings' values and length.

The CoderDecorator class, like CoderImpl, implements the business method of the Coder interface, codeString:

@Decorator
public abstract class CoderDecorator implements Coder {

    @Inject
    @Delegate
    @Any
    Coder coder;

    public String codeString(String s, int tval) {
        int len = s.length();

        return "\"" + s + "\" becomes " + "\"" + coder.codeString(s, tval) 
                + "\", " + len + " characters in length";
    }
}

The decorator's codeString method calls the delegate object's codeString method to perform the actual encoding.

The decorators example includes the Logged interceptor binding and LoggedInterceptor class from the billpayment example. For this example, the interceptor is set on the CoderBean.encodeString method and the CoderImpl.codeString method. The interceptor code is unchanged; interceptors are usually reusable for different applications.

Except for the interceptor annotations, the CoderBean and CoderImpl classes are identical to the versions in the encoder example.

The beans.xml file specifies both the decorator and the interceptor:

    <decorators>
        <class>javaeetutorial.decorators.CoderDecorator</class>
    </decorators>
    <interceptors>
        <class>javaeetutorial.decorators.LoggedInterceptor</class>
    </interceptors>

26.5.2 Running the decorators Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the decorators application.

26.5.2.1 To Build, Package, and Deploy the decorators Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/cdi

Select the decorators folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the decorators project and select Build.

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, decorators.war, located in the target directory, and then deploys it to GlassFish Server.

26.5.2.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the decorators Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/cdi/decorators/

Enter the following command to deploy the application:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, decorators.war, located in the target directory, and then deploys it to GlassFish Server.

26.5.2.3 To Run the decorators Example

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/decorators

On the Decorated String Encoder page, enter a string and the number of letters to shift by, and then click Encode.

The output from the decorator method appears in blue on the Result line. For example, if you entered Java and 4, you would see the following:

"Java" becomes "Neze", 4 characters in length

Examine the server log output.

In NetBeans IDE, the output is visible in the GlassFish Server Output tab. Otherwise, view domain-dir/logs/server.log.

The output from the interceptors appears:

INFO: Entering method: encodeString in class javaeetutorial.decorators.CoderBean
INFO: Entering method: codeString in class javaeetutorial.decorators.CoderImpl

23 Introduction to Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE

Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE (CDI) is one of several Java EE features that help to knit together the web tier and the transactional tier of the Java EE platform. CDI is a set of services that, used together, make it easy for developers to use enterprise beans along with JavaServer Faces technology in web applications. Designed for use with stateful objects, CDI also has many broader uses, allowing developers a great deal of flexibility to integrate various kinds of components in a loosely coupled but typesafe way.

CDI 1.1 is specified by JSR 346. Related specifications that CDI uses include the following:

JSR 330, Dependency Injection for Java

The Managed Beans specification, an offshoot of the Java EE 7 platform specification (JSR 342)

The following topics are addressed here:

Getting Started

Overview of CDI

About Beans

About CDI Managed Beans

Beans as Injectable Objects

Using Qualifiers

Injecting Beans

Using Scopes

Giving Beans EL Names

Adding Setter and Getter Methods

Using a Managed Bean in a Facelets Page

Injecting Objects by Using Producer Methods

Configuring a CDI Application

Using the @PostConstruct and @PreDestroy Annotations with CDI Managed Bean Classes

Further Information about CDI

23.1 Getting Started

Contexts and Dependency Injection (CDI) enables your objects to have their dependencies provided to them automatically, instead of creating them or receiving them as parameters. CDI also manages the lifecycle of those dependencies for you.

For example, consider the following servlet:

@WebServlet("/cdiservlet")
public class NewServlet extends HttpServlet {
    private Message message;

    @Override
    public void init() {
        message = new MessageB();
    }

    @Override
    public void doGet(HttpServletRequest request, HttpServletResponse response)
                  throws IOException {
        response.getWriter().write(message.get());
    }
}

This servlet needs an instance of an object that implements the Message interface:

public interface Message {
    public String get();
}

The servlet creates itself an instance of the following object:

public class MessageB implements Message {
    public MessageB() { }

    @Override
    public String get() {
        return "message B";
    }
}

Using CDI, this servlet can declare its dependency on a Message instance and have it injected automatically by the CDI runtime. The new servlet code is the following:

@WebServlet("/cdiservlet")
public class NewServlet extends HttpServlet {
    @Inject private Message message;

    @Override
    public void doGet(HttpServletRequest request, HttpServletResponse response)
                  throws IOException {
        response.getWriter().write(message.get());
    }
}

The CDI runtime looks for classes that implement the Message interface, finds the MessageB class, creates a new instance of it, and injects it into the servlet at runtime. To manage the lifecycle of the new instance, the CDI runtime needs to know what the scope of the instance should be. In this example, the servlet only needs the instance to process an HTTP request; the instance can then be garbage collected. This is specified using the javax.enterprise.context.RequestScoped annotation:

@RequestScoped
public class MessageB implements Message { ... }

For more information on scopes, see Using Scopes.

The MessageB class is a CDI bean. CDI beans are classes that CDI can instantiate, manage, and inject automatically to satisfy the dependencies of other objects. Almost any Java class can be managed and injected by CDI. For more information on beans, see About Beans. A JAR or WAR file that contains a CDI bean is a bean archive. For more information on packaging bean archives, see Configuring a CDI Application in this chapter and Packaging CDI Applications in Chapter 25, "Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE: Advanced Topics".

In this example, MessageB is the only class that implements the Message interface. If an application has more than one implementation of an interface, CDI provides mechanisms that you can use to select which implementation to inject. For more information, see Using Qualifiers in this chapter and Using Alternatives in CDI Applications in Chapter 25, "Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE: Advanced Topics".

23.2 Overview of CDI

The most fundamental services provided by CDI are as follows.

Contexts: This service enables you to bind the lifecycle and interactions of stateful components to well-defined but extensible lifecycle contexts.

Dependency injection: This service enables you to inject components into an application in a typesafe way and to choose at deployment time which implementation of a particular interface to inject.

In addition, CDI provides the following services:

Integration with the Expression Language (EL), which allows any component to be used directly within a JavaServer Faces page or a JavaServer Pages page

The ability to decorate injected components

The ability to associate interceptors with components using typesafe interceptor bindings

An event-notification model

A web conversation scope in addition to the three standard scopes (request, session, and application) defined by the Java Servlet specification

A complete Service Provider Interface (SPI) that allows third-party frameworks to integrate cleanly in the Java EE 7 environment

A major theme of CDI is loose coupling. CDI does the following:

Decouples the server and the client by means of well-defined types and qualifiers, so that the server implementation may vary

Decouples the lifecycles of collaborating components by

Making components contextual, with automatic lifecycle management

Allowing stateful components to interact like services, purely by message passing

Completely decouples message producers from consumers, by means of events

Decouples orthogonal concerns by means of Java EE interceptors

Along with loose coupling, CDI provides strong typing by

Eliminating lookup using string-based names for wiring and correlations so that the compiler will detect typing errors

Allowing the use of declarative Java annotations to specify everything, largely eliminating the need for XML deployment descriptors, and making it easy to provide tools that introspect the code and understand the dependency structure at development time

23.3 About Beans

CDI redefines the concept of a bean beyond its use in other Java technologies, such as the JavaBeans and Enterprise JavaBeans (EJB) technologies. In CDI, a bean is a source of contextual objects that define application state and/or logic. A Java EE component is a bean if the lifecycle of its instances may be managed by the container according to the lifecycle context model defined in the CDI specification.

More specifically, a bean has the following attributes:

A (nonempty) set of bean types

A (nonempty) set of qualifiers (see Using Qualifiers)

A scope (see Using Scopes)

Optionally, a bean EL name (see Giving Beans EL Names)

A set of interceptor bindings

A bean implementation

A bean type defines a client-visible type of the bean. Almost any Java type may be a bean type of a bean.

A bean type may be an interface, a concrete class, or an abstract class and may be declared final or have final methods.

A bean type may be a parameterized type with type parameters and type variables.

A bean type may be an array type. Two array types are considered identical only if the element type is identical.

A bean type may be a primitive type. Primitive types are considered to be identical to their corresponding wrapper types in java.lang.

A bean type may be a raw type.

23.4 About CDI Managed Beans

A managed bean is implemented by a Java class, which is called its bean class. A top-level Java class is a managed bean if it is defined to be a managed bean by any other Java EE technology specification, such as the JavaServer Faces technology specification, or if it meets all the following conditions.

It is not a nonstatic inner class.

It is a concrete class or is annotated @Decorator.

It is not annotated with an EJB component-defining annotation or declared as an EJB bean class in ejb-jar.xml.

It has an appropriate constructor. That is, one of the following is the case.

The class has a constructor with no parameters.

The class declares a constructor annotated @Inject.

No special declaration, such as an annotation, is required to define a managed bean.

23.5 Beans as Injectable Objects

The concept of injection has been part of Java technology for some time. Since the Java EE 5 platform was introduced, annotations have made it possible to inject resources and some other kinds of objects into container-managed objects. CDI makes it possible to inject more kinds of objects and to inject them into objects that are not container-managed.

The following kinds of objects can be injected:

(Almost) any Java class

Session beans

Java EE resources: data sources, Java Message Service topics, queues, connection factories, and the like

Persistence contexts (Java Persistence API EntityManager objects)

Producer fields

Objects returned by producer methods

Web service references

Remote enterprise bean references

For example, suppose that you create a simple Java class with a method that returns a string:

package greetings;

public class Greeting {
    public String greet(String name) {
        return "Hello, " + name + ".";
    }
}

This class becomes a bean that you can then inject into another class. This bean is not exposed to the EL in this form. Giving Beans EL Names explains how you can make a bean accessible to the EL.

23.6 Using Qualifiers

You can use qualifiers to provide various implementations of a particular bean type. A qualifier is an annotation that you apply to a bean. A qualifier type is a Java annotation defined as @Target({METHOD, FIELD, PARAMETER, TYPE}) and @Retention(RUNTIME).

For example, you could declare an @Informal qualifier type and apply it to another class that extends the Greeting class. To declare this qualifier type, you would use the following code:

package greetings;

import static java.lang.annotation.ElementType.FIELD;
import static java.lang.annotation.ElementType.METHOD;
import static java.lang.annotation.ElementType.PARAMETER;
import static java.lang.annotation.ElementType.TYPE;
import static java.lang.annotation.RetentionPolicy.RUNTIME;

import java.lang.annotation.Retention;
import static java.lang.annotation.RetentionPolicy.RUNTIME;
import java.lang.annotation.Target;

import javax.inject.Qualifier;

@Qualifier
@Retention(RUNTIME)
@Target({TYPE, METHOD, FIELD, PARAMETER})
public @interface Informal {}

You can then define a bean class that extends the Greeting class and uses this qualifier:

ppackage greetings;

@Informal
public class InformalGreeting extends Greeting {
    public String greet(String name) {
        return "Hi, " + name + "!";
    }
}

Both implementations of the bean can now be used in the application.

If you define a bean with no qualifier, the bean automatically has the qualifier @Default. The unannotated Greeting class could be declared as follows:

package greetings;

import javax.enterprise.inject.Default;

@Default
public class Greeting {
    public String greet(String name) {
        return "Hello, " + name + ".";
    }
}

23.7 Injecting Beans

In order to use the beans you create, you inject them into yet another bean that can then be used by an application, such as a JavaServer Faces application. For example, you might create a bean called Printer into which you would inject one of the Greeting beans:

import javax.inject.Inject;

public class Printer {

    @Inject Greeting greeting;
    ...
}

This code injects the @Default Greeting implementation into the bean. The following code injects the @Informal implementation:

import javax.inject.Inject;

public class Printer {

    @Inject @Informal Greeting greeting;
    ...
}

More is needed for the complete picture of this bean. Its use of scope needs to be understood. In addition, for a JavaServer Faces application, the bean needs to be accessible through the EL.

23.8 Using Scopes

For a web application to use a bean that injects another bean class, the bean needs to be able to hold state over the duration of the user's interaction with the application. The way to define this state is to give the bean a scope. You can give an object any of the scopes described in Table 23-1, depending on how you are using it.

Table 23-1 Scopes

Scope | Annotation | Duration

Request

|

@RequestScoped

|

A user's interaction with a web application in a single HTTP request.

Session

|

@SessionScoped

|

A user's interaction with a web application across multiple HTTP requests.

Application

|

@ApplicationScoped

|

Shared state across all users' interactions with a web application.

Dependent

|

@Dependent

|

The default scope if none is specified; it means that an object exists to serve exactly one client (bean) and has the same lifecycle as that client (bean).

Conversation

|

@ConversationScoped

|

A user's interaction with a servlet, including JavaServer Faces applications. The conversation scope exists within developer-controlled boundaries that extend it across multiple requests for long-running conversations. All long-running conversations are scoped to a particular HTTP servlet session and may not cross session boundaries.

The first three scopes are defined by both JSR 346 and the JavaServer Faces specification. The last two are defined by JSR 346.

All predefined scopes except @Dependent are contextual scopes. CDI places beans of contextual scope in the context whose lifecycle is defined by the Java EE specifications. For example, a session context and its beans exist during the lifetime of an HTTP session. Injected references to the beans are contextually aware. The references always apply to the bean that is associated with the context for the thread that is making the reference. The CDI container ensures that the objects are created and injected at the correct time as determined by the scope that is specified for these objects.

You can also define and implement custom scopes, but that is an advanced topic. Custom scopes are likely to be used by those who implement and extend the CDI specification.

A scope gives an object a well-defined lifecycle context. A scoped object can be automatically created when it is needed and automatically destroyed when the context in which it was created ends. Moreover, its state is automatically shared by any clients that execute in the same context.

Java EE components, such as servlets and enterprise beans, and JavaBeans components do not by definition have a well-defined scope. These components are one of the following:

Singletons, such as Enterprise JavaBeans singleton beans, whose state is shared among all clients

Stateless objects, such as servlets and stateless session beans, which do not contain client-visible state

Objects that must be explicitly created and destroyed by their client, such as JavaBeans components and stateful session beans, whose state is shared by explicit reference passing between clients

If, however, you create a Java EE component that is a managed bean, it becomes a scoped object, which exists in a well-defined lifecycle context.

The web application for the Printer bean will use a simple request and response mechanism, so the managed bean can be annotated as follows:

import javax.enterprise.context.RequestScoped;
import javax.inject.Inject;

@RequestScoped
public class Printer {

    @Inject @Informal Greeting greeting;
    ...
}

Beans that use session, application, or conversation scope must be serializable, but beans that use request scope do not have to be serializable.

23.9 Giving Beans EL Names

To make a bean accessible through the EL, use the @Named built-in qualifier:

import javax.enterprise.context.RequestScoped;
import javax.inject.Inject;
import javax.inject.Named;

@Named
@RequestScoped
public class Printer {

    @Inject @Informal Greeting greeting;
    ...
}

The @Named qualifier allows you to access the bean by using the bean name, with the first letter in lowercase. For example, a Facelets page would refer to the bean as printer.

You can specify an argument to the @Named qualifier to use a nondefault name:

@Named("MyPrinter")

With this annotation, the Facelets page would refer to the bean as MyPrinter.

23.10 Adding Setter and Getter Methods

To make the state of the managed bean accessible, you need to add setter and getter methods for that state. The createSalutation method calls the bean's greet method, and the getSalutation method retrieves the result.

Once the setter and getter methods have been added, the bean is complete. The final code looks like this:

package greetings;

import javax.enterprise.context.RequestScoped;
import javax.inject.Inject;
import javax.inject.Named;

@Named
@RequestScoped
public class Printer {

    @Inject @Informal Greeting greeting;
    
    private String name;
    private String salutation;

    public void createSalutation() {
        this.salutation = greeting.greet(name);
    }

    public String getSalutation() {
        return salutation;
    }

    public void setName(String name) {
        this.name = name;
    }

    public String getName() {
        return name;
    }
}

23.11 Using a Managed Bean in a Facelets Page

To use the managed bean in a Facelets page, you typically create a form that uses user interface elements to call its methods and display their results. This example provides a button that asks the user to type a name, retrieves the salutation, and then displays the text in a paragraph below the button:

<h:form id="greetme">
   <p><h:outputLabel value="Enter your name: " for="name"/>
      <h:inputText id="name" value="#{printer.name}"/></p>
   <p><h:commandButton value="Say Hello" 
                       action="#{printer.createSalutation}"/></p>
   <p><h:outputText value="#{printer.salutation}"/></p>
</h:form>

23.12 Injecting Objects by Using Producer Methods

Producer methods provide a way to inject objects that are not beans, objects whose values may vary at runtime, and objects that require custom initialization. For example, if you want to initialize a numeric value defined by a qualifier named @MaxNumber, you can define the value in a managed bean and then define a producer method, getMaxNumber, for it:

private int maxNumber = 100;
...
@Produces @MaxNumber int getMaxNumber() {
    return maxNumber;
}

When you inject the object in another managed bean, the container automatically invokes the producer method, initializing the value to 100:

@Inject @MaxNumber private int maxNumber;

If the value can vary at runtime, the process is slightly different. For example, the following code defines a producer method that generates a random number defined by a qualifier called @Random:

private java.util.Random random = 
    new java.util.Random( System.currentTimeMillis() );

java.util.Random getRandom() {
        return random;
}

@Produces @Random int next() {
    return getRandom().nextInt(maxNumber);
}

When you inject this object in another managed bean, you declare a contextual instance of the object:

@Inject @Random InstanceInteger randomInt;

You then call the get method of the Instance:

this.number = randomInt.get();

23.13 Configuring a CDI Application

When your beans are annotated with a scope type, the server recognizes the application as a bean archive and no additional configuration is required. The possible scope types for CDI beans are listed in Using Scopes.

CDI uses an optional deployment descriptor named beans.xml. Like other Java EE deployment descriptors, the configuration settings in beans.xml are used in addition to annotation settings in CDI classes. The settings in beans.xml override the annotation settings if there is a conflict. An archive must contain the beans.xml deployment descriptor only in certain limited situations, described in Chapter 25, "Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE: Advanced Topics".

For a web application, the beans.xml deployment descriptor, if present, must be in the WEB-INF directory. For EJB modules or JAR files, the beans.xml deployment descriptor, if present, must be in the META-INF directory.

23.14 Using the @PostConstruct and @PreDestroy Annotations with CDI Managed Bean Classes

CDI managed bean classes and their superclasses support the annotations for initializing and for preparing for the destruction of a bean. These annotations are defined in JSR 250: Common Annotations for the Java platform (http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=250).

23.14.1 To Initialize a Managed Bean Using the @PostConstruct Annotation

Initializing a managed bean specifies the lifecycle callback method that the CDI framework should call after dependency injection but before the class is put into service.

In the managed bean class or any of its superclasses, define a method that performs the initialization that you require.

Annotate the declaration of the method with the javax.annotation.PostConstruct annotation.

When the managed bean is injected into a component, CDI calls the method after all injection has occurred and after all initializers have been called.

Note:

As mandated in JSR 250, if the annotated method is declared in a superclass, the method is called unless a subclass of the declaring class overrides the method.

The UserNumberBean managed bean in The guessnumber-cdi CDI Example uses @PostConstruct to annotate a method that resets all bean fields:

@PostConstruct
public void reset () {
    this.minimum = 0;
    this.userNumber = 0;
    this.remainingGuesses = 0;
    this.maximum = maxNumber;
    this.number = randomInt.get();
}

23.14.2 To Prepare for the Destruction of a Managed Bean Using the @PreDestroy Annotation

Preparing for the destruction of a managed bean specifies the lifecycle call back method that signals that an application component is about to be destroyed by the container.

In the managed bean class or any of its superclasses, prepare for the destruction of the managed bean.

In this method, perform any cleanup that is required before the bean is destroyed, such as releasing a resource that the bean has been holding.

Annotate the declaration of the method with the javax.annotation.PreDestroy annotation.

CDI calls this method before starting to destroy the bean.

23.15 Further Information about CDI

For more information about CDI, see

Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE specification:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=346

An introduction to Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE:

http://docs.jboss.org/weld/reference/latest/en-US/html/

Dependency Injection for Java specification:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=330

Managed Beans specification, which is part of the Java Platform, Enterprise Edition 7 (Java EE 7) Specification:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=342

56 Concurrency Utilities for Java EE

This chapter describes Concurrency Utilities for Java EE, which are specified by JSR 236.

This chapter covers the following topics:

Concurrency Basics

Main Components of the Concurrency Utilities

Concurrency and Transactions

Concurrency and Security

The jobs Concurrency Example

The taskcreator Concurrency Example

Further Information about the Concurrency Utilities

56.1 Concurrency Basics

Concurrency is the concept of executing two or more tasks at the same time (in parallel). Tasks may include methods (functions), parts of a program, or even other programs. With current computer architectures, support for multiple cores and multiple processors in a single CPU is very common.

The Java Platform has always offered support for concurrent programming, which was the basis for implementing many of the services offered by Java EE containers. At Java SE 5, additional high-level API support for concurrency was provided by the java.util.concurrent package.

Prior to Java EE 7, there were no specific APIs that allowed enterprise developers to use concurrency utilities in a safely standard manner. The Java EE web and EJB containers instantiate objects using container-managed thread pools. Therefore, using Java SE concurrent APIs to instantiate Thread objects was strongly discouraged. If a developer creates a new (non-managed) Thread object, the container could not guarantee that other Java EE platform services (for example, transactions and security) would be part of this Thread.

56.1.1 Threads and Processes

The two main concurrency concepts are processes and threads.

Processes are primarily associated with applications running on the operating system (OS). A process has specific runtime resources to interact with the underlying OS and allocate other resources, such as its own memory, just as the JVM process does. A JVM is in fact a process.

The Java programming language and platform are primarily concerned with threads.

Threads share some features with processes, since both consume resources from the OS or the execution environment. But threads are easier to create and consume many fewer resources than a process.

Because threads are so lightweight, any modern CPU that has a couple of cores and a few gigabytes of RAM can handle thousands of threads in a single JVM process. The precise number of threads will depend on the combined output of the CPU, OS, and RAM available, as well as on correct configuration (tuning) of the JVM.

Although concurrent programming solves many problems and can improve performance for most applications, there are a number of situations where multiple execution lines (threads or processes) can cause major problems. These situations include the following:

Deadlocks

Thread starvation

Concurrent accessing of shared resources

Situations when the program generates incorrect data

56.2 Main Components of the Concurrency Utilities

Concurrent resources are managed objects that provide concurrency capabilities to Java EE applications. In GlassFish Server, you configure concurrent resources and then make them available for use by application components such as servlets and enterprise beans. Concurrent resources are accessed through JNDI lookup or resource injection.

The primary components of the concurrency utilities are as follows.

ManagedExecutorService: A managed executor service is used by applications to execute submitted tasks asynchronously. Tasks are executed on threads that are started and managed by the container. The context of the container is propagated to the thread executing the task.

For example, by using an ManagedExecutorService.submit() call, a task, such as the GenerateReportTask, could be submitted to execute at a later time and then, by using the Future object callback, retrieve the result when it becomes available.

ManagedScheduledExecutorService: A managed scheduled executor service is used by applications to execute submitted tasks asynchronously at specific times. Tasks are executed on threads that are started and managed by the container. The context of the container is propagated to the thread executing the task. The API provides the scheduling functionality that allows users to set a specific date/time for the Task execution programmatically in the application.

ContextService: A context service is used to create dynamic proxy objects that capture the context of a container and enable applications to run within that context at a later time or be submitted to a Managed Executor Service. The context of the container is propagated to the thread executing the task.

ManagedThreadFactory: A managed thread factory is used by applications to create managed threads. The threads are started and managed by the container. The context of the container is propagated to the thread executing the task. This object can also be used to provide custom factories for specific use cases (with custom Threads) and, for example, set specific/proprietary properties to these objects.

56.3 Concurrency and Transactions

The most basic operations for transactions are commit and rollback, but, in a distributed environment with concurrent processing, it can be difficult to guarantee that commit or rollback operations will be successfully processed, and the transaction can be spread among different threads, CPU cores, physical machines, and networks.

Ensuring that a rollback operation will successfully execute in such a scenario is crucial. Concurrency Utilities relies on the Java Transaction API (JTA) to implement and support transactions on its components through javax.transaction.UserTransaction, allowing application developers to explicitly manage transaction boundaries. More information is available in the JTA specification.

Optionally, context objects can begin, commit, or roll back transactions, but these objects cannot enlist in parent component transactions.

The following code snippet illustrates a Runnable task that obtains a UserTransaction and then starts and commits a transaction while interacting with other transactional components, such as an enterprise bean and a database:

public class MyTransactionalTask implements Runnable {
 
   UserTransaction ut = ... // obtained through JNDI or injection
 
   public void run() {
 
       // Start a transaction
       ut.begin();
 
       // Invoke a Service or an EJB
       myEJB.businessMethod();
 
       // Update a database entity using an XA JDBC driver
       myEJB.updateCustomer(customer);
 
       // Commit the transaction
       ut.commit();
 
   }
} 

56.4 Concurrency and Security

Concurrency Utilities for Java EE defers most security decisions to the application server implementation. If, however, the container supports a security context, that context can be propagated to the thread of execution. The ContextService can support several runtime behaviors, and the security attribute, if enabled, will propagate the container security principal.

56.5 The jobs Concurrency Example

This section describes a very basic example that shows how to use some of the basic concurrency features in an enterprise application. Specifically, this example uses one of the main components of Concurrency Utilities for Java EE, a Managed Executor Service.

The example demonstrates a scenario where a RESTful web service, exposed as a public API, is used to submit generic jobs for execution. These jobs are processed in the background. Each job prints a "Starting" and a "Finished" message at the beginning and end of the execution. Also, to simulate background processing, each job takes 10 seconds to execute.

The RESTful service exposes two methods:

/token: Exposed as a GET method that registers and returns valid API tokens

/process: Exposed as a POST method that receives a jobID query parameter, which is the identifier for the job to be executed, and a custom HTTP header named X-REST-API-Key, which will be used internally to validate requests with tokens

The token is used to differentiate the Quality of Service (QoS) offered by the API. Users that provide a token in a service request can process multiple concurrent jobs. However, users that do not provide a token can process only one job at a time. Since every job takes 10 seconds to execute, users that provide no token will be able to execute only one call to the service every 10 seconds. For users that provide a token, processing will be much faster.

This differentiation is made possible by the use of two different Managed Executor Services, one for each type of request.

56.5.1 Running the jobs Example

After configuring GlassFish Server by adding two Managed Executor Services, you can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the jobs example.

56.5.1.1 To Configure GlassFish Server for the Basic Concurrency Example

To configure GlassFish Server, follow these steps.

Open the Administration Console at http://localhost:4848.

Expand the Resources node.

Expand the Concurrent Resources node.

Click Managed Executor Services.

On the Managed Executor Services page, click New to open the New Managed Executor Services page.

In the JNDI Name field, enter MES_High to create the high-priority Managed Executor Service. Use the following settings (keep the default values for other settings):

Thread Priority: 10

Core Size: 2

Maximum Pool Size: 5

Task Queue Capacity: 2

Click OK.

On the On the Managed Executor Services page, click New again.

In the JNDI Name field, enter MES_Low to create the low-priority Managed Executor Service. Use the following settings (keep the default values for other settings):

Thread Priority: 1

Core Size: 1

Maximum Pool Size: 1

Task Queue Capacity: 0

Click OK.

56.5.1.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the jobs Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/concurrency

Select the jobs folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the jobs project and select Build.

This command builds and deploys the application.

56.5.1.3 To Build, Package, and Deploy the jobs Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/concurrency/jobs

Enter the following command to build and deploy the application:

mvn install

56.5.1.4 To Run the jobs Example and Submit Jobs with Low Priority

To run the example as a user who submits jobs with low priority, follow these steps:

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/jobs

In the Jobs Client page, enter the value 1 in the Enter a JobID field, enter nothing in the Enter a Token field, then click Submit Job.

The following message should be displayed at the bottom of the page:

Job 1 successfully submitted

The server log includes the following messages:

INFO:   Invalid or missing token! 
INFO:   Task started LOW-1
INFO:   Job 1 successfully submitted
INFO:   Task finished LOW-1

You submitted a job with low priority. This means that you cannot submit another job for 10 seconds. If you try to do so, the RESTful API will return a service unavailable (HTTP 503) response and the following message will be displayed at the bottom of the page:

Job 2 was NOT submitted

The server log will include the following messages:

INFO:   Invalid or missing token! 
INFO:   Job 1 successfully submitted
INFO:   Task started LOW-1
INFO:   Invalid or missing token! 
INFO:   Job 2 was NOT submitted
INFO:   Task finished LOW-1

56.5.1.5 To Run the jobs Example and Submit Jobs with High Priority

To run the example as a user who submits jobs with high priority, follow these steps:

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/jobs

In the Jobs Client page, enter a value of one to ten digits in the Enter a JobID field.

Click the here link on the line "Get a token here" to get a token. The page that displays the token will open in a new tab.

Copy the token and return to the Jobs Client page.

Paste the token in the Enter a Token field, then click Submit Job.

A message like the following should be displayed at the bottom of the page:

Job 11 successfully submitted

The server log includes the following messages:

INFO:   Token accepted. Execution with high priority.
INFO:   Task started HIGH-11
INFO:   Job 11 successfully submitted
INFO:   Task finished HIGH-11

You submitted a job with high priority. This means that you can submit multiple jobs, each with a token, and not face the 10 second per job restriction that the low priority submitters face. If you submit 3 jobs with tokens in rapid succession, messages like the following will be displayed at the bottom of the page:

Job 1 was submitted
Job 2 was submitted
Job 3 was submitted

The server log will include the following messages:

INFO:   Token accepted. Execution with high priority.
INFO:   Task started HIGH-1
INFO:   Job 1 successfully submitted
INFO:   Token accepted. Execution with high priority.
INFO:   Task started HIGH-2
INFO:   Job 2 successfully submitted
INFO:   Task finished HIGH-1
INFO:   Token accepted. Execution with high priority.
INFO:   Task started HIGH-3
INFO:   Job 3 successfully submitted
INFO:   Task finished HIGH-2
INFO:   Task finished HIGH-3

56.6 The taskcreator Concurrency Example

The taskcreator example demonstrates how to use Concurrency Utilities for Java EE to run tasks immediately, periodically, or after a fixed delay. This example provides a JavaServer Faces interface that enables users to submit tasks to be executed and displays information messages for each task. The example uses the Managed Executor Service to run tasks immediately and the Managed Scheduled Executor Service to run tasks periodically or after a fixed delay. (See Main Components of the Concurrency Utilities for information about these services.)

The taskcreator example consists of the following components.

A JavaServer Faces page (index.xhtml) that contains three elements: a form to submit tasks, a task execution log, and a form to cancel periodic tasks. This page submits Ajax requests to create and cancel tasks. This page also receives WebSocket messages, using JavaScript code to update the task execution log.

A CDI managed bean (TaskCreatorBean) that processes the requests from the JavaServer Faces page. This bean invokes the methods in TaskEJB to submit new tasks and to cancel periodic tasks.

An enterprise bean (TaskEJB) that obtains executor service instances using resource injection and submits tasks for execution. This bean is also a JAX-RS web service endpoint. The tasks send information messages to this endpoint.

A WebSocket endpoint (InfoEndpoint) that the enterprise bean uses to send information messages to the clients.

A task class (Task) that implements the Runnable interface. The run method in this class sends information messages to the web service endpoint in TaskEJB and sleeps for 1.5 seconds.

Figure 56-1 shows the architecture of the taskcreator example.

Figure 56-1 Architecture of the taskcreator Example

Description of "Figure 56-1 Architecture of the taskcreator Example"

The TaskEJB class obtains the default executor service objects from the application server as follows:

@Resource(name="java:comp/DefaultManagedExecutorService")
ManagedExecutorService mExecService;

@Resource(name="java:comp/DefaultManagedScheduledExecutorService")
ManagedScheduledExecutorService sExecService;

The submitTask method in TaskEJB uses these objects to submit tasks for execution as follows:

public void submitTask(Task task, String type) {
    /* Use the managed executor objects from the app server */
    switch (type) {
        case "IMMEDIATE":
            mExecService.submit(task);
            break;
        case "DELAYED":
            sExecService.schedule(task, 3, TimeUnit.SECONDS);
            break;
        case "PERIODIC":
            ScheduledFuture<?> fut;
            fut = sExecService.scheduleAtFixedRate(task, 0, 8, 
                    TimeUnit.SECONDS);
            periodicTasks.put(task.getName(), fut);
            break;
    }
}

For periodic tasks, TaskEJB keeps a reference to the ScheduledFuture object, so that the user can cancel the task at any time.

56.6.1 Running the taskcreator Example

This section describes how to build, package, deploy, and run the taskcreator example using NetBeans IDE or Maven.

56.6.1.1 To Build, Package, and Deploy the taskcreator Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/concurrency

Select the taskcreator folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the taskcreator project and select Build.

This command builds and deploys the application.

56.6.1.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the taskcreator Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/concurrency/taskcreator

Enter the following command to build and deploy the application:

mvn install

56.6.1.3 To Run the taskcreator Example

Open the following URL in a web browser:

http://localhost:8080/taskcreator/

The page contains a form to submit tasks, a task execution log, and a form to cancel periodic tasks.

Select the Immediate task type, enter a task name, and click the Submit button. Messages like the following appear in the task execution log:

12:40:47 - IMMEDIATE Task TaskA finished
12:40:45 - IMMEDIATE Task TaskA started

Select the Delayed (3 sec) task type, enter a task name, and click the Submit button. Messages like the following appear in the task execution log:

12:43:26 - DELAYED Task TaskB finished
12:43:25 - DELAYED Task TaskB started
12:43:22 - DELAYED Task TaskB submitted

Select the Periodic (8 sec) task type, enter a task name, and click the Submit button. Messages like the following appear in the task execution log:

12:45:25 - PERIODIC Task TaskC finished run #2
12:45:23 - PERIODIC Task TaskC started run #2
12:45:17 - PERIODIC Task TaskC finished run #1
12:45:15 - PERIODIC Task TaskC started run #1

You can add more than one periodic task. To cancel a periodic task, select it from the form and click Cancel Task.

56.7 Further Information about the Concurrency Utilities

For more information about concurrency, see

Concurrency Utilities for Java EE specification:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=236

Concurrency Utilities specification:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=166

Concurrency Lesson in The Java Tutorials:

http://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/essential/concurrency/

53 The Resource Adapter Examples

This chapter describes two examples that demonstrate how to use resource adapters in Java EE applications and how to implement simple resource adapters. The trading example shows how to use a simple custom client interface to connect to an EIS from a web application. The resource adapter in this example implements the outbound contract and the custom client interface. The traffic example shows how to use a message-driven bean (MDB) to process traffic information updates from an EIS. The resource adapter in this example implements the inbound and work management contracts.

The following topics are addressed here:

The trading Example

The traffic Example

53.1 The trading Example

The trading example demonstrates how to implement and use a simple outbound resource adapter that submits requests to a legacy EIS using a TCP socket. The example demonstrates the scenario in Figure 53-1 and consists of the following modules:

trading-eis: A Java SE program that simulates a legacy EIS

trading-rar: The outbound resource adapter implementation

trading-war: A web application that uses the resource adapter

trading-ear: An enterprise archive that contains the resource adapter and the web application

Figure 53-1 The trading Example

Description of "Figure 53-1 The trading Example"

The trading-eis module is an auxiliary project that resembles a legacy stock trading execution platform. It contains a Java SE program that listens for trading requests in plain text on a TCP socket. The program replies to trading requests with a status value, a confirmation number, and the dollar amounts for the requested shares and fees. For example, a request-response pair would look like this:

>> BUY 1000 ZZZZ MARKET
<< EXECUTED #1234567 TOTAL 50400.00 FEE 252.00

The trading-rar module implements the outbound contract of the Java EE Connector Architecture to submit requests and obtain responses from the legacy stock trading execution platform. The trading-rar module provides and implements a custom client interface for Java EE applications to use. This interface is simpler than the Common Client Interface (CCI).

The trading-war module is a web application with a JavaServer Faces interface and a managed bean. This application enables clients to submit trades to the EIS using the resource adapter provided by the trading-rar module. The trading-war module uses the custom client interface provided by the resource adapter to obtain connections to the EIS.

53.1.1 Using the Outbound Resource Adapter

In most cases, Java EE application developers use outbound resource adapters developed by a third party. Outbound resource adapters either implement the Common Client Interface (CCI) or provide a custom interface for applications to interact with the EIS. Outbound resource adapters provide Java EE applications with the following elements:

Connection factories

Connection handles

Other interfaces and objects specific to the EIS domain

Java EE applications obtain an instance of the connection factory via resource injection and then use the factory object to obtain connection handles to the EIS. The connection handles enable the application to make requests and obtain information from the EIS.

The trading-rar module provides a custom client interface that consists of the classes listed in Table 53-1.

Table 53-1 Classes and Interfaces in the javaeetutorial.trading.rar.api Package

API Component | Description

TradeOrder

|

Represents a trade order for the EIS

TradeResponse

|

Represents a response from the EIS to a trade request

TradeConnection

|

Represents a connection handle to the EIS

Provides a method for applications to submit trades to the EIS

TradeConnectionFactory

|

Enables applications to obtain connection handles to the EIS

TradeProcessingException

|

Indicates that a problem occurred processing a trade request

The ResourceAccessBean managed bean in the trading-war module configures a connection factory for the trading-rar resource adapter by using the @ConnectionFactoryDefinition annotation as follows:

@Named
@SessionScoped
@ConnectionFactoryDefinition(
    name = "java:comp/env/eis/TradeConnectionFactory",
    interfaceName = "javaeetutorial.trading.rar.api.TradeConnectionFactory",
    resourceAdapter = "#trading-rar",
    minPoolSize = 5,
    transactionSupport = 
            TransactionSupport.TransactionSupportLevel.NoTransaction
)
public class ResourceAccessBean implements Serializable { ... }

The name parameter specifies the JNDI name for the connection factory. This example registers the connection factory in the java:comp scope. You can use the ConnectionFactoryDefinition annotation to specify a different scope, such as java:global, java:app, or java:module. The AdministeredObjectDefinition annotation also enables you to register administered connector objects in the JNDI namespace.

The interfaceName parameter specifies the interface implemented by the connection factory included in the resource adapter. In this example, this is a custom interface.

The resourceAdapter parameter specifies the name of the resource adapter that contains the connection factory implementation. The # prefix in #trading-rar indicates that trading-rar is an embedded resource adapter that is bundled in the same EAR as this web application.

Note:

You can also configure a connection factory for a previously deployed outbound resource adapter using the administration commands from your application server. However, this is a vendor-specific procedure.

The managed bean obtains a connection factory object using resource injection as follows:

...
public class ResourceAccessBean implements Serializable {
    @Resource(lookup = "java:comp/env/eis/TradeConnectionFactory")
    private TradeConnectionFactory connectionFactory;
    ...
}

The managed bean uses the connection factory to obtain connection handles as follows:

TradeConnection connection = connectionFactory.getConnection();

The resource adapter returns a connection handle associated with a physical connection to the EIS. Once a connection handle is available, the managed bean submits a trade and obtains the response as follows:

TradeOrder order = new TradeOrder();
order.setNShares(1000);
order.setTicker(TradeOrder.Ticker.YYYY);
order.setOrderType(TradeOrder.OrderType.BUY);
order.setOrderClass(TradeOrder.OrderClass.MARKET);
...
try {
    TradeResponse response = connection.submitOrder(order);
    ...
} catch (TradeProcessingException ex) { ... }

53.1.2 Implementing the Outbound Resource Adapter

The trading-rar module implements the outbound contract and a custom client interface for the simple legacy stock trading platform EIS used in this example. The architecture of the outbound resource adapter is shown in Figure 53-2.

Figure 53-2 Architecture of the trading Example

Description of "Figure 53-2 Architecture of the trading Example"

The trading-rar module implements the interfaces listed in Table 53-2.

Table 53-2 Interfaces Implemented in the trading-rar Module

Package | Interface | Description

javax.resource.spi

|

ResourceAdapter

|

Defines the lifecycle methods of the resource adapter

javax.resource.spi

|

ManagedConnectionFactory

|

Defines a connection factory that the connection manager from the application server uses to obtain physical connections to the EIS

javax.resource.spi

|

ManagedConnection

|

Defines a physical connection to the EIS that can be managed by the connection manager

trading.rar.api

|

TradeConnectionFactory

|

Defines a connection factory that applications use to obtain connection handles

trading.rar.api

|

TradeConnection

|

Defines a connection handle that applications use to interact with the EIS

When the trading-ear archive is deployed and a connection pool resource is configured as described in Using the Outbound Resource Adapter, the application server creates TradeConnectionFactory objects that applications can obtain using resource injection. The TradeConnectionFactory implementation delegates creating connections to the connection manager provided by the application server.

The connection manager uses the ManagedConnectionFactory implementation to obtain physical connections to the EIS and maintains a pool of active physical connections. When an application requests a connection handle, the connection manager associates a connection from the pool with a new connection handle that the application can use. Connection pooling improves application performance and simplifies resource adapter development.

For more details, see the code and the comments in the trading-rar module.

53.1.3 Running the trading Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the trading example.

53.1.3.1 To Run the trading Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/connectors

Select the trading folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, expand the trading node.

Right-click the trading-eis module and select Open Project.

Right-click the trading-eis project and select Run.

The messages from the EIS appear in the Output tab:

Trade execution server listening on port 4004.

Right-click the trading-ear project and select Build.

This command packages the resource adapter and the web application in an EAR file and deploys it to GlassFish Server.

Open the following URL in a web browser:

http://localhost:8080/trading/

The web interface enables you to connect to the EIS and submit trades. The server log shows the requests from the web application and the call sequence that provides connection handles from the resource adapter.

Before undeploying the trading-ear application, close the trading-eis application from the status bar.

53.1.3.2 To Run the trading Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/connectors/trading/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the resource adapter and the web application into an EAR archive and deploys it to GlassFish Server.

In the same terminal window, go to the trading-eis directory:

cd trading-eis

Enter the following command to run the trade execution platform:

mvn exec:java

The messages from the EIS appear in the terminal window:

Trade execution server listening on port 4004.

Open the following URL in a web browser:

http://localhost:8080/trading/

The web interface enables you to connect to the EIS and submit trades. The server log shows the requests from the web application and the call sequence that provides connection handles from the resource adapter.

Before undeploying the trading-ear application, press Ctrl+C on the terminal window to close the trading-eis application.

53.2 The traffic Example

The traffic example demonstrates how to implement and use a simple inbound resource adapter that receives data from a legacy EIS using a TCP socket.

The example is in the tut-install/examples/connectors/traffic directory. See Chapter 2, "Using the Tutorial Examples," for basic information on building and running sample applications.

The example demonstrates the scenario in Figure 53-3 and consists of the following modules:

traffic-eis: A Java SE program that simulates an EIS

traffic-rar: The inbound resource adapter implementation

traffic-ejb: A message-driven bean that is the endpoint for incoming messages

traffic-war: A web application that displays information from the message-driven bean

traffic-ear: An enterprise archive that contains the resource adapter, the message-driven bean, and the web application

Figure 53-3 The traffic Example

Description of "Figure 53-3 The traffic Example"

The traffic-eis module is an auxiliary project that resembles a legacy traffic information system. It contains a Java SE program that sends traffic status updates for several cities to any subscribed client. The program sends the updates in JSON format over a TCP socket. For example, a traffic update looks like this:

{"report":[
    {"city":"City1", "access":"AccessA", "status":"GOOD"},
    {"city":"City1", "access":"AccessB", "status":"CONGESTED"},
    ...
    {"city":"City5", "access":"AccessE", "status":"SLOW"}
 ]}

The traffic-rar module implements the inbound contract of the Java EE Connector Architecture. This module subscribes to the traffic information system using the TCP port indicated by the configuration provided by the MDB and invokes the methods of the MDB to process traffic information updates.

The traffic-ejb module contains a message-driven bean that activates the resource adapter with a configuration parameter (the TCP port to subscribe to the traffic information system). The MDB contains a method to process the traffic information updates. This method filters the updates for a particular city and publishes the results to a Java Message Service (JMS) topic.

The traffic-war module contains a message-driven bean that receives filtered traffic information updates from the JMS topic asynchronously and sends them to the clients using a WebSocket endpoint.

53.2.1 Using the Inbound Resource Adapter

In most cases, Java EE application developers use inbound resource adapters developed by a third party. To use an inbound resource adapter, a Java EE application includes a message-driven bean with the following characteristics.

The MDB implements the business interface defined by the resource adapter.

The MDB specifies configuration parameters to activate the resource adapter.

The business interface defined by the resource adapter is not specified in the Java EE Connector Architecture; it is specific to the EIS.

The MDB in this example is defined as follows:

@MessageDriven(
    activationConfig = {
      @ActivationConfigProperty(propertyName = "port", 
                                propertyValue = "4008")
    }
)
public class TrafficMdb implements TrafficListener { ... }

The TrafficListener interface is defined in the API package of the resource adapter. The resource adapter requires the MDB to provide the port property.

When the MDB is deployed, it activates the traffic-rar resource adapter, which invokes the methods of the MDB to process traffic information updates. Then the MDB filters the updates for a particular city and publishes the results to a JMS topic.

In this particular example, the TrafficListener interface is empty. In addition to this interface, the resource adapter provides the TrafficCommand annotation and uses reflection to discover which methods in the MDB are decorated with this annotation:

@MessageDriven(...)
public class TrafficMdb implements TrafficListener {

    @TrafficCommand(name="report", info="Process report")
    public void processReport(String jsonReport) { ... }
    ...
}

This approach enables you to adapt the MDB to support new features in the EIS without having to modify the TrafficListener interface or the resource adapter module.

53.2.2 Implementing the Inbound Resource Adapter

The traffic-rar module implements the inbound resource adapter contract from the Java EE Connector Architecture for the simple traffic information system (EIS) used in this example. The architecture of the inbound resource adapter is shown in Figure 53-4.

Figure 53-4 Architecture of the traffic Example

Description of "Figure 53-4 Architecture of the traffic Example"

The traffic-rar module implements the interfaces listed in Table 53-3.

Table 53-3 Interfaces Implemented in the traffic-rar Module

Package | Interface | Description

javax.resource.spi

|

ResourceAdapter

|

Defines the lifecycle methods of the resource adapter.

javax.resource.spi

|

ActivationSpec

|

Defines the configuration parameters that the MDB provides to activate the inbound resource adapter.

javax.resource.spi

|

Work

|

The traffic service subscriber implements this interface from the work management contract to wait for traffic updates on a separate thread.

When an MDB activates the inbound resource adapter, the container invokes the endpointActivation method in the TrafficResourceAdapter class:

@Connector(...)
public class TrafficResourceAdapter implements ResourceAdapter, Serializable {
    ...
    @Override
    public void endpointActivation(MessageEndpointFactory endpointFactory, 
                                   ActivationSpec spec) 
                                   throws ResourceException {
        Class endpointClass = endpointFactory.getEndpointClass();
        /* this method is called from a new thread in the example: 
        MessageEndpoint endpoint = endpointFactory.createEndpoint(null); */
    }
}

The getEndpointClass method returns the Class type of the MDB performing the activation, which enables the resource adapter to use reflection to find methods annotated with @TrafficCommand in the MDB.

The createEndpoint method returns an instance of the MDB. The resource adapter uses this instance to invoke the methods of the MDB when it receives requests from the EIS.

After obtaining the message endpoint instance (MDB), the resource adapter uses the work management contract to create the traffic service subscriber thread that receives traffic updates from the EIS. The resource adapter obtains the WorkManager instance from the bootstrap context as follows:

WorkManager workManager;
...
@Override
public void start(BootstrapContext ctx) ... {
    workManager = ctx.getWorkManager();
}

The resource adapter schedules the traffic service subscriber thread using the work manager:

tSubscriber = new TrafficServiceSubscriber(tSpec, endpoint);
workManager.scheduleWork(tSubscriber);

The TrafficServiceSubscriber class implements the javax.resource.spi.Work interface from the work management contract.

The traffic service subscriber thread uses reflection to invoke the methods in the MDB:

private String callMdb(MessageEndpoint mdb, Method command, 
                       String... params) ... {
    String resp;
    /* this code contains proper exception handling in the sources */
    mdb.beforeDelivery(command);
    Object ret = command.invoke(mdb, (Object[]) params);
    resp = (String) ret;
    mdb.afterDelivery();
    return resp;
}

For more details, see the code and the comments in the traffic-rar module.

53.2.3 Running the traffic Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the traffic example.

53.2.3.1 To Run the traffic Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/connectors

Select the traffic folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, expand the traffic node.

Right-click the traffic-eis module and select Open Project.

Right-click the traffic-eis project and select Run.

The messages from the EIS appear on the Output tab:

Traffic EIS accepting connections on port 4008

In the Projects tab, right-click the traffic project and select Clean and Build.

This command builds and packages the resource adapter, the MDB, and the web application into an EAR archive and deploys it. The server log shows the call sequence that activates the resource adapter and the filtered traffic updates for City1.

Open the following URL in a web browser:

http://localhost:8080/traffic/

The web interface shows filtered traffic updates for City1 every few seconds.

After undeploying the traffic-ear application, close the traffic-eis application from the status bar.

53.2.3.2 To Run the traffic Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/connectors/traffic/traffic-eis/

Enter the following command in the terminal window:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the traffic EIS.

Enter the following command in the terminal window:

mvn exec:java

The messages from the EIS appear in the terminal window:

Traffic EIS accepting connections on port 4008

Leave this terminal window open.

Open a new terminal window and go to:

tut-install/examples/connectors/traffic/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the resource adapter, the MDB, and the web application into an EAR archive and deploys it. The server log shows the call sequence that activates the resource adapter and the filtered traffic updates for City1.

Open the following URL in a web browser:

http://localhost:8080/traffic/

The web interface shows the filtered traffic updates for City1 every few seconds.

After undeploying the traffic-ear application, press Ctrl+C in the first terminal window to close the traffic-eis application.

57 Duke's Bookstore Case Study Example

The Duke's Bookstore example is a simple e-commerce application that illustrates some of the more advanced features of JavaServer Faces technology in combination with Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE (CDI), enterprise beans, and the Java Persistence API. Users can select books from an image map, view the bookstore catalog, and purchase books. No security is used in this application.

The following topics are addressed here:

Design and Architecture of Duke's Bookstore

The Duke's Bookstore Interface

Running the Duke's Bookstore Case Study Application

57.1 Design and Architecture of Duke's Bookstore

Duke's Bookstore is a simple web application that uses many features of JavaServer Faces technology, in addition to other Java EE 7 features:

JavaServer Faces technology, as well as Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE (CDI)

A set of Facelets pages, along with a template, provides the user interface to the application.

CDI managed beans are associated with each of the Facelets pages.

A custom image map component on the front page allows you to select a book to enter the store. Each area of the map is represented by a JavaServer Faces managed bean. Text hyperlinks are also provided for accessibility.

Action listeners are registered on the image map and the text links. These listeners retrieve the ID value for the selected book and store it in the session map so it can be retrieved by the managed bean for the next page.

The h:dataTable tag is used to render the book catalog and shopping cart contents dynamically.

A custom converter is registered on the credit card field on the checkout page, bookcashier.xhtml, which also uses an f:validateRegEx tag to ensure that the input is correctly formatted.

A value-change listener is registered on the name field on bookcashier.xhtml. This listener saves the name in a parameter so the following page, bookreceipt.xhtml, can access it.

Enterprise beans: Local, no-interface-view stateless session bean and singleton bean

A Java Persistence API entity

The packages of the Duke's Bookstore application, located in the tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/src/main/java/javaeetutorial/dukesbookstore/ directory, are as follows:

components: Includes the custom UI component classes, MapComponent and AreaComponent

converters: Includes the custom converter class, CreditCardConverter

ejb: Includes two enterprise beans:

A singleton bean, ConfigBean, that initializes the data in the database

A stateless session bean, BookRequestBean, that contains the business logic to manage the entity

entity: Includes the Book entity class

exceptions: Includes three exception classes

listeners: Includes the event handler and event listener classes

model: Includes a model JavaBeans class

renderers: Includes the custom renderers for the custom UI component classes

web.managedbeans: Includes the managed beans for the Facelets pages

web.messages: Includes the resource bundle files for localized messages

57.2 The Duke's Bookstore Interface

This section provides additional detail regarding the components of the Duke's Bookstore example and how they interact.

57.2.1 The Book Java Persistence API Entity

The Book entity, located in the dukesbookstore.entity package, encapsulates the book data stored by Duke's Bookstore.

The Book entity defines attributes used in the example:

A book ID

The author's first name

The author's surname

The title

The price

Whether the book is on sale

The publication year

A description of the book

The number of copies in the inventory

The Book entity also defines a simple named query, findBooks.

57.2.2 Enterprise Beans Used in Duke's Bookstore

Two enterprise beans located in the dukesbookstore.ejb package provide the business logic for Duke's Bookstore.

BookRequestBean is a stateful session bean that contains the business methods for the application. The methods create, retrieve, and purchase books, and update the inventory for a book. To retrieve the books, the getBooks method calls the findBooks named query defined in the Book entity.

ConfigBean is a singleton session bean used to create the books in the catalog when the application is initially deployed. It calls the createBook method defined in BookRequestBean.

57.2.3 Facelets Pages and Managed Beans Used in Duke's Bookstore

The Duke's Bookstore application uses Facelets and its templating features to display the user interface. The Facelets pages interact with a set of CDI managed beans that act as backing beans, providing the underlying properties and methods for the user interface. The front page also interacts with the custom components used by the application.

The application uses the following Facelets pages, which are located in the tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/src/main/webapp/ directory.

bookstoreTemplate.xhtml: The template file, which specifies a header used on every page as well as the style sheet used by all the pages. The template also retrieves the language set in the web browser.

Uses the LocaleBean managed bean.

index.xhtml: Landing page, which lays out the custom map and area components using managed beans configured in the faces-config.xml file and allows the user to select a book and advance to the bookstore.xhtml page.

bookstore.xhtml: Page that allows the user to obtain details on the selected book or the featured book, to add either book to the shopping cart, and to advance to the bookcatalog.xhtml page.

Uses the BookstoreBean managed bean.

bookdetails.xhtml: Page that shows details on a book selected from bookstore.xhtml or other pages and allows the user to add the book to the cart and/or advance to the bookcatalog.xhtml page.

Uses the BookDetailsBean managed bean.

bookcatalog.xhtml: Page that displays the books in the catalog and allows the user to add books to the shopping cart, view the details for any book, view the shopping cart, empty the shopping cart, or purchase the books in the shopping cart.

Uses the BookstoreBean, CatalogBean, and ShoppingCart managed beans.

bookshowcart.xhtml: Page that displays the contents of the shopping cart and allows the user to remove items, view the details for an item, empty the shopping cart, purchase the books in the shopping cart, or return to the catalog.

Uses the ShowCartBean and ShoppingCart managed beans.

bookcashier.xhtml: Page that allows the user to purchase books, specify a shipping option, subscribe to newsletters, or join the Duke Fan Club with a purchase over a certain amount.

Uses the CashierBean and ShoppingCart managed beans.

bookreceipt.xhtml: Page that confirms the user's purchase and allows the user to return to the catalog page to continue shopping.

Uses the CashierBean managed bean.

bookordererror.xhtml: Page rendered by CashierBean if the bookstore has no more copies of a book that was ordered.

The application uses the following managed beans, which are located in the tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/src/main/java/javaeetutorial/dukesbookstore/web/managedbeans/ directory.

AbstractBean: Contains utility methods called by other managed beans.

BookDetailsBean: Backing bean for the bookdetails.xhtml page. Specifies the name details.

BookstoreBean: Backing bean for the bookstore.xhtml page. Specifies the name store.

CashierBean: Backing bean for the bookcashier.xhtml and bookreceipt.xhtml pages.

CatalogBean: Backing bean for the bookcatalog.xhtml page. Specifies the name catalog.

LocaleBean: Managed bean that retrieves the current locale; used on each page.

ShoppingCart: Backing bean used by the bookcashier.xhtml, bookcatalog.xhtml, and bookshowcart.xhtml pages. Specifies the name cart.

ShoppingCartItem: Contains methods called by ShoppingCart, CatalogBean, and ShowCartBean.

ShowCartBean: Backing bean for the bookshowcart.xhtml page. Specifies the name showcart.

57.2.4 Custom Components and Other Custom Objects Used in Duke's Bookstore

The map and area custom components for Duke's Bookstore, along with associated renderer, listener, and model classes, are defined in the following packages in the tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/src/main/java/javaeetutorial/dukesbookstore/ directory.

components: Contains the MapComponent and AreaComponent classes. See Creating Custom Component Classes.

listeners: Contains the AreaSelectedEvent class, along with other listener classes. See Handling Events for Custom Components.

model: Contains the ImageArea class. See Configuring Model Data for more information.

renderers: Contains the MapRenderer and AreaRenderer classes. See Delegating Rendering to a Renderer.

The tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/src/java/dukesbookstore/ directory also contains a custom converter and other custom listeners not specifically tied to the custom components.

converters: Contains the CreditCardConverter class. See Creating and Using a Custom Converter.

listeners: Contains the LinkBookChangeListener, MapBookChangeListener, and NameChanged classes. See Implementing an Event Listener.

57.2.5 Properties Files Used in Duke's Bookstore

The strings used in the Duke's Bookstore application are encapsulated into resource bundles to allow the display of localized strings in multiple locales. The properties files, located in the tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/src/main/java/javaeetutorial/dukesbookstore/web/messages/ directory, consist of a default file containing English strings and three additional files for other locales. The files are as follows:

Messages.properties: Default file, containing English strings

Messages_de.properties: File containing German strings

Messages_es.properties: File containing Spanish strings

Messages_fr.properties: File containing French strings

The language setting in the user's web browser determines which locale is used. The html tag in bookstoreTemplate.xhtml retrieves the language setting from the language property of LocaleBean:

<html lang="#{localeBean.language}"
...

For more information about resource bundles, see Chapter 20, "Internationalizing and Localizing Web Applications."

The resource bundle is configured as follows in the faces-config.xml file:

<application>
    <resource-bundle>
        <base-name>
            javaeetutorial.dukesbookstore.web.messages.Messages
        </base-name>
        <var>bundle</var>
    </resource-bundle>
    <locale-config>
        <default-locale>en</default-locale>
        <supported-locale>de</supported-locale>
        <supported-locale>es</supported-locale>
        <supported-locale>fr</supported-locale>
    </locale-config>
</application>

This configuration means that in the Facelets pages, messages are retrieved using the prefix bundle with the key found in the Messages_locale.properties file, as in the following example from the index.xhtml page:

<h:outputText style="font-weight:bold" 
              value="#{bundle.ChooseBook}" />

In Messages.properties, the key string is defined as follows:

ChooseBook=Choose a Book from our Catalog

57.2.6 Deployment Descriptors Used in Duke's Bookstore

The following deployment descriptors are used in Duke's Bookstore:

src/main/resources/META-INF/persistence.xml: The Java Persistence API configuration file

src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/bookstore.taglib.xml: The tag library descriptor file for the custom components

src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/faces-config.xml: The JavaServer Faces configuration file, which configures the managed beans for the map component as well as the resource bundles for the application

src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml: The web application configuration file

57.3 Running the Duke's Bookstore Case Study Application

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the Duke's Bookstore application.

57.3.1 To Build and Deploy Duke's Bookstore Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/case-studies

Select the dukes-bookstore folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the dukes-bookstore project and select Build.

This will build, package, and deploy Duke's Bookstore to GlassFish Server.

57.3.2 To Build and Deploy Duke's Bookstore Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server), as well as the database server (see Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds the application and packages it in a WAR file in the tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/target/ directory. It then deploys the application to GlassFish Server.

57.3.3 To Run Duke's Bookstore

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/dukes-bookstore/

On the Duke's Bookstore main page, click a book in the graphic, or click one of the links at the bottom of the page.

Use the pages in the application to view and purchase books.

36 Using Asynchronous Method Invocation in Session Beans

This chapter discusses how to implement asynchronous business methods in session beans and call them from enterprise bean clients.

The following topics are addressed here:

Asynchronous Method Invocation

The async Example Application

36.1 Asynchronous Method Invocation

Session beans can implement asynchronous methods, business methods where control is returned to the client by the enterprise bean container before the method is invoked on the session bean instance. Clients may then use the Java SE concurrency API to retrieve the result, cancel the invocation, and check for exceptions. Asynchronous methods are typically used for long-running operations, for processor-intensive tasks, for background tasks, to increase application throughput, or to improve application response time if the method invocation result isn't required immediately.

When a session bean client invokes a typical non-asynchronous business method, control is not returned to the client until the method has completed. Clients calling asynchronous methods, however, immediately have control returned to them by the enterprise bean container. This allows the client to perform other tasks while the method invocation completes. If the method returns a result, the result is an implementation of the java.util.concurrent.Future<V> interface, where "V" is the result value type. The Future<V> interface defines methods the client may use to check whether the computation is completed, wait for the invocation to complete, retrieve the final result, and cancel the invocation.

36.1.1 Creating an Asynchronous Business Method

Annotate a business method with javax.ejb.Asynchronous to mark that method as an asynchronous method, or apply @Asynchronous at the class level to mark all the business methods of the session bean as asynchronous methods. Session bean methods that expose web services can't be asynchronous.

Asynchronous methods must return either void or an implementation of the Future<V> interface. Asynchronous methods that return void can't declare application exceptions, but if they return Future<V>, they may declare application exceptions. For example:

@Asynchronous
public Future<String> processPayment(Order order) throws PaymentException { ... }

This method will attempt to process the payment of an order, and return the status as a String. Even if the payment processor takes a long time, the client can continue working, and display the result when the processing finally completes.

The javax.ejb.AsyncResult<V> class is a concrete implementation of the Future<V> interface provided as a helper class for returning asynchronous results. AsyncResult has a constructor with the result as a parameter, making it easy to create Future<V> implementations. For example, the processPayment method would use AsyncResult to return the status as a String:

@Asynchronous
public Future<String> processPayment(Order order) throws PaymentException {
    ...
    String status = ...;
    return new AsyncResult<String>(status);
}

The result is returned to the enterprise bean container, not directly to the client, and the enterprise bean container makes the result available to the client. The session bean can check whether the client requested that the invocation be cancelled by calling the javax.ejb.SessionContext.wasCancelled method. For example:

@Asynchronous
public Future<String> processPayment(Order order) throws PaymentException {
    ...
    if (SessionContext.wasCancelled()) {
        // clean up
    } else {
        // process the payment
    }
    ...
}

36.1.2 Calling Asynchronous Methods from Enterprise Bean Clients

Session bean clients call asynchronous methods just like non-asynchronous business methods. If the asynchronous method returns a result, the client receives a Future<V> instance as soon as the method is invoked. This instance can be used to retrieve the final result, cancel the invocation, check whether the invocation has completed, check whether any exceptions were thrown during processing, and check whether the invocation was cancelled.

36.1.2.1 Retrieving the Final Result from an Asynchronous Method Invocation

The client may retrieve the result using one of the Future<V>.get methods. If processing hasn't been completed by the session bean handling the invocation, calling one of the get methods will result in the client halting execution until the invocation completes. Use the Future<V>.isDone method to determine whether processing has completed before calling one of the get methods.

The get() method returns the result as the type specified in the type value of the Future<V> instance. For example, calling Future<String>.get() will return a String object. If the method invocation was cancelled, calls to get() result in a java.util.concurrent.CancellationException being thrown. If the invocation resulted in an exception during processing by the session bean, calls to get() result in a java.util.concurrent.ExecutionException being thrown. The cause of the ExecutionException may be retrieved by calling the ExecutionException.getCause method.

The get(long timeout, java.util.concurrent.TimeUnit unit) method is similar to the get() method, but allows the client to set a timeout value. If the timeout value is exceeded, a java.util.concurrent.TimeoutException is thrown. See the Javadoc for the TimeUnit class for the available units of time to specify the timeout value.

36.1.2.2 Cancelling an Asynchronous Method Invocation

Call the cancel(boolean mayInterruptIfRunning) method on the Future<V> instance to attempt to cancel the method invocation. The cancel method returns true if the cancellation was successful and false if the method invocation cannot be cancelled.

When the invocation cannot be cancelled, the mayInterruptIfRunning parameter is used to alert the session bean instance on which the method invocation is running that the client attempted to cancel the invocation. If mayInterruptIfRunning is set to true, calls to SessionContext.wasCancelled by the session bean instance will return true. If mayInterruptIfRunning is to set false, calls to SessionContext.wasCancelled by the session bean instance will return false.

The Future<V>.isCancelled method is used to check whether the method invocation was cancelled before the asynchronous method invocation completed by calling Future<V>.cancel. The isCancelled method returns true if the invocation was cancelled.

36.1.2.3 Checking the Status of an Asynchronous Method Invocation

The Future<V>.isDone method returns true if the session bean instance completed processing the method invocation. The isDone method returns true if the asynchronous method invocation completed normally, was cancelled, or resulted in an exception. That is, isDone indicates only whether the session bean has completed processing the invocation.

36.2 The async Example Application

The async example demonstrates how to define an asynchronous business method on a session bean and call it from a web client. This example contains two modules.

A web application (async-war) that contains a stateless session bean and a JavaServer Faces interface. The MailerBean stateless session bean defines an asynchronous method, sendMessage, which uses the JavaMail API to send an email to an specified email address.

An auxiliary Java SE program (async-smtpd) that simulates an SMTP server. This program listens on TCP port 3025 for SMTP requests and prints the email messages to the standard output (instead of delivering them).

The following section describes the architecture of the async-war module.

36.2.1 Architecture of the async-war Module

The async-war module consists of a single stateless session bean, MailerBean, and a JavaServer Faces web application front end that uses Facelets tags in XHTML files to display a form for users to enter the email address for the recipient of an email. The status of the email is updated when the email is finally sent.

The MailerBean session bean injects a JavaMail resource used to send an email message to an address specified by the user. The message is created, modified, and sent using the JavaMail API. The session bean looks like this:

@Named
@Stateless
public class MailerBean {
    @Resource(name="mail/myExampleSession")
    private Session session;
    private static final Logger logger = 
            Logger.getLogger(MailerBean.class.getName());

    @Asynchronous
    public Future<String> sendMessage(String email) {
        String status;
        try {
            Properties properties = new Properties();            properties.put("mail.smtp.port", "3025");            session = Session.getInstance(properties);                        Message message = new MimeMessage(session);
            message.setFrom();
            message.setRecipients(Message.RecipientType.TO,
                    InternetAddress.parse(email, false));
            message.setSubject("Test message from async example");
            message.setHeader("X-Mailer", "JavaMail");
            DateFormat dateFormatter = DateFormat
                    .getDateTimeInstance(DateFormat.LONG, DateFormat.SHORT);
            Date timeStamp = new Date();
            String messageBody = "This is a test message from the async "
                    + "example of the Java EE Tutorial. It was sent on "
                    + dateFormatter.format(timeStamp)
                    + ".";
            message.setText(messageBody);
            message.setSentDate(timeStamp);
            Transport.send(message);
            status = "Sent";
            logger.log(Level.INFO, "Mail sent to {0}", email);
        } catch (MessagingException ex) {
            logger.severe("Error in sending message.");
            status = "Encountered an error: " + ex.getMessage();
            logger.severe(ex.getMessage());
        }
        return new AsyncResult<>(status);
    }
}

The injected JavaMail resource can be configured through the GlassFish Server Administration Console, through a GlassFish Server administrative command, or through a resource configuration file packaged with the application. The resource configuration can be modified at runtime by the GlassFish Server administrator to use a different mail server or transport protocol.

The web client consists of a Facelets template, template.xhtml; two Facelets clients, index.xhtml and response.xhtml; and a JavaServer Faces managed bean, MailerManagedBean. The index.xhtml file contains a form for the target email address. When the user submits the form, the MailerManagedBean.send method is called. This method uses an injected instance of the MailerBean session bean to call MailerBean.sendMessage. The result is sent to the response.xhtml Facelets view.

36.2.2 Running the async Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the async example.

36.2.2.1 To Run the async Example Application Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/ejb

Select the async folder, select Open Required Projects, and click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the async-smtpd project and select Run.

The SMTP server simulator starts accepting connections. The async-smptd output tab shows the following message:

[Test SMTP server listening on port 3025]

In the Projects tab, right-click the async-war project and select Build.

This command configures the JavaMail resource using a GlassFish Server administrative command and builds, packages, and deploys the async-war module.

Open the following URL in a web browser window:

http://localhost:8080/async-war

In the web browser window, enter an email address and click Send email.

The MailerBean stateless bean uses the JavaMail API to deliver an email to the SMTP server simulator. The async-smptd output window in NetBeans IDE shows the resulting email message, including its headers.

To stop the SMTP server simulator, click the X button on the right side of the status bar in NetBeans IDE.

Delete the JavaMail session resource.

In the Services tab, expand the Servers node, then expand the GlassFish Server server node.

Expand the Resources node, then expand the JavaMail Sessions node.

Right-click mail/myExampleSession and select Unregister.

36.2.2.2 To Run the async Example Application Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/ejb/async/async-smtpd/

Enter the following command to build and package the SMTP server simulator:

mvn install

Enter the following command to start the STMP server simulator:

mvn exec:java

The following message appears:

[Test SMTP server listening on port 3025]

Keep this terminal window open.

In a new terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/ejb/async/async-war

Enter the following command to configure the JavaMail resource and to build, package, and deploy the async-war module:

mvn install

Open the following URL in a web browser window:

http://localhost:8080/async-war

In the web browser window, enter an email address and click Send email.

The MailerBean stateless bean uses the JavaMail API to deliver an email to the SMTP server simulator. The resulting email message appears on the first terminal window, including its headers.

To stop the SMTP server simulator, close the terminal window in which you issued the command to start the STMP server simulator.

To delete the JavaMail session resource, type the following command:

asadmin delete-javamail-resource mail/myExampleSession

34 Running the Enterprise Bean Examples

This chapter describes the EJB examples. Session beans provide a simple but powerful way to encapsulate business logic within an application. They can be accessed from remote Java clients, web service clients, and components running in the same server.

In Chapter 33, "Getting Started with Enterprise Beans", you built a stateless session bean named ConverterBean. This chapter examines the source code of four more session beans:

CartBean: a stateful session bean that is accessed by a remote client

CounterBean: a singleton session bean

HelloServiceBean: a stateless session bean that implements a web service

TimerSessionBean: a stateless session bean that sets a timer

The following topics are addressed here:

The cart Example

A Singleton Session Bean Example: counter

A Web Service Example: helloservice

Using the Timer Service

Handling Exceptions

34.1 The cart Example

The cart example represents a shopping cart in an online bookstore and uses a stateful session bean to manage the operations of the shopping cart. The bean's client can add a book to the cart, remove a book, or retrieve the cart's contents. To assemble cart, you need the following code:

Session bean class (CartBean)

Remote business interface (Cart)

All session beans require a session bean class. All enterprise beans that permit remote access must have a remote business interface. To meet the needs of a specific application, an enterprise bean may also need some helper classes. The CartBean session bean uses two helper classes, BookException and IdVerifier, which are discussed in the section Helper Classes.

The source code for this example is in the tut-install/examples/ejb/cart/ directory.

34.1.1 The Business Interface

The Cart business interface is a plain Java interface that defines all the business methods implemented in the bean class. If the bean class implements a single interface, that interface is assumed to the business interface. The business interface is a local interface unless it is annotated with the javax.ejb.Remote annotation; the javax.ejb.Local annotation is optional in this case.

The bean class may implement more than one interface. In that case, the business interfaces must either be explicitly annotated @Local or @Remote or be specified by decorating the bean class with @Local or @Remote. However, the following interfaces are excluded when determining whether the bean class implements more than one interface:

java.io.Serializable

java.io.Externalizable

Any of the interfaces defined by the javax.ejb package

The source code for the Cart business interface is as follows:

package javaeetutorial.cart.ejb;

import cart.util.BookException;
import java.util.List;
import javax.ejb.Remote;

@Remote
public interface Cart {
    public void initialize(String person) throws BookException;
    public void initialize(String person, String id) throws BookException;
    public void addBook(String title);
    public void removeBook(String title) throws BookException;
    public List<String> getContents();
    public void remove();
}

34.1.2 Session Bean Class

The session bean class for this example is called CartBean. Like any stateful session bean, the CartBean class must meet the following requirements.

The class is annotated @Stateful.

The class implements the business methods defined in the business interface.

Stateful session beans may also do the following.

Implement the business interface, a plain Java interface. It is good practice to implement the bean's business interface.

Implement any optional lifecycle callback methods, annotated @PostConstruct, @PreDestroy, @PostActivate, and @PrePassivate.

Implement any optional business methods annotated @Remove.

The source code for the CartBean class is as follows:

package javaeetutorial.cart.ejb;

import java.io.Serializable;
import java.util.ArrayList;
import java.util.List;
import javaeetutorial.cart.util.BookException;
import javaeetutorial.cart.util.IdVerifier;
import javax.ejb.Remove;
import javax.ejb.Stateful;

@Stateful
public class CartBean implements Cart {
    String customerId;
    String customerName;
    List<String> contents;

    @Override
    public void initialize(String person) throws BookException {
        if (person == null) {
            throw new BookException("Null person not allowed.");
        } else {
            customerName = person;
        }
        customerId = "0";
        contents = new ArrayList<>();
    }

    @Override
    public void initialize(String person, String id)
                 throws BookException {
        if (person == null) {
            throw new BookException("Null person not allowed.");
        } else {
            customerName = person;
        }

        IdVerifier idChecker = new IdVerifier();
        if (idChecker.validate(id)) {
            customerId = id;
        } else {
            throw new BookException("Invalid id: " + id);
        }

        contents = new ArrayList<>();
    }

    @Override
    public void addBook(String title) {
        contents.add(title);
    }

    @Override
    public void removeBook(String title) throws BookException {
        boolean result = contents.remove(title);
        if (result == false) {
            throw new BookException("\"" + title + " not in cart.");
        }
    }

    @Override
    public List<String> getContents() {
        return contents;
    }

    @Remove
    @Override
    public void remove() {
        contents = null;
    }
}

34.1.2.1 Lifecycle Callback Methods

A method in the bean class may be declared as a lifecycle callback method by annotating the method with the following annotations.

javax.annotation.PostConstruct: Methods annotated with @PostConstruct are invoked by the container on newly constructed bean instances after all dependency injection has completed and before the first business method is invoked on the enterprise bean.

javax.annotation.PreDestroy: Methods annotated with @PreDestroy are invoked after any method annotated @Remove has completed and before the container removes the enterprise bean instance.

javax.ejb.PostActivate: Methods annotated with @PostActivate are invoked by the container after the container moves the bean from secondary storage to active status.

javax.ejb.PrePassivate: Methods annotated with @PrePassivate are invoked by the container before it passivates the enterprise bean, meaning that the container temporarily removes the bean from the environment and saves it to secondary storage.

Lifecycle callback methods must return void and have no parameters.

34.1.2.2 Business Methods

The primary purpose of a session bean is to run business tasks for the client. The client invokes business methods on the object reference it gets from dependency injection or JNDI lookup. From the client's perspective, the business methods appear to run locally, although they run remotely in the session bean. The following code snippet shows how the CartClient program invokes the business methods:

cart.initialize("Duke DeEarl", "123");
...
cart.addBook("Bel Canto");
 ...
List<String> bookList = cart.getContents();
...
cart.removeBook("Gravity's Rainbow");

The CartBean class implements the business methods in the following code:

@Override
public void addBook(String title) {
   contents.add(title);
}

@Override
public void removeBook(String title) throws BookException {
   boolean result = contents.remove(title);
   if (result == false) {
      throw new BookException("\"" + title + "not in cart.");
   }
}

@Override
public List<String> getContents() {
   return contents;
}

The signature of a business method must conform to these rules.

The method name must not begin with ejb, to avoid conflicts with callback methods defined by the EJB architecture. For example, you cannot call a business method ejbCreate or ejbActivate.

The access control modifier must be public.

If the bean allows remote access through a remote business interface, the arguments and return types must be legal types for the Java Remote Method Invocation (RMI) API.

If the bean is a JAX-WS web service endpoint, the arguments and return types for the methods annotated @WebMethod must be legal types for JAX-WS.

If the bean is a JAX-RS resource, the arguments and return types for the resource methods must be legal types for JAX-RS.

The modifier must not be static or final.

The throws clause can include exceptions that you define for your application. The removeBook method, for example, throws a BookException if the book is not in the cart.

To indicate a system-level problem, such as the inability to connect to a database, a business method should throw a javax.ejb.EJBException. The container will not wrap application exceptions, such as BookException. Because EJBException is a subclass of RuntimeException, you do not need to include it in the throws clause of the business method.

34.1.3 The @Remove Method

Business methods annotated with javax.ejb.Remove in the stateful session bean class can be invoked by enterprise bean clients to remove the bean instance. The container will remove the enterprise bean after a @Remove method completes, either normally or abnormally.

In CartBean, the remove method is a @Remove method:

@Remove
@Override
public void remove() {
    contents = null;
}

34.1.4 Helper Classes

The CartBean session bean has two helper classes: BookException and IdVerifier. The BookException is thrown by the removeBook method, and the IdVerifier validates the customerId in one of the create methods. Helper classes may reside in an EJB JAR file that contains the enterprise bean class; a WAR file if the enterprise bean is packaged within a WAR; or an EAR file that contains an EJB JAR, a WAR file, or a separate library JAR file. In cart, the helper classes are included in a library JAR used by the application client and the EJB JAR.

34.1.5 Running the cart Example

Now you are ready to compile the remote interface (Cart.java), the enterprise bean class (CartBean.java), the client class (CartClient.java), and the helper classes (BookException.java and IdVerifier.java).

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the cart application.

34.1.5.1 To Run the cart Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/ejb

Select the cart folder.

Select the Open Required Projects check box.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the cart project and select Build.

This builds and packages the application into cart.ear, located in tut-install/examples/ejb/cart/cart-ear/target/, and deploys this EAR file to your GlassFish Server instance.

You will see the output of the cart-app-client application client in the Output tab:

...
Retrieving book title from cart: Infinite Jest
Retrieving book title from cart: Bel Canto
Retrieving book title from cart: Kafka on the Shore
Removing "Gravity's Rainbow" from cart.
Caught a BookException: "Gravity's Rainbow" not in cart.

34.1.5.2 To Run the cart Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/ejb/cart/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command compiles and packages the application into an EAR file, cart.ear, located in the target directory, and deploys the EAR to your GlassFish Server instance.

Then, the client stubs are retrieved and run. This is equivalent to running the following command:

appclient -client cart-ear/target/cart-earClient.jar

The client JAR, cart-earClient.jar, contains the application client class, the helper class BookException, and the Cart business interface.

When you run the client, the application client container injects any component references declared in the application client class, in this case the reference to the Cart enterprise bean.

You will see the output of the cart-app-client application client in the terminal window:

...
Retrieving book title from cart: Infinite Jest
Retrieving book title from cart: Bel Canto
Retrieving book title from cart: Kafka on the Shore
Removing "Gravity's Rainbow" from cart.
Caught a BookException: "Gravity's Rainbow" not in cart.

34.2 A Singleton Session Bean Example: counter

The counter example demonstrates how to create a singleton session bean.

34.2.1 Creating a Singleton Session Bean

The javax.ejb.Singleton annotation is used to specify that the enterprise bean implementation class is a singleton session bean:

@Singleton
public class SingletonBean { ... }

34.2.1.1 Initializing Singleton Session Beans

The EJB container is responsible for determining when to initialize a singleton session bean instance unless the singleton session bean implementation class is annotated with the javax.ejb.Startup annotation. In this case, sometimes called eager initialization, the EJB container must initialize the singleton session bean upon application startup. The singleton session bean is initialized before the EJB container delivers client requests to any enterprise beans in the application. This allows the singleton session bean to perform, for example, application startup tasks.

The following singleton session bean stores the status of an application and is eagerly initialized:

@Startup
@Singleton
public class StatusBean {
  private String status;

  @PostConstruct
  void init {
    status = "Ready";
  }
  ...
}

Sometimes multiple singleton session beans are used to initialize data for an application and therefore must be initialized in a specific order. In these cases, use the javax.ejb.DependsOn annotation to declare the startup dependencies of the singleton session bean. The @DependsOn annotation's value attribute is one or more strings that specify the name of the target singleton session bean. If more than one dependent singleton bean is specified in @DependsOn, the order in which they are listed is not necessarily the order in which the EJB container will initialize the target singleton session beans.

The following singleton session bean, PrimaryBean, should be started up first:

@Singleton
public class PrimaryBean { ... }

SecondaryBean depends on PrimaryBean:

@Singleton
@DependsOn("PrimaryBean")
public class SecondaryBean { ... }

This guarantees that the EJB container will initialize PrimaryBean before SecondaryBean.

The following singleton session bean, TertiaryBean, depends on PrimaryBean and SecondaryBean:

@Singleton
@DependsOn({"PrimaryBean", "SecondaryBean"})
public class TertiaryBean { ... }

SecondaryBean explicitly requires PrimaryBean to be initialized before it is initialized, through its own @DependsOn annotation. In this case, the EJB container will first initialize PrimaryBean, then SecondaryBean, and finally TertiaryBean.

If, however, SecondaryBean did not explicitly depend on PrimaryBean, the EJB container may initialize either PrimaryBean or SecondaryBean first. That is, the EJB container could initialize the singletons in the following order: SecondaryBean, PrimaryBean, TertiaryBean.

34.2.1.2 Managing Concurrent Access in a Singleton Session Bean

Singleton session beans are designed for concurrent access, situations in which many clients need to access a single instance of a session bean at the same time. A singleton's client needs only a reference to a singleton in order to invoke any business methods exposed by the singleton and doesn't need to worry about any other clients that may be simultaneously invoking business methods on the same singleton.

When creating a singleton session bean, concurrent access to the singleton's business methods can be controlled in two ways: container-managed concurrency and bean-managed concurrency.

The javax.ejb.ConcurrencyManagement annotation is used to specify container-managed or bean-managed concurrency for the singleton. With @ConcurrencyManagement, a type attribute must be set to either javax.ejb.ConcurrencyManagementType.CONTAINER or javax.ejb.ConcurrencyManagementType.BEAN. If no @ConcurrencyManagement annotation is present on the singleton implementation class, the EJB container default of container-managed concurrency is used.

Container-Managed Concurrency

If a singleton uses container-managed concurrency, the EJB container controls client access to the business methods of the singleton. The javax.ejb.Lock annotation and a javax.ejb.LockType type are used to specify the access level of the singleton's business methods or @Timeout methods. The LockType enumerated types are READ and WRITE.

Annotate a singleton's business or timeout method with @Lock(LockType.READ) if the method can be concurrently accessed, or shared, with many clients. Annotate the business or timeout method with @Lock(LockType.WRITE) if the singleton session bean should be locked to other clients while a client is calling that method. Typically, the @Lock(LockType.WRITE) annotation is used when clients are modifying the state of the singleton.

Annotating a singleton class with @Lock specifies that all the business methods and any timeout methods of the singleton will use the specified lock type unless they explicitly set the lock type with a method-level @Lock annotation. If no @Lock annotation is present on the singleton class, the default lock type, @Lock(LockType.WRITE), is applied to all business and timeout methods.

The following example shows how to use the @ConcurrencyManagement, @Lock(LockType.READ), and @Lock(LockType.WRITE) annotations for a singleton that uses container-managed concurrency.

Although by default singletons use container-managed concurrency, the @ConcurrencyManagement(CONTAINER) annotation may be added at the class level of the singleton to explicitly set the concurrency management type:

@ConcurrencyManagement(ConcurrencyManagementType.CONTAINER) 
@Singleton
public class ExampleSingletonBean {
  private String state;

  @Lock(LockType.READ)
  public String getState() {
    return state;
  }

  @Lock(LockType.WRITE)
  public void setState(String newState) {
    state = newState;
  }
}

The getState method can be accessed by many clients at the same time because it is annotated with @Lock(LockType.READ). When the setState method is called, however, all the methods in ExampleSingletonBean will be locked to other clients because setState is annotated with @Lock(LockType.WRITE). This prevents two clients from attempting to simultaneously change the state variable of ExampleSingletonBean.

The getData and getStatus methods in the following singleton are of type READ, and the setStatus method is of type WRITE:

@Singleton
@Lock(LockType.READ)
public class SharedSingletonBean {
  private String data;
  private String status;

  public String getData() {
    return data;
  }

  public String getStatus() {
    return status;
  }

  @Lock(LockType.WRITE)
  public void setStatus(String newStatus) {
    status = newStatus;
  }
}

If a method is of locking type WRITE, client access to all the singleton's methods is blocked until the current client finishes its method call or an access timeout occurs. When an access timeout occurs, the EJB container throws a javax.ejb.ConcurrentAccessTimeoutException. The javax.ejb.AccessTimeout annotation is used to specify the number of milliseconds before an access timeout occurs. If added at the class level of a singleton, @AccessTimeout specifies the access timeout value for all methods in the singleton unless a method explicitly overrides the default with its own @AccessTimeout annotation.

The @AccessTimeout annotation can be applied to both @Lock(LockType.READ) and @Lock(LockType.WRITE) methods. The @AccessTimeout annotation has one required element, value, and one optional element, unit. By default, the value is specified in milliseconds. To change the value unit, set unit to one of the java.util.concurrent.TimeUnit constants: NANOSECONDS, MICROSECONDS, MILLISECONDS, or SECONDS.

The following singleton has a default access timeout value of 120,000 milliseconds, or 2 minutes. The doTediousOperation method overrides the default access timeout and sets the value to 360,000 milliseconds, or 6 minutes:

@Singleton
@AccessTimeout(value=120000)
public class StatusSingletonBean {
  private String status;

  @Lock(LockType.WRITE)
  public void setStatus(String new Status) {
    status = newStatus;
  }

  @Lock(LockType.WRITE)
  @AccessTimeout(value=360000)
  public void doTediousOperation {
    ...
  }
}

The following singleton has a default access timeout value of 60 seconds, specified using the TimeUnit.SECONDS constant:

@Singleton
@AccessTimeout(value=60, unit=TimeUnit.SECONDS)
public class StatusSingletonBean { ... }

Bean-Managed Concurrency

Singletons that use bean-managed concurrency allow full concurrent access to all the business and timeout methods in the singleton. The developer of the singleton is responsible for ensuring that the state of the singleton is synchronized across all clients. Developers who create singletons with bean-managed concurrency are allowed to use the Java programming language synchronization primitives, such as synchronization and volatile, to prevent errors during concurrent access.

Add a @ConcurrencyManagement annotation with the type set to ConcurrencyManagementType.BEAN at the class level of the singleton to specify bean-managed concurrency:

@ConcurrencyManagement(ConcurrencyManagementType.BEAN) 
@Singleton
public class AnotherSingletonBean { ... }

34.2.1.3 Handling Errors in a Singleton Session Bean

If a singleton session bean encounters an error when initialized by the EJB container, that singleton instance will be destroyed.

Unlike other enterprise beans, once a singleton session bean instance is initialized, it is not destroyed if the singleton's business or lifecycle methods cause system exceptions. This ensures that the same singleton instance is used throughout the application lifecycle.

34.2.2 The Architecture of the counter Example

The counter example consists of a singleton session bean, CounterBean, and a JavaServer Faces Facelets web front end.

CounterBean is a simple singleton with one method, getHits, that returns an integer representing the number of times a web page has been accessed. Here is the code of CounterBean:

package javaeetutorial.counter.ejb;

import javax.ejb.Singleton;

/**
 * CounterBean is a simple singleton session bean that records the number
 * of hits to a web page.
 */
@Singleton
public class CounterBean {
    private int hits = 1;

    // Increment and return the number of hits
    public int getHits() {
        return hits++;
    }
}

The @Singleton annotation marks CounterBean as a singleton session bean. CounterBean uses a local, no-interface view.

CounterBean uses the EJB container's default metadata values for singletons to simplify the coding of the singleton implementation class. There is no @ConcurrencyManagement annotation on the class, so the default of container-managed concurrency access is applied. There is no @Lock annotation on the class or business method, so the default of @Lock(WRITE) is applied to the only business method, getHits.

The following version of CounterBean is functionally equivalent to the preceding version:

package javaeetutorial.counter.ejb;

import javax.ejb.Singleton;
import javax.ejb.ConcurrencyManagement;
import static javax.ejb.ConcurrencyManagementType.CONTAINER;
import javax.ejb.Lock;
import javax.ejb.LockType.WRITE;

/**
 * CounterBean is a simple singleton session bean that records the number
 * of hits to a web page.
 */
@Singleton
@ConcurrencyManagement(CONTAINER)
public class CounterBean {
    private int hits = 1;

    // Increment and return the number of hits
    @Lock(WRITE)
    public int getHits() {
        return hits++;
    }
}

The web front end of counter consists of a JavaServer Faces managed bean, Count.java, that is used by the Facelets XHTML files template.xhtml and index.xhtml. The Count JavaServer Faces managed bean obtains a reference to CounterBean through dependency injection. Count defines a hitCount JavaBeans property. When the getHitCount getter method is called from the XHTML files, CounterBean's getHits method is called to return the current number of page hits.

Here's the Count managed bean class:

@Named
@ConversationScoped
public class Count implements Serializable {
    @EJB
    private CounterBean counterBean;

    private int hitCount;

    public Count() {
        this.hitCount = 0;
    }

    public int getHitCount() {
        hitCount = counterBean.getHits();
        return hitCount;
    }

    public void setHitCount(int newHits) {
        this.hitCount = newHits;
    }
}

The template.xhtml and index.xhtml files are used to render a Facelets view that displays the number of hits to that view. The index.xhtml file uses an expression language statement, #{count.hitCount}, to access the hitCount property of the Count managed bean. Here is the content of index.xhtml:

<html lang="en"
      xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:ui="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/facelets"
      xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html">
    <ui:composition template="/template.xhtml">
        <ui:define name="title">
            This page has been accessed #{count.hitCount} time(s).
        </ui:define>
        <ui:define name="body">
            Hooray!
        </ui:define>
    </ui:composition>
</html>

34.2.3 Running the counter Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the counter example.

34.2.3.1 To Run the counter Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/ejb

Select the counter folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the counter project and select Run.

A web browser will open the URL http://localhost:8080/counter, which displays the number of hits.

Reload the page to see the hit count increment.

34.2.3.2 To Run the counter Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/ejb/counter/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This will build and deploy counter to your GlassFish Server instance.

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/counter

Reload the page to see the hit count increment.

34.3 A Web Service Example: helloservice

This example demonstrates a simple web service that generates a response based on information received from the client. HelloServiceBean is a stateless session bean that implements a single method: sayHello. This method matches the sayHello method invoked by the client described in A Simple JAX-WS Application Client.

34.3.1 The Web Service Endpoint Implementation Class

HelloServiceBean is the endpoint implementation class, typically the primary programming artifact for enterprise bean web service endpoints. The web service endpoint implementation class has the following requirements.

The class must be annotated with either the javax.jws.WebService or the javax.jws.WebServiceProvider annotation.

The implementing class may explicitly reference an SEI through the endpointInterface element of the @WebService annotation but is not required to do so. If no endpointInterface is specified in @WebService, an SEI is implicitly defined for the implementing class.

The business methods of the implementing class must be public and must not be declared static or final.

Business methods that are exposed to web service clients must be annotated with javax.jws.WebMethod.

Business methods that are exposed to web service clients must have JAXB-compatible parameters and return types. See the list of JAXB default data type bindings at Types Supported by JAX-WS.

The implementing class must not be declared final and must not be abstract.

The implementing class must have a default public constructor.

The endpoint class must be annotated @Stateless.

The implementing class must not define the finalize method.

The implementing class may use the javax.annotation.PostConstruct or javax.annotation.PreDestroy annotations on its methods for lifecycle event callbacks.

The @PostConstruct method is called by the container before the implementing class begins responding to web service clients.

The @PreDestroy method is called by the container before the endpoint is removed from operation.

34.3.2 Stateless Session Bean Implementation Class

The HelloServiceBean class implements the sayHello method, which is annotated @WebMethod. The source code for the HelloServiceBean class is as follows:

package javaeetutorial.helloservice.ejb;

import javax.ejb.Stateless;
import javax.jws.WebMethod;
import javax.jws.WebService;

@Stateless
@WebService
public class HelloServiceBean {
    private final String message = "Hello, ";

    public void HelloServiceBean() {}

    @WebMethod
    public String sayHello(String name) {
        return message + name + ".";
    }
}

34.3.3 Running the helloservice Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, and deploy the helloservice example. You can then use the Administration Console to test the web service endpoint methods.

34.3.3.1 To Build, Package, and Deploy the helloservice Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/ejb

Select the helloservice folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the helloservice project and select Build.

This builds and packages the application into helloservice.ear, located in tut-install/examples/ejb/helloservice/target/, and deploys this EAR file to GlassFish Server.

34.3.3.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the helloservice Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/ejb/helloservice/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This compiles the source files and packages the application into an EJB JAR file located at tut-install/examples/ejb/helloservice/target/helloservice.jar. Then the EJB JAR file is deployed to GlassFish Server.

Upon deployment, GlassFish Server generates additional artifacts required for web service invocation, including the WSDL file.

34.3.3.3 To Test the Service without a Client

The GlassFish Server Administration Console allows you to test the methods of a web service endpoint. To test the sayHello method of HelloServiceBean, follow these steps.

Open the Administration Console by opening the following URL in a web browser:

http://localhost:4848/

In the navigation tree, select the Applications node.

In the Applications table, click the helloservice link.

In the Modules and Components table, click the View Endpoint link.

On the Web Service Endpoint Information page, click the Tester link:

/HelloServiceBeanService/HelloServiceBean?Tester

On the Web Service Test Links page, click the non-secure link (the one that specifies port 8080).

On the HelloServiceBeanService Web Service Tester page, under Methods, enter a name as the parameter to the sayHello method.

Click sayHello.

The sayHello Method invocation page opens. Under Method returned, you'll see the response from the endpoint.

34.4 Using the Timer Service

Applications that model business work flows often rely on timed notifications. The timer service of the enterprise bean container enables you to schedule timed notifications for all types of enterprise beans except for stateful session beans. You can schedule a timed notification to occur according to a calendar schedule, at a specific time, after a duration of time, or at timed intervals. For example, you could set timers to go off at 10:30 a.m. on May 23, in 30 days, or every 12 hours.

Enterprise bean timers are either programmatic timers or automatic timers. Programmatic timers are set by explicitly calling one of the timer creation methods of the TimerService interface. Automatic timers are created upon the successful deployment of an enterprise bean that contains a method annotated with the javax.ejb.Schedule or javax.ejb.Schedules annotations.

34.4.1 Creating Calendar-Based Timer Expressions

Timers can be set according to a calendar-based schedule, expressed using a syntax similar to the UNIX cron utility. Both programmatic and automatic timers can use calendar-based timer expressions. Table 34-1 shows the calendar-based timer attributes.

Table 34-1 Calendar-Based Timer Attributes

Attribute | Description | Default Value | Allowable Values and Examples

second

|

One or more seconds within a minute

|

0

|

0 to 59. For example: second="30".

minute

|

One or more minutes within an hour

|

0

|

0 to 59. For example: minute="15".

hour

|

One or more hours within a day

|

0

|

0 to 23. For example: hour="13".

dayOfWeek

|

One or more days within a week

|

*

|

0 to 7 (both 0 and 7 refer to Sunday). For example: dayOfWeek="3".

Sun, Mon, Tue, Wed, Thu, Fri, Sat. For example: dayOfWeek="Mon".

dayOfMonth

|

One or more days within a month

|

*

|

1 to 31. For example: dayOfMonth="15".

7 to 1 (a negative number means the nth day or days before the end of the month). For example: dayOfMonth="3".

Last. For example: dayOfMonth="Last".

[1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th, Last] [Sun, Mon, Tue, Wed, Thu, Fri, Sat]. For example: dayOfMonth="2nd Fri".

month

|

One or more months within a year

|

*

|

1 to 12. For example: month="7".

Jan, Feb, Mar, Apr, May, Jun, Jul, Aug, Sep, Oct, Nov, Dec. For example: month="July".

year

|

A particular calendar year

|

*

|

A four-digit calendar year. For example: year="2011".

34.4.1.1 Specifying Multiple Values in Calendar Expressions

You can specify multiple values in calendar expressions, as described in the following sections.

Using Wildcards in Calendar Expressions

Setting an attribute to an asterisk symbol (*) represents all allowable values for the attribute.

The following expression represents every minute:

minute="*"

The following expression represents every day of the week:

dayOfWeek="*"

Specifying a List of Values

To specify two or more values for an attribute, use a comma (,) to separate the values. A range of values is allowed as part of a list. Wildcards and intervals, however, are not allowed.

Duplicates within a list are ignored.

The following expression sets the day of the week to Tuesday and Thursday:

dayOfWeek="Tue, Thu"

The following expression represents 4:00 a.m., every hour from 9:00 a.m. to 5:00 p.m. using a range, and 10:00 p.m.:

hour="4,9-17,22"

Specifying a Range of Values

Use a dash character (-) to specify an inclusive range of values for an attribute. Members of a range cannot be wildcards, lists, or intervals. A range of the form x-x, is equivalent to the single-valued expression x. A range of the form x-y where x is greater than y is equivalent to the expression x-maximumvalue, minimumvalue-y. That is, the expression begins at x, rolls over to the beginning of the allowable values, and continues up to y.

The following expression represents 9:00 a.m. to 5:00 p.m.:

hour="9-17"

The following expression represents Friday through Monday:

dayOfWeek="5-1"

The following expression represents the twenty-fifth day of the month to the end of the month, and the beginning of the month to the fifth day of the month:

dayOfMonth="25-5"

It is equivalent to the following expression:

dayOfMonth="25-Last,1-5"

Specifying Intervals

The forward slash (/) constrains an attribute to a starting point and an interval and is used to specify every N seconds, minutes, or hours within the minute, hour, or day. For an expression of the form x/y, x represents the starting point and y represents the interval. The wildcard character may be used in the x position of an interval and is equivalent to setting x to 0.

Intervals may be set only for second, minute, and hour attributes.

The following expression represents every 10 minutes within the hour:

minute="*/10"

It is equivalent to:

minute="0,10,20,30,40,50"

The following expression represents every 2 hours starting at noon:

hour="12/2"

34.4.2 Programmatic Timers

When a programmatic timer expires (goes off), the container calls the method annotated @Timeout in the bean's implementation class. The @Timeout method contains the business logic that handles the timed event.

34.4.2.1 The @Timeout Method

Methods annotated @Timeout in the enterprise bean class must return void and optionally take a javax.ejb.Timer object as the only parameter. They may not throw application exceptions:

@Timeout
public void timeout(Timer timer) {
    System.out.println("TimerBean: timeout occurred");
}

34.4.2.2 Creating Programmatic Timers

To create a timer, the bean invokes one of the create methods of the TimerService interface. These methods allow single-action, interval, or calendar-based timers to be created.

For single-action or interval timers, the expiration of the timer can be expressed as either a duration or an absolute time. The duration is expressed as a the number of milliseconds before a timeout event is triggered. To specify an absolute time, create a java.util.Date object and pass it to the TimerService.createSingleActionTimer or the TimerService.createTimer method.

The following code sets a programmatic timer that will expire in 1 minute (60,000 milliseconds):

long duration = 60000;
Timer timer =
    timerService.createSingleActionTimer(duration, new TimerConfig());

The following code sets a programmatic timer that will expire at 12:05 p.m. on May 1, 2015, specified as a java.util.Date:

SimpleDateFormatter formatter = 
    new SimpleDateFormatter("MM/dd/yyyy 'at' HH:mm");
Date date = formatter.parse("05/01/2015 at 12:05");
Timer timer = timerService.createSingleActionTimer(date, new TimerConfig());

For calendar-based timers, the expiration of the timer is expressed as a javax.ejb.ScheduleExpression object, passed as a parameter to the TimerService.createCalendarTimer method. The ScheduleExpression class represents calendar-based timer expressions and has methods that correspond to the attributes described in Creating Calendar-Based Timer Expressions.

The following code creates a programmatic timer using the ScheduleExpression helper class:

ScheduleExpression schedule = new ScheduleExpression();
schedule.dayOfWeek("Mon");
schedule.hour("12-17, 23");
Timer timer = timerService.createCalendarTimer(schedule);

For details on the method signatures, see the TimerService API documentation at http://docs.oracle.com/javaee/7/api/javax/ejb/TimerService.html.

The bean described in The timersession Example creates a timer as follows:

Timer timer = timerService.createTimer(intervalDuration,
        "Created new programmatic timer");

In the timersession example, the method that calls createTimer is invoked in a business method, which is called by a client.

Timers are persistent by default. If the server is shut down or crashes, persistent timers are saved and will become active again when the server is restarted. If a persistent timer expires while the server is down, the container will call the @Timeout method when the server is restarted.

Nonpersistent programmatic timers are created by calling TimerConfig.setPersistent(false) and passing the TimerConfig object to one of the timer-creation methods.

The Date and long parameters of the createTimer methods represent time with the resolution of milliseconds. However, because the timer service is not intended for real-time applications, a callback to the @Timeout method might not occur with millisecond precision. The timer service is for business applications, which typically measure time in hours, days, or longer durations.

34.4.3 Automatic Timers

Automatic timers are created by the EJB container when an enterprise bean that contains methods annotated with the @Schedule or @Schedules annotations is deployed. An enterprise bean can have multiple automatic timeout methods, unlike a programmatic timer, which allows only one method annotated with the @Timeout annotation in the enterprise bean class.

Automatic timers can be configured through annotations or through the ejb-jar.xml deployment descriptor.

Adding a @Schedule annotation on an enterprise bean marks that method as a timeout method according to the calendar schedule specified in the attributes of @Schedule.

The @Schedule annotation has elements that correspond to the calendar expressions detailed in Creating Calendar-Based Timer Expressions and the persistent, info, and timezone elements.

The optional persistent element takes a Boolean value and is used to specify whether the automatic timer should survive a server restart or crash. By default, all automatic timers are persistent.

The optional timezone element is used to specify that the automatic timer is associated with a particular time zone. If set, this element will evaluate all timer expressions in relation to the specified time zone, regardless of the time zone in which the EJB container is running. By default, all automatic timers set are in relation to the default time zone of the server.

The optional info element is used to set an informational description of the timer. A timer's information can be retrieved later by using Timer.getInfo.

The following timeout method uses @Schedule to set a timer that will expire every Sunday at midnight:

@Schedule(dayOfWeek="Sun", hour="0")
public void cleanupWeekData() { ... }

The @Schedules annotation is used to specify multiple calendar-based timer expressions for a given timeout method.

The following timeout method uses the @Schedules annotation to set multiple calendar-based timer expressions. The first expression sets a timer to expire on the last day of every month. The second expression sets a timer to expire every Friday at 11:00 p.m.:

@Schedules ({
    @Schedule(dayOfMonth="Last"),
    @Schedule(dayOfWeek="Fri", hour="23")
})
public void doPeriodicCleanup() { ... }

34.4.4 Canceling and Saving Timers

Timers can be cancelled by the following events.

When a single-event timer expires, the EJB container calls the associated timeout method and then cancels the timer.

When the bean invokes the cancel method of the Timer interface, the container cancels the timer.

If a method is invoked on a cancelled timer, the container throws the javax.ejb.NoSuchObjectLocalException.

To save a Timer object for future reference, invoke its getHandle method and store the TimerHandle object in a database. (A TimerHandle object is serializable.) To reinstantiate the Timer object, retrieve the handle from the database and invoke getTimer on the handle. A TimerHandle object cannot be passed as an argument of a method defined in a remote or web service interface. In other words, remote clients and web service clients cannot access a bean's TimerHandle object. Local clients, however, do not have this restriction.

34.4.5 Getting Timer Information

In addition to defining the cancel and getHandle methods, the Timer interface defines methods for obtaining information about timers:

public long getTimeRemaining();
public java.util.Date getNextTimeout();
public java.io.Serializable getInfo();

The getInfo method returns the object that was the last parameter of the createTimer invocation. For example, in the createTimer code snippet of the preceding section, this information parameter is a String object with the value created timer.

To retrieve all of a bean's active timers, call the getTimers method of the TimerService interface. The getTimers method returns a collection of Timer objects.

34.4.6 Transactions and Timers

An enterprise bean usually creates a timer within a transaction. If this transaction is rolled back, the timer creation also is rolled back. Similarly, if a bean cancels a timer within a transaction that gets rolled back, the timer cancellation is rolled back. In this case, the timer's duration is reset as if the cancellation had never occurred.

In beans that use container-managed transactions, the @Timeout method usually has the Required or RequiresNew transaction attribute to preserve transaction integrity. With these attributes, the EJB container begins the new transaction before calling the @Timeout method. If the transaction is rolled back, the container will call the @Timeout method at least one more time.

34.4.7 The timersession Example

The source code for this example is in the tut-install/examples/ejb/timersession/src/main/java/ directory.

TimerSessionBean is a singleton session bean that shows how to set both an automatic timer and a programmatic timer. In the source code listing of TimerSessionBean that follows, the setTimer and @Timeout methods are used to set a programmatic timer. A TimerService instance is injected by the container when the bean is created. Because it's a business method, setTimer is exposed to the local, no-interface view of TimerSessionBean and can be invoked by the client. In this example, the client invokes setTimer with an interval duration of 8,000 milliseconds, or 8 seconds. The setTimer method creates a new timer by invoking the createTimer method of TimerService. Now that the timer is set, the EJB container will invoke the programmaticTimeout method of TimerSessionBean when the timer expires, in about 8 seconds:

...
    public void setTimer(long intervalDuration) {
        logger.log(Level.INFO, 
                "Setting a programmatic timeout for {0} milliseconds from now.",
                intervalDuration);
        Timer timer = timerService.createTimer(intervalDuration, 
                "Created new programmatic timer");
    }
    
    @Timeout
    public void programmaticTimeout(Timer timer) {
        this.setLastProgrammaticTimeout(new Date());
        logger.info("Programmatic timeout occurred.");
    }
...

TimerSessionBean also has an automatic timer and timeout method, automaticTimeout. The automatic timer is set to expire every 1 minute and is set by using a calendar-based timer expression in the @Schedule annotation:

...
    @Schedule(minute = "*/1", hour = "*", persistent = false)
    public void automaticTimeout() {
        this.setLastAutomaticTimeout(new Date());
        logger.info("Automatic timeout occured");
    }
...

TimerSessionBean also has two business methods: getLastProgrammaticTimeout and getLastAutomaticTimeout. Clients call these methods to get the date and time of the last timeout for the programmatic timer and automatic timer, respectively.

Here's the source code for the TimerSessionBean class:

package javaeetutorial.timersession.ejb;

import java.util.Date;
import java.util.logging.Level;
import java.util.logging.Logger;
import javax.annotation.Resource;
import javax.ejb.Schedule;
import javax.ejb.Singleton;
import javax.ejb.Startup;
import javax.ejb.Timeout;
import javax.ejb.Timer;
import javax.ejb.TimerService;

@Singleton
@Startup
public class TimerSessionBean {
    @Resource
    TimerService timerService;

    private Date lastProgrammaticTimeout;
    private Date lastAutomaticTimeout;
    
    private static final Logger logger = 
            Logger.getLogger("timersession.ejb.TimerSessionBean");
    
    public void setTimer(long intervalDuration) {
        logger.log(Level.INFO,
                "Setting a programmatic timeout for {0} milliseconds from now.",
                intervalDuration);
        Timer timer = timerService.createTimer(intervalDuration, 
                "Created new programmatic timer");
    }
    
    @Timeout
    public void programmaticTimeout(Timer timer) {
        this.setLastProgrammaticTimeout(new Date());
        logger.info("Programmatic timeout occurred.");
    }

    @Schedule(minute = "*/1", hour = "*", persistent = false)
    public void automaticTimeout() {
        this.setLastAutomaticTimeout(new Date());
        logger.info("Automatic timeout occured");
    }

    public String getLastProgrammaticTimeout() {
        if (lastProgrammaticTimeout != null) {
            return lastProgrammaticTimeout.toString();
        } else {
            return "never";
        }
    }

    public void setLastProgrammaticTimeout(Date lastTimeout) {
        this.lastProgrammaticTimeout = lastTimeout;
    }

    public String getLastAutomaticTimeout() {
        if (lastAutomaticTimeout != null) {
            return lastAutomaticTimeout.toString();
        } else {
            return "never";
        }
    }

    public void setLastAutomaticTimeout(Date lastAutomaticTimeout) {
        this.lastAutomaticTimeout = lastAutomaticTimeout;
    }
}

Note:

GlassFish Server has a default minimum timeout value of 1,000 milliseconds, or 1 second. If you need to set the timeout value lower than 1,000 milliseconds, change the value of the Minimum Delivery Interval setting in the Administration Console. To modify the minimum timeout value, in the Administration Console expand Configurations, then expand server-config, select EJB Container, and click the EJB Timer Service tab. Enter a new timeout value under Minimum Delivery Interval and click Save. The lowest practical value for minimum-delivery-interval-in-millis is around 10 milliseconds, owing to virtual machine constraints.

34.4.8 Running the timersession Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the timersession example.

34.4.8.1 To Run the timersession Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/ejb

Select the timersession folder.

Click Open Project.

From the Run menu, choose Run Project.

This builds and packages the application into a WAR file located at tut-install/examples/ejb/timersession/target/timersession.war, deploys this WAR file to your GlassFish Server instance, and then runs the web client.

34.4.8.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the timersession Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/ejb/timersession/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This builds and packages the application into a WAR file located at tut-install/examples/ejb/timersession/target/timersession.war and deploys this WAR file to your GlassFish Server instance.

34.4.8.3 To Run the Web Client

Open a web browser to the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/timersession

Click Set Timer to set a programmatic timer.

Wait for a while and click the browser's Refresh button.

You will see the date and time of the last programmatic and automatic timeouts.

To see the messages that are logged when a timeout occurs, open the server.log file located in domain-dir/logs/.

34.5 Handling Exceptions

The exceptions thrown by enterprise beans fall into two categories: system and application.

A system exception indicates a problem with the services that support an application. For example, a connection to an external resource cannot be obtained, or an injected resource cannot be found. If it encounters a system-level problem, your enterprise bean should throw a javax.ejb.EJBException. Because the EJBException is a subclass of RuntimeException, you do not have to specify it in the throws clause of the method declaration. If a system exception is thrown, the EJB container might destroy the bean instance. Therefore, a system exception cannot be handled by the bean's client program, but instead requires intervention by a system administrator.

An application exception signals an error in the business logic of an enterprise bean. Application exceptions are typically exceptions that you've coded yourself, such as the BookException thrown by the business methods of the CartBean example. When an enterprise bean throws an application exception, the container does not wrap it in another exception. The client should be able to handle any application exception it receives.

If a system exception occurs within a transaction, the EJB container rolls back the transaction. However, if an application exception is thrown within a transaction, the container does not roll back the transaction.

30 Accessing REST Resources with the JAX-RS Client API

This chapter describes the JAX-RS Client API and includes examples of how to access REST resources using the Java programming language.

JAX-RS provides a client API for accessing REST resources from other Java applications.

The following topics are addressed here:

Overview of the Client API

Using the Client API in the JAX-RS Example Applications

Advanced Features of the Client API

30.1 Overview of the Client API

The JAX-RS Client API provides a high-level API for accessing any REST resources, not just JAX-RS services. The Client API is defined in the javax.ws.rs.client package.

30.1.1 Creating a Basic Client Request Using the Client API

The following steps are needed to access a REST resource using the Client API.

Obtain an instance of the javax.ws.rs.client.Client interface.

Configure the Client instance with a target.

Create a request based on the target.

Invoke the request.

The Client API is designed to be fluent, with method invocations chained together to configure and submit a request to a REST resource in only a few lines of code.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
String name = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/hello")
        .request(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)
        .get(String.class);

In this example, the client instance is first created by calling the javax.ws.rs.client.ClientBuilder.newClient method. Then, the request is configured and invoked by chaining method calls together in one line of code. The Client.target method sets the target based on a URI. The javax.ws.rs.client.WebTarget.request method sets the media type for the returned entity. The javax.ws.rs.client.Invocation.Builder.get method invokes the service using an HTTP GET request, setting the type of the returned entity to String.

30.1.1.1 Obtaining the Client Instance

The Client interface defines the actions and infrastructure a REST client requires to consume a RESTful web service. Instances of Client are obtained by calling the ClientBuilder.newClient method.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();

Use the close method to close Client instances after all the invocations for the target resource have been performed:

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
...
client.close();

Client instances are heavyweight objects. For performance reasons, limit the number of Client instances in your application, as the initialization and destruction of these instances may be expensive in your runtime environment.

30.1.1.2 Setting the Client Target

The target of a client, the REST resource at a particular URI, is represented by an instance of the javax.ws.rs.client.WebTarget interface. You obtain a WebTarget instance by calling the Client.target method and passing in the URI of the target REST resource.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi");

For complex REST resources, it may be beneficial to create several instances of WebTarget. In the following example, a base target is used to construct several other targets that represent different services provided by a REST resource.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
WebTarget base = client.target("http://example.com/webapi");
// WebTarget at http://example.com/webapi/read
WebTarget read = base.path("read");
// WebTarget at http://example.com/webapi/write
WebTarget write = base.path("write");

The WebTarget.path method creates a new WebTarget instance by appending the current target URI with the path that was passed in.

30.1.1.3 Setting Path Parameters in Targets

Path parameters in client requests can be specified as URI template parameters, similar to the template parameters used when defining a resource URI in a JAX-RS service. Template parameters are specified by surrounding the template variable with braces ({}). Call the resolveTemplate method to substitute the {username}, and then call the queryParam method to add another variable to pass.

WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/read")
        .path("{userName}")
        .resolveTemplate("userName", "janedoe")        .queryParam("chapter", "1");// http://example.com/webapi/read/janedoe?chapter=1Response response = myResource.request(...)        .get();

30.1.1.4 Invoking the Request

After setting and applying any configuration options to the target, call one of the WebTarget.request methods to begin creating the request. This is usually accomplished by passing to WebTarget.request the accepted media response type for the request either as a string of the MIME type or using one of the constants in javax.ws.rs.core.MediaType. The WebTarget.request method returns an instance of javax.ws.rs.client.Invocation.Builder, a helper object that provides methods for preparing the client request.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/read");
Invocation.Builder builder = myResource.request(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN);

Using a MediaType constant is equivalent to using the string defining the MIME type.

Invocation.Builder builder = myResource.request("text/plain");

After setting the media type, invoke the request by calling one of the methods of the Invocation.Builder instance that corresponds to the type of HTTP request the target REST resource expects. These methods are:

get()

post()

delete()

put()

head()

options()

For example, if the target REST resource is for an HTTP GET request, call the Invocation.Builder.get method. The return type should correspond to the entity returned by the target REST resource.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/read");
String response = myResource.request(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)
        .get(String.class);

If the target REST resource is expecting an HTTP POST request, call the Invocation.Builder.post method.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
StoreOrder order = new StoreOrder(...);
WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/write");
TrackingNumber trackingNumber = myResource.request(MediaType.APPLICATION_XML)
                                   .post(Entity.xml(order), TrackingNumber.class);

In the preceding example, the return type is a custom class and is retrieved by setting the type in the Invocation.Builder.post(Entity? entity, ClassT responseType) method as a parameter.

If the return type is a collection, use javax.ws.rs.core.GenericTypeT as the response type parameter, where T is the collection type:

List<StoreOrder> orders = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/read")
        .path("allOrders")
        .request(MediaType.APPLICATION_XML)
        .get(new GenericType<List<StoreOrder>>() {});

This preceding example shows how methods are chained together in the Client API to simplify how requests are configured and invoked.

30.2 Using the Client API in the JAX-RS Example Applications

The rsvp and customer examples use the Client API to call JAX-RS services. This section describes how each example application uses the Client API.

30.2.1 The Client API in the rsvp Example Application

The rsvp application allows users to respond to event invitations using JAX-RS resources, as explained in Chapter 29, "The rsvp Example Application". The web application uses the Client API in CDI backing beans to interact with the service resources, and the Facelets web interface displays the results.

The StatusManager CDI backing bean retrieves all the current events in the system. The client instance used in the backing bean is obtained in the constructor:

public StatusManager() {
    this.client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
}

The StatusManager.getEvents method returns a collection of all the current events in the system by calling the resource at http://localhost:8080/rsvp/webapi/status/all, which returns an XML document with entries for each event. The Client API automatically unmarshals the XML and creates a ListEvent instance.

    public List<Event> getEvents() {
        List<Event> returnedEvents = null;
        try {
            returnedEvents = client.target(baseUri)
                    .path("all")
                    .request(MediaType.APPLICATION_XML)
                    .get(new GenericType<List<Event>>() {
            });
            if (returnedEvents == null) {
                logger.log(Level.SEVERE, "Returned events null.");
            } else {
                logger.log(Level.INFO, "Events have been returned.");
            }
        } catch (WebApplicationException ex) {
            throw new WebApplicationException(Response.Status.NOT_FOUND);
        }
        ...
        return returnedEvents;
    }

The StatusManager.changeStatus method is used to update the attendee's response. It creates an HTTP POST request to the service with the new response. The body of the request is an XML document.

    public String changeStatus(ResponseEnum userResponse, 
            Person person, Event event) {
        String navigation;
        try {
            logger.log(Level.INFO, 
                    "changing status to {0} for {1} {2} for event ID {3}.",
                    new Object[]{userResponse,
                        person.getFirstName(),
                        person.getLastName(),
                        event.getId().toString()});
             client.target(baseUri)
                     .path(event.getId().toString())
                     .path(person.getId().toString())
                     .request(MediaType.APPLICATION_XML)
                     .post(Entity.xml(userResponse.getLabel()));
            navigation = "changedStatus";
        } catch (ResponseProcessingException ex) {
            logger.log(Level.WARNING, "couldn''t change status for {0} {1}",
                    new Object[]{person.getFirstName(),
                        person.getLastName()});
            logger.log(Level.WARNING, ex.getMessage());
            navigation = "error";
        }
        return navigation;
    }

30.2.2 The Client API in the customer Example Application

The customer example application stores customer data in a database and exposes the resource as XML, as explained in Chapter 31, "The customer Example Application". The service resource exposes methods that create customers and retrieve all the customers. A Facelets web application acts as a client for the service resource, with a form for creating customers and displaying the list of customers in a table.

The CustomerBean stateless session bean uses the JAX-RS Client API to interface with the service resource. The CustomerBean.createCustomer method takes the Customer entity instance created by the Facelets form and makes a POST call to the service URI.

public String createCustomer(Customer customer) {
    if (customer == null) {
        logger.log(Level.WARNING, "customer is null.");
        return "customerError";
    }
    String navigation;
    Response response =
            client.target("http://localhost:8080/customer/webapi/Customer")
            .request(MediaType.APPLICATION_XML)
            .post(Entity.entity(customer, MediaType.APPLICATION_XML),
                    Response.class);
    if (response.getStatus() == Status.CREATED.getStatusCode()) {
        navigation = "customerCreated";
    } else {
        logger.log(Level.WARNING, 
                "couldn''t create customer with id {0}. Status returned was {1}",
                new Object[]{customer.getId(), response.getStatus()});
        FacesContext context = FacesContext.getCurrentInstance();
        context.addMessage(null, 
                new FacesMessage("Could not create customer."));
        navigation = "customerError";
    }
    return navigation;
}

The XML request entity is created by calling the Invocation.Builder.post method, passing in a new Entity instance from the Customer instance, and specifying the media type as MediaType.APPLICATION_XML.

The CustomerBean.retrieveCustomer method retrieves a Customer entity instance from the service by appending the customer's ID to the service URI.

public String retrieveCustomer(String id) {
    String navigation;
    Customer customer =
            client.target("http://localhost:8080/customer/webapi/Customer")
            .path(id)
            .request(MediaType.APPLICATION_XML)
            .get(Customer.class);
    if (customer == null) {
        navigation = "customerError";
    } else {
        navigation = "customerRetrieved";
    }
    return navigation;
}

The CustomerBean.retrieveAllCustomers method retrieves a collection of customers as a ListCustomer instance. This list is then displayed as a table in the Facelets web application.

public ListCustomer retrieveAllCustomers() {    ListCustomer customers =            client.target("http://localhost:8080/customer/webapi/Customer")            .path("all")            .request(MediaType.APPLICATION_XML)            .get(new GenericTypeListCustomer() {            });    return customers;}

Because the response type is a collection, the Invocation.Builder.get method is called by passing in a new instance of GenericTypeListCustomer.

30.3 Advanced Features of the Client API

This section describes some of the advanced features of the JAX-RS Client API.

30.3.1 Configuring the Client Request

Additional configuration options may be added to the client request after it is created but before it is invoked.

30.3.1.1 Setting Message Headers in the Client Request

You can set HTTP headers on the request by calling the Invocation.Builder.header method.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/read");
String response = myResource.request(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)
        .header("myHeader", "The header value")
        .get(String.class);

If you need to set multiple headers on the request, call the Invocation.Builder.headers method and pass in a javax.ws.rs.core.MultivaluedMap instance with the name-value pairs of the HTTP headers. Calling the headers method replaces all the existing headers with the headers supplied in the MultivaluedMap instance.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/read");
MultivaluedMap<String, Object> myHeaders = 
    new MultivaluedMap<>("myHeader", "The header value");
myHeaders.add(...);
String response = myResource.request(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)
        .headers(myHeaders)
        .get(String.class);

The MultivaluedMap interface allows you to specify multiple values for a given key.

MultivaluedMap<String, Object> myHeaders = 
    new MultivaluedMap<String, Object>();
List<String> values = new ArrayList<>();
values.add(...)
myHeaders.add("myHeader", values

30.3.1.2 Setting Cookies in the Client Request

You can add HTTP cookies to the request by calling the Invocation.Builder.cookie method, which takes a name-value pair as parameters.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/read");
String response = myResource.request(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)
        .cookie("myCookie", "The cookie value")
        .get(String.class);

The javax.ws.rs.core.Cookie class encapsulates the attributes of an HTTP cookie, including the name, value, path, domain, and RFC specification version of the cookie. In the following example, the Cookie object is configured with a name-value pair, a path, and a domain.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/read");
Cookie myCookie = new Cookie("myCookie", "The cookie value", 
    "/webapi/read", "example.com"); 
String response = myResource.request(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)
        .cookie(myCookie)
        .get(String.class);

30.3.1.3 Adding Filters to the Client

You can register custom filters with the client request or the response received from the target resource. To register filter classes when the Client instance is created, call the Client.register method.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient().register(MyLoggingFilter.class);

In the preceding example, all invocations that use this Client instance have the MyLoggingFilter filter registered with them.

You can also register the filter classes on the target by calling WebTarget.register.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient().register(MyLoggingFilter.class);
WebTarget target = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/secure")
        .register(MyAuthenticationFilter.class);

In the preceding example, both the MyLoggingFilter and MyAuthenticationFilter filters are attached to the invocation.

Request and response filter classes implement the javax.ws.rs.client.ClientRequestFilter and javax.ws.rs.client.ClientResponseFilter interfaces, respectively. Both of these interfaces define a single method, filter. All filters must be annotated with javax.ws.rs.ext.Provider.

The following class is a logging filter for both client requests and client responses.

@Provider
public class MyLoggingFilter implements ClientRequestFilter, 
        ClientResponseFilter {
    static final Logger logger = Logger.getLogger(...);

    // implement the ClientRequestFilter.filter method
    @Override
    public void filter(ClientRequestContext requestContext) 
            throws IOException {
        logger.log(...);
        ...
    }

    // implement the ClientResponseFilter.filter method
    @Override
    public void filter(ClientRequestContext requestContext, 
           ClientResponseContext responseContext) throws IOException {
        logger.log(...);
        ...
    }
}

If the invocation must be stopped while the filter is active, call the context object's abortWith method, and pass in a javax.ws.rs.core.Response instance from within the filter.

@Override
public void filter(ClientRequestContext requestContext) throws IOException {
    ...
    Response response = new Response();
    response.status(500);
    requestContext.abortWith(response);
}

30.3.2 Asynchronous Invocations in the Client API

In networked applications, network issues can affect the perceived performance of the application, particularly in long-running or complicated network calls. Asynchronous processing helps prevent blocking and makes better use of an application's resources.

In the JAX-RS Client API, the Invocation.Builder.async method is used when constructing a client request to indicate that the call to the service should be performed asynchronously. An asynchronous invocation returns control to the caller immediately, with a return type of java.util.concurrent.FutureT (part of the Java SE concurrency API) and with the type set to the return type of the service call. FutureT objects have methods to check if the asynchronous call has been completed, to retrieve the final result, to cancel the invocation, and to check if the invocation has been cancelled.

The following example shows how to invoke an asynchronous request on a resource.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/read");
Future<String> response = myResource.request(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)
        .async()
        .get(String.class);

30.3.2.1 Using Custom Callbacks in Asynchronous Invocations

The InvocationCallback interface defines two methods, completed and failed, that are called when an asynchronous invocation either completes successfully or fails, respectively. You may register an InvocationCallback instance on your request by creating a new instance when specifying the request method.

The following example shows how to register a callback object on an asynchronous invocation.

Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
WebTarget myResource = client.target("http://example.com/webapi/read");
Future<Customer> fCustomer = myResource.request(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)
        .async()
        .get(new InvocationCallback<Customer>() {
            @Override
            public void completed(Customer customer) {
            // Do something with the customer object
            }
            @Override
             public void failed(Throwable throwable) {
            // handle the error
            }
    });

45 Java Message Service Concepts

This chapter provides an introduction to the Java Message Service (JMS) API, a Java API that allows applications to create, send, receive, and read messages using reliable, asynchronous, loosely coupled communication. It covers the following topics:

Overview of the JMS API

Basic JMS API Concepts

The JMS API Programming Model

Using Advanced JMS Features

Using the JMS API in Java EE Applications

Further Information about JMS

45.1 Overview of the JMS API

This overview defines the concept of messaging, describes the JMS API and where it can be used, and explains how the JMS API works within the Java EE platform.

45.1.1 What Is Messaging?

Messaging is a method of communication between software components or applications. A messaging system is a peer-to-peer facility: A messaging client can send messages to, and receive messages from, any other client. Each client connects to a messaging agent that provides facilities for creating, sending, receiving, and reading messages.

Messaging enables distributed communication that is loosely coupled. A component sends a message to a destination, and the recipient can retrieve the message from the destination. What makes the communication loosely coupled is that the destination is all that the sender and receiver have in common. The sender and the receiver do not have to be available at the same time in order to communicate. In fact, the sender does not need to know anything about the receiver; nor does the receiver need to know anything about the sender. The sender and the receiver need to know only which message format and which destination to use. In this respect, messaging differs from tightly coupled technologies, such as Remote Method Invocation (RMI), which require an application to know a remote application's methods.

Messaging also differs from electronic mail (email), which is a method of communication between people or between software applications and people. Messaging is used for communication between software applications or software components.

45.1.2 What Is the JMS API?

The Java Message Service is a Java API that allows applications to create, send, receive, and read messages. The JMS API defines a common set of interfaces and associated semantics that allow programs written in the Java programming language to communicate with other messaging implementations.

The JMS API minimizes the set of concepts a programmer must learn in order to use messaging products but provides enough features to support sophisticated messaging applications. It also strives to maximize the portability of JMS applications across JMS providers.

JMS enables communication that is not only loosely coupled but also

Asynchronous: A receiving client does not have to receive messages at the same time the sending client sends them. The sending client can send them and go on to other tasks; the receiving client can receive them much later.

Reliable: A messaging provider that implements the JMS API can ensure that a message is delivered once and only once. Lower levels of reliability are available for applications that can afford to miss messages or to receive duplicate messages.

The current version of the JMS specification is Version 2.0. You can download a copy of the specification from the Java Community Process website: http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=343.

45.1.3 When Can You Use the JMS API?

An enterprise application provider is likely to choose a messaging API over a tightly coupled API, such as a remote procedure call (RPC), under the following circumstances.

The provider wants the components not to depend on information about other components' interfaces, so components can be easily replaced.

The provider wants the application to run whether or not all components are up and running simultaneously.

The application business model allows a component to send information to another and to continue to operate without receiving an immediate response.

For example, components of an enterprise application for an automobile manufacturer can use the JMS API in situations like the following.

The inventory component can send a message to the factory component when the inventory level for a product goes below a certain level so the factory can make more cars.

The factory component can send a message to the parts components so the factory can assemble the parts it needs.

The parts components in turn can send messages to their own inventory and order components to update their inventories and to order new parts from suppliers.

Both the factory and the parts components can send messages to the accounting component to update budget numbers.

The business can publish updated catalog items to its sales force.

Using messaging for these tasks allows the various components to interact with one another efficiently, without tying up network or other resources. Figure 45-1 illustrates how this simple example might work.

Figure 45-1 Messaging in an Enterprise Application

Description of "Figure 45-1 Messaging in an Enterprise Application"

Manufacturing is only one example of how an enterprise can use the JMS API. Retail applications, financial services applications, health services applications, and many others can make use of messaging.

45.1.4 How Does the JMS API Work with the Java EE Platform?

When the JMS API was first introduced, its most important purpose was to allow Java applications to access existing messaging-oriented middleware (MOM) systems. Since that time, many vendors have adopted and implemented the JMS API, so a JMS product can now provide a complete messaging capability for an enterprise.

The JMS API is an integral part of the Java EE platform, and application developers can use messaging with Java EE components. JMS 2.0 is part of the Java EE 7 release.

The JMS API in the Java EE platform has the following features.

Application clients, Enterprise JavaBeans (EJB) components, and web components can send or synchronously receive a JMS message. Application clients can in addition set a message listener that allows JMS messages to be delivered to it asynchronously by being notified when a message is available.

Message-driven beans, which are a kind of enterprise bean, enable the asynchronous consumption of messages in the EJB container. An application server typically pools message-driven beans to implement concurrent processing of messages.

Message send and receive operations can participate in Java Transaction API (JTA) transactions, which allow JMS operations and database accesses to take place within a single transaction.

The JMS API enhances the other parts of the Java EE platform by simplifying enterprise development, allowing loosely coupled, reliable, asynchronous interactions among Java EE components and legacy systems capable of messaging. A developer can easily add new behavior to a Java EE application that has existing business events by adding a new message-driven bean to operate on specific business events. The Java EE platform, moreover, enhances the JMS API by providing support for JTA transactions and allowing for the concurrent consumption of messages. For more information, see the Enterprise JavaBeans specification, v3.2.

The JMS provider can be integrated with the application server using the Java EE Connector architecture. You access the JMS provider through a resource adapter. This capability allows vendors to create JMS providers that can be plugged in to multiple application servers, and it allows application servers to support multiple JMS providers. For more information, see the Java EE Connector architecture specification, v1.7.

45.2 Basic JMS API Concepts

This section introduces the most basic JMS API concepts, the ones you must know to get started writing simple application clients that use the JMS API.

The next section introduces the JMS API programming model. Later sections cover more advanced concepts, including the ones you need in order to write applications that use message-driven beans.

45.2.1 JMS API Architecture

A JMS application is composed of the following parts.

A JMS provider is a messaging system that implements the JMS interfaces and provides administrative and control features. An implementation of the Java EE platform that supports the full profile includes a JMS provider.

JMS clients are the programs or components, written in the Java programming language, that produce and consume messages. Any Java EE application component can act as a JMS client.

Java SE applications can also act as JMS clients; the Message Queue Developer's Guide for Java Clients in the GlassFish Server documentation (https://glassfish.java.net/docs/) explains how to make this work.

Messages are the objects that communicate information between JMS clients.

Administered objects are JMS objects configured for the use of clients. The two kinds of JMS administered objects are destinations and connection factories, described in JMS Administered Objects. An administrator can create objects that are available to all applications that use a particular installation of GlassFish Server; alternatively, a developer can use annotations to create objects that are specific to a particular application.

Figure 45-2 illustrates the way these parts interact. Administrative tools or annotations allow you to bind destinations and connection factories into a JNDI namespace. A JMS client can then use resource injection to access the administered objects in the namespace and then establish a logical connection to the same objects through the JMS provider.

Figure 45-2 JMS API Architecture

Description of "Figure 45-2 JMS API Architecture"

45.2.2 Messaging Styles

Before the JMS API existed, most messaging products supported either the point-to-point or the publish/subscribe style of messaging. The JMS specification defines compliance for each style. A JMS provider must implement both styles, and the JMS API provides interfaces that are specific to each. The following subsections describe these messaging styles.

The JMS API, however, makes it unnecessary to use only one of the two styles. It allows you to use the same code to send and receive messages using either the PTP or the pub/sub style. The destinations you use remain specific to one style, and the behavior of the application will depend in part on whether you are using a queue or a topic. However, the code itself can be common to both styles, making your applications flexible and reusable. This tutorial describes and illustrates this coding approach, using the greatly simplified API provided by JMS 2.0.

45.2.2.1 Point-to-Point Messaging Style

A point-to-point (PTP) product or application is built on the concept of message queues, senders, and receivers. Each message is addressed to a specific queue, and receiving clients extract messages from the queues established to hold their messages. Queues retain all messages sent to them until the messages are consumed or expire.

PTP messaging, illustrated in Figure 45-3, has the following characteristics.

Each message has only one consumer.

The receiver can fetch the message whether or not it was running when the client sent the message.

Figure 45-3 Point-to-Point Messaging

Description of "Figure 45-3 Point-to-Point Messaging"

Use PTP messaging when every message you send must be processed successfully by one consumer.

45.2.2.2 Publish/Subscribe Messaging Style

In a publish/subscribe (pub/sub) product or application, clients address messages to a topic, which functions somewhat like a bulletin board. Publishers and subscribers can dynamically publish or subscribe to the topic. The system takes care of distributing the messages arriving from a topic's multiple publishers to its multiple subscribers. Topics retain messages only as long as it takes to distribute them to subscribers.

With pub/sub messaging, it is important to distinguish between the consumer that subscribes to a topic (the subscriber) and the subscription that is created. The consumer is a JMS object within an application, while the subscription is an entity within the JMS provider. Normally, a topic can have many consumers, but a subscription has only one subscriber. It is possible, however, to create shared subscriptions; see Creating Shared Subscriptions for details. See Consuming Messages from Topics for details on the semantics of pub/sub messaging.

Pub/sub messaging has the following characteristics.

Each message can have multiple consumers.

A client that subscribes to a topic can consume only messages sent after the client has created a subscription, and the consumer must continue to be active in order for it to consume messages.

The JMS API relaxes this requirement to some extent by allowing applications to create durable subscriptions, which receive messages sent while the consumers are not active. Durable subscriptions provide the flexibility and reliability of queues but still allow clients to send messages to many recipients. For more information about durable subscriptions, see Creating Durable Subscriptions.

Use pub/sub messaging when each message can be processed by any number of consumers (or none). Figure 45-4 illustrates pub/sub messaging.

Figure 45-4 Publish/Subscribe Messaging

Description of "Figure 45-4 Publish/Subscribe Messaging"

45.2.3 Message Consumption

Messaging products are inherently asynchronous: There is no fundamental timing dependency between the production and the consumption of a message. However, the JMS specification uses this term in a more precise sense. Messages can be consumed in either of two ways.

Synchronously: A consumer explicitly fetches the message from the destination by calling the receive method. The receive method can block until a message arrives or can time out if a message does not arrive within a specified time limit.

Asynchronously: An application client or a Java SE client can register a message listener with a consumer. A message listener is similar to an event listener. Whenever a message arrives at the destination, the JMS provider delivers the message by calling the listener's onMessage method, which acts on the contents of the message. In a Java EE application, a message-driven bean serves as a message listener (it too has an onMessage method), but a client does not need to register it with a consumer.

45.3 The JMS API Programming Model

The basic building blocks of a JMS application are

Administered objects: connection factories and destinations

Connections

Sessions

JMSContext objects, which combine a connection and a session in one object

Message producers

Message consumers

Messages

Figure 45-5 shows how all these objects fit together in a JMS client application.

Figure 45-5 The JMS API Programming Model

Description of "Figure 45-5 The JMS API Programming Model"

JMS also provides queue browsers, objects that allow an application to browse messages on a queue.

This section describes all these objects briefly and provides sample commands and code snippets that show how to create and use the objects. The last subsection briefly describes JMS API exception handling.

Examples that show how to combine all these objects in applications appear in Chapter 46, "Java Message Service Examples," beginning with Writing Simple JMS Applications. For more detail, see the JMS API documentation, part of the Java EE API documentation.

45.3.1 JMS Administered Objects

Two parts of a JMS application, destinations and connection factories, are commonly maintained administratively rather than programmatically. The technology underlying these objects is likely to be very different from one implementation of the JMS API to another. Therefore, the management of these objects belongs with other administrative tasks that vary from provider to provider.

JMS clients access administered objects through interfaces that are portable, so a client application can run with little or no change on more than one implementation of the JMS API. Ordinarily, an administrator configures administered objects in a JNDI namespace, and JMS clients then access them by using resource injection.

With GlassFish Server, you can use the asadmin create-jms-resource command or the Administration Console to create JMS administered objects in the form of connector resources. You can also specify the resources in a file named glassfish-resources.xml that you can bundle with an application.

NetBeans IDE provides a wizard that allows you to create JMS resources for GlassFish Server. See Creating JMS Administered Objects for details.

The Java EE platform specification allows a developer to create administered objects using annotations or deployment descriptor elements. Objects created in this way are specific to the application for which they are created. See Creating Resources for Java EE Applications for details. Definitions in a deployment descriptor override those specified by annotations.

45.3.1.1 JMS Connection Factories

A connection factory is the object a client uses to create a connection to a provider. A connection factory encapsulates a set of connection configuration parameters that has been defined by an administrator. Each connection factory is an instance of the ConnectionFactory, QueueConnectionFactory, or TopicConnectionFactory interface. To learn how to create connection factories, see Creating JMS Administered Objects.

At the beginning of a JMS client program, you usually inject a connection factory resource into a ConnectionFactory object. A Java EE server must provide a JMS connection factory with the logical JNDI name java:comp/DefaultJMSConnectionFactory. The actual JNDI name will be implementation-specific.

For example, the following code fragment looks up the default JMS connection factory and assigns it to a ConnectionFactory object:

@Resource(lookup = "java:comp/DefaultJMSConnectionFactory")
private static ConnectionFactory connectionFactory;

45.3.1.2 JMS Destinations

A destination is the object a client uses to specify the target of messages it produces and the source of messages it consumes. In the PTP messaging style, destinations are called queues. In the pub/sub messaging style, destinations are called topics. A JMS application can use multiple queues or topics (or both). To learn how to create destination resources, see Creating JMS Administered Objects.

To create a destination using GlassFish Server, you create a JMS destination resource that specifies a JNDI name for the destination.

In the GlassFish Server implementation of JMS, each destination resource refers to a physical destination. You can create a physical destination explicitly, but if you do not, the Application Server creates it when it is needed and deletes it when you delete the destination resource.

In addition to injecting a connection factory resource into a client program, you usually inject a destination resource. Unlike connection factories, destinations are specific to either the PTP or pub/sub messaging style. To create an application that allows you to use the same code for both topics and queues, you assign the destination to a Destination object.

The following code specifies two resources, a queue and a topic. The resource names are mapped to destination resources created in the JNDI namespace:

@Resource(lookup = "jms/MyQueue")
private static Queue queue;

@Resource(lookup = "jms/MyTopic")
private static Topic topic;

In a Java EE application, JMS administered objects are normally placed in the jms naming subcontext.

With the common interfaces, you can mix or match connection factories and destinations. That is, in addition to using the ConnectionFactory interface, you can inject a QueueConnectionFactory resource and use it with a Topic, and you can inject a TopicConnectionFactory resource and use it with a Queue. The behavior of the application will depend on the kind of destination you use and not on the kind of connection factory you use.

45.3.2 Connections

A connection encapsulates a virtual connection with a JMS provider. For example, a connection could represent an open TCP/IP socket between a client and a provider service daemon. You use a connection to create one or more sessions.

Note:

In the Java EE platform, the ability to create multiple sessions from a single connection is limited to application clients. In web and enterprise bean components, a connection can create no more than one session.

You normally create a connection by creating a JMSContext object. See JMSContext Objects for details.

45.3.3 Sessions

A session is a single-threaded context for producing and consuming messages.

You normally create a session (as well as a connection) by creating a JMSContext object. See JMSContext Objects for details. You use sessions to create message producers, message consumers, messages, queue browsers, and temporary destinations.

Sessions serialize the execution of message listeners; for details, see JMS Message Listeners.

A session provides a transactional context with which to group a set of sends and receives into an atomic unit of work. For details, see Using JMS Local Transactions.

45.3.4 JMSContext Objects

A JMSContext object combines a connection and a session in a single object. That is, it provides both an active connection to a JMS provider and a single-threaded context for sending and receiving messages.

You use the JMSContext to create the following objects:

Message producers

Message consumers

Messages

Queue browsers

Temporary queues and topics (see Creating Temporary Destinations)

You can create a JMSContext in a try-with-resources block.

To create a JMSContext, call the createContext method on the connection factory:

JMSContext context = connectionFactory.createContext();

When called with no arguments from an application client or a Java SE client, or from the Java EE web or EJB container when there is no active JTA transaction in progress, the createContext method creates a non-transacted session with an acknowledgment mode of JMSContext.AUTO_ACKNOWLEDGE. When called with no arguments from the web or EJB container when there is an active JTA transaction in progress, the createContext method creates a transacted session. For information about the way JMS transactions work in Java EE applications, see Using the JMS API in Java EE Applications.

From an application client or a Java SE client, you can also call the createContext method with the argument JMSContext.SESSION_TRANSACTED to create a transacted session:

JMSContext context = 
        connectionFactory.createContext(JMSContext.SESSION_TRANSACTED);

The session uses local transactions; see Using JMS Local Transactions for details.

Alternatively, you can specify a non-default acknowledgment mode; see Controlling Message Acknowledgment for more information.

When you use a JMSContext, message delivery normally begins as soon as you create a consumer. See JMS Message Consumers for more information.

If you create a JMSContext in a try-with-resources block, you do not need to close it explicitly. It will be closed when the try block comes to an end. Make sure that your application completes all its JMS activity within the try-with-resources block. If you do not use a try-with-resources block, you must call the close method on the JMSContext to close the connection when the application has finished its work.

45.3.5 JMS Message Producers

A message producer is an object that is created by a JMSContext or a session and used for sending messages to a destination. A message producer created by a JMSContext implements the JMSProducer interface. You could create it this way:

try (JMSContext context = connectionFactory.createContext();) {
    JMSProducer producer = context.createProducer();
    ...

However, a JMSProducer is a lightweight object that does not consume significant resources. For this reason, you do not need to save the JMSProducer in a variable; you can create a new one each time you send a message. You send messages to a specific destination by using the send method. For example:

context.createProducer().send(dest, message);

You can create the message in a variable before sending it, as shown here, or you can create it within the send call. See JMS Messages for more information.

45.3.6 JMS Message Consumers

A message consumer is an object that is created by a JMSContext or a session and used for receiving messages sent to a destination. A message producer created by a JMSContext implements the JMSConsumer interface. The simplest way to create a message consumer is to use the JMSContext.createConsumer method:

try (JMSContext context = connectionFactory.createContext();) {
    JMSConsumer consumer = context.createConsumer(dest);
    ...

A message consumer allows a JMS client to register interest in a destination with a JMS provider. The JMS provider manages the delivery of messages from a destination to the registered consumers of the destination.

When you use a JMSContext to create a message consumer, message delivery begins as soon as you have created the consumer. You can disable this behavior by calling setAutoStart(false) when you create the JMSContext and then calling the start method explicitly to start message delivery. If you want to stop message delivery temporarily without closing the connection, you can call the stop method; to restart message delivery, call start.

You use the receive method to consume a message synchronously. You can use this method at any time after you create the consumer.

If you specify no arguments or an argument of 0, the method blocks indefinitely until a message arrives:

Message m = consumer.receive();
Message m = consumer.receive(0);

For a simple client, this may not matter. But if it is possible that a message might not be available, use a synchronous receive with a timeout: Call the receive method with a timeout argument greater than 0. One second is a recommended timeout value:

Message m = consumer.receive(1000); // time out after a second

To enable asynchronous message delivery from an application client or a Java SE client, you use a message listener, as described in the next section.

You can use the JMSContext.createDurableConsumer method to create a durable topic subscription. This method is valid only if you are using a topic. For details, see Creating Durable Subscriptions. For topics, you can also create shared consumers; see Creating Shared Subscriptions.

45.3.6.1 JMS Message Listeners

A message listener is an object that acts as an asynchronous event handler for messages. This object implements the MessageListener interface, which contains one method, onMessage. In the onMessage method, you define the actions to be taken when a message arrives.

From an application client or a Java SE client, you register the message listener with a specific message consumer by using the setMessageListener method. For example, if you define a class named Listener that implements the MessageListener interface, you can register the message listener as follows:

Listener myListener = new Listener();
consumer.setMessageListener(myListener);

When message delivery begins, the JMS provider automatically calls the message listener's onMessage method whenever a message is delivered. The onMessage method takes one argument of type Message, which your implementation of the method can cast to another message subtype as needed (see Message Bodies).

In the Java EE web or EJB container, you use message-driven beans for asynchronous message delivery. A message-driven bean also implements the MessageListener interface and contains an onMessage method. For details, see Using Message-Driven Beans to Receive Messages Asynchronously.

Your onMessage method should handle all exceptions. Throwing a RuntimeException is considered a programming error.

For a simple example of the use of a message listener, see Using a Message Listener for Asynchronous Message Delivery. Chapter 46, "Java Message Service Examples," contains several more examples of message listeners and message-driven beans.

45.3.6.2 JMS Message Selectors

If your messaging application needs to filter the messages it receives, you can use a JMS message selector, which allows a message consumer for a destination to specify the messages that interest it. Message selectors assign the work of filtering messages to the JMS provider rather than to the application. For an example of an application that uses a message selector, see Sending Messages from a Session Bean to an MDB.

A message selector is a String that contains an expression. The syntax of the expression is based on a subset of the SQL92 conditional expression syntax. The message selector in the example selects any message that has a NewsType property that is set to the value 'Sports' or 'Opinion':

NewsType = 'Sports' OR NewsType = 'Opinion'

The createConsumer and createDurableConsumer methods, as well as the methods for creating shared consumers, allow you to specify a message selector as an argument when you create a message consumer.

The message consumer then receives only messages whose headers and properties match the selector. (See Message Headers and Message Properties.) A message selector cannot select messages on the basis of the content of the message body.

45.3.6.3 Consuming Messages from Topics

The semantics of consuming messages from topics are more complex than the semantics of consuming messages from queues.

An application consumes messages from a topic by creating a subscription on that topic and creating a consumer on that subscription. Subscriptions may be durable or nondurable, and they may be shared or unshared.

A subscription may be thought of as an entity within the JMS provider itself, whereas a consumer is a JMS object within the application.

A subscription will receive a copy of every message that is sent to the topic after the subscription is created, unless a message selector is specified. If a message selector is specified, only those messages whose properties match the message selector will be added to the subscription.

Unshared subscriptions are restricted to a single consumer. In this case, all the messages in the subscription are delivered to that consumer. Shared subscriptions allow multiple consumers. In this case, each message in the subscription is delivered to only one consumer. JMS does not define how messages are distributed between multiple consumers on the same subscription.

Subscriptions may be durable or nondurable.

A nondurable subscription exists only as long as there is an active consumer on the subscription. This means that any messages sent to the topic will be added to the subscription only while a consumer exists and is not closed.

A nondurable subscription may be either unshared or shared.

An unshared nondurable subscription does not have a name and may have only a single consumer object associated with it. It is created automatically when the consumer object is created. It is not persisted and is deleted automatically when the consumer object is closed.

The JMSContext.createConsumer method creates a consumer on an unshared nondurable subscription if a topic is specified as the destination.

A shared nondurable subscription is identified by name and an optional client identifier, and may have several consumer objects consuming messages from it. It is created automatically when the first consumer object is created. It is not persisted and is deleted automatically when the last consumer object is closed. See Creating Shared Subscriptions for more information.

At the cost of higher overhead, a subscription may be durable. A durable subscription is persisted and continues to accumulate messages until explicitly deleted, even if there are no consumer objects consuming messages from it. See Creating Durable Subscriptions for details.

45.3.6.4 Creating Durable Subscriptions

To ensure that a pub/sub application receives all sent messages, use durable subscriptions for the consumers on the topic.

Like a nondurable subscription, a durable subscription may be either unshared or shared.

An unshared durable subscription is identified by name and client identifier (which must be set) and may have only a single consumer object associated with it.

A shared durable subscription is identified by name and an optional client identifier, and may have several consumer objects consuming messages from it.

A durable subscription that exists but that does not currently have a non-closed consumer object associated with it is described as being inactive.

You can use the JMSContext.createDurableConsumer method to create a consumer on an unshared durable subscription. An unshared durable subscription can have only one active consumer at a time.

A consumer identifies the durable subscription from which it consumes messages by specifying a unique identity that is retained by the JMS provider. Subsequent consumer objects that have the same identity resume the subscription in the state in which it was left by the preceding consumer. If a durable subscription has no active consumer, the JMS provider retains the subscription's messages until they are received by the subscription or until they expire.

You establish the unique identity of an unshared durable subscription by setting the following:

A client ID for the connection

A topic and a subscription name for the subscription

You can set the client ID administratively for a client-specific connection factory using either the command line or the Administration Console. (In an application client or a Java SE client, you can instead call JMSContext.setClientID.)

After using this connection factory to create the JMSContext, you call the createDurableConsumer method with two arguments: the topic and a string that specifies the name of the subscription:

String subName = "MySub";
JMSConsumer consumer = context.createDurableConsumer(myTopic, subName);

The subscription becomes active after you create the consumer. Later, you might close the consumer:

consumer.close();

The JMS provider stores the messages sent to the topic, as it would store messages sent to a queue. If the program or another application calls createDurableConsumer using the same connection factory and its client ID, the same topic, and the same subscription name, then the subscription is reactivated and the JMS provider delivers the messages that were sent while the subscription was inactive.

To delete a durable subscription, first close the consumer, then call the unsubscribe method with the subscription name as the argument:

consumer.close();
context.unsubscribe(subName);

The unsubscribe method deletes the state the provider maintains for the subscription.

Figure 45-6 and Figure 45-7 show the difference between a nondurable and a durable subscription. With an ordinary, nondurable subscription, the consumer and the subscription begin and end at the same point and are, in effect, identical. When the consumer is closed, the subscription also ends. Here, create stands for a call to JMSContext.createConsumer with a Topic argument, and close stands for a call to JMSConsumer.close. Any messages sent to the topic between the time of the first close and the time of the second create are not added to either subscription. In Figure 45-6, the consumers receive messages M1, M2, M5, and M6, but they do not receive messages M3 and M4.

Figure 45-6 Nondurable Subscriptions and Consumers

Description of "Figure 45-6 Nondurable Subscriptions and Consumers"

With a durable subscription, the consumer can be closed and re-created, but the subscription continues to exist and to hold messages until the application calls the unsubscribe method. In Figure 45-7, create stands for a call to JMSContext.createDurableConsumer, close stands for a call to JMSConsumer.close, and unsubscribe stands for a call to JMSContext.unsubscribe. Messages sent after the first consumer is closed are received when the second consumer is created (on the same durable subscription), so even though messages M2, M4, and M5 arrive while there is no consumer, they are not lost.

Figure 45-7 Consumers on a Durable Subscription

Description of "Figure 45-7 Consumers on a Durable Subscription"

A shared durable subscription allows you to use multiple consumers to receive messages from a durable subscription. If you use a shared durable subscription, the connection factory you use does not need to have a client identifier. To create a shared durable subscription, call the JMSContext.createSharedDurableConsumer method, specifying the topic and subscription name:

JMSConsumer consumer = 
        context.createSharedDurableConsumer(topic, "MakeItLast");

See Acknowledging Messages, Using Durable Subscriptions, Using Shared Durable Subscriptions, and Sending Messages from a Session Bean to an MDB for examples of Java EE applications that use durable subscriptions.

45.3.6.5 Creating Shared Subscriptions

A topic subscription created by the createConsumer or createDurableConsumer method can have only one consumer (although a topic can have many). Multiple clients consuming from the same topic have, by definition, multiple subscriptions to the topic, and all the clients receive all the messages sent to the topic (unless they filter them with message selectors).

It is, however, possible to create a nondurable shared subscription to a topic by using the createSharedConsumer method and specifying not only a destination but a subscription name:

consumer = context.createSharedConsumer(topicName, "SubName");

With a shared subscription, messages will be distributed among multiple clients that use the same topic and subscription name. Each message sent to the topic will be added to every subscription (subject to any message selectors), but each message added to a subscription will be delivered to only one of the consumers on that subscription, so it will be received by only one of the clients. A shared subscription can be useful if you want to share the message load among several consumers on the subscription rather than having just one consumer on the subscription receive each message. This feature can improve the scalability of Java EE application client applications and Java SE applications. (Message-driven beans share the work of processing messages from a topic among multiple threads.)

See Using Shared Nondurable Subscriptions for a simple example of using shared nondurable consumers.

You can also create shared durable subscriptions by using the JMSContext.createSharedDurableConsumer method. For details, see Creating Durable Subscriptions.

45.3.7 JMS Messages

The ultimate purpose of a JMS application is to produce and consume messages that can then be used by other software applications. JMS messages have a basic format that is simple but highly flexible, allowing you to create messages that match formats used by non-JMS applications on heterogeneous platforms.

A JMS message can have three parts: a header, properties, and a body. Only the header is required. The following sections describe these parts.

For complete documentation of message headers, properties, and bodies, see the documentation of the Message interface in the API documentation. For a list of possible message types, see Message Bodies.

45.3.7.1 Message Headers

A JMS message header contains a number of predefined fields that contain values used by both clients and providers to identify and route messages. Table 45-1 lists and describes the JMS message header fields and indicates how their values are set. For example, every message has a unique identifier, which is represented in the header field JMSMessageID. The value of another header field, JMSDestination, represents the queue or the topic to which the message is sent. Other fields include a timestamp and a priority level.

Each header field has associated setter and getter methods, which are documented in the description of the Message interface. Some header fields are intended to be set by a client, but many are set automatically by the send method, which overrides any client-set values.

Table 45-1 How JMS Message Header Field Values Are Set

Header Field | Description | Set By

JMSDestination

|

Destination to which the message is being sent

|

JMS provider send method

JMSDeliveryMode

|

Delivery mode specified when the message was sent (see Specifying Message Persistence)

|

JMS provider send method

JMSDeliveryTime

|

The time the message was sent plus the delivery delay specified when the message was sent (see Specifying a Delivery Delay

|

JMS provider send method

JMSExpiration

|

Expiration time of the message (see Allowing Messages to Expire)

|

JMS provider send method

JMSPriority

|

The priority of the message (see Setting Message Priority Levels)

|

JMS provider send method

JMSMessageID

|

Value that uniquely identifies each message sent by a provider

|

JMS provider send method

JMSTimestamp

|

The time the message was handed off to a provider to be sent

|

JMS provider send method

JMSCorrelationID

|

Value that links one message to another; commonly the JMSMessageID value is used

|

Client application

JMSReplyTo

|

Destination where replies to the message should be sent

|

Client application

JMSType

|

Type identifier supplied by client application

|

Client application

JMSRedelivered

|

Whether the message is being redelivered

|

JMS provider prior to delivery

45.3.7.2 Message Properties

You can create and set properties for messages if you need values in addition to those provided by the header fields. You can use properties to provide compatibility with other messaging systems, or you can use them to create message selectors (see JMS Message Selectors). For an example of setting a property to be used as a message selector, see Sending Messages from a Session Bean to an MDB.

The JMS API provides some predefined property names that begin with JMSX. A JMS provider is required to implement only one of these, JMSXDeliveryCount (which specifies the number of times a message has been delivered); the rest are optional. The use of these predefined properties or of user-defined properties in applications is optional.

45.3.7.3 Message Bodies

The JMS API defines six different types of messages. Each message type corresponds to a different message body. These message types allow you to send and receive data in many different forms. Table 45-2 describes these message types.

Table 45-2 JMS Message Types

Message Type | Body Contains

TextMessage

|

A java.lang.String object (for example, the contents of an XML file).

MapMessage

|

A set of name-value pairs, with names as String objects and values as primitive types in the Java programming language. The entries can be accessed sequentially by enumerator or randomly by name. The order of the entries is undefined.

BytesMessage

|

A stream of uninterpreted bytes. This message type is for literally encoding a body to match an existing message format.

StreamMessage

|

A stream of primitive values in the Java programming language, filled and read sequentially.

ObjectMessage

|

A Serializable object in the Java programming language.

Message

|

Nothing. Composed of header fields and properties only. This message type is useful when a message body is not required.

The JMS API provides methods for creating messages of each type and for filling in their contents. For example, to create and send a TextMessage, you might use the following statements:

TextMessage message = context.createTextMessage();
message.setText(msg_text);     // msg_text is a String
context.createProducer().send(message);

At the consuming end, a message arrives as a generic Message object. You can then cast the object to the appropriate message type and use more specific methods to access the body and extract the message contents (and its headers and properties if needed). For example, you might use the stream-oriented read methods of BytesMessage. You must always cast to the appropriate message type to retrieve the body of a StreamMessage.

Instead of casting the message to a message type, you can call the getBody method on the Message, specifying the type of the message as an argument. For example, you can retrieve a TextMessage as a String. The following code fragment uses the getBody method:

Message m = consumer.receive();
if (m instanceof TextMessage) {
    String message = m.getBody(String.class);
    System.out.println("Reading message: " + message);
} else {
    // Handle error or process another message type
}

The JMS API provides shortcuts for creating and receiving a TextMessage, BytesMessage, MapMessage, or ObjectMessage. For example, you do not have to wrap a string in a TextMessage; instead, you can send and receive the string directly. For example, you can send a string as follows:

String message = "This is a message";
context.createProducer().send(dest, message);

You can receive the message by using the receiveBody method:

String message = receiver.receiveBody(String.class);

You can use the receiveBody method to receive any type of message except StreamMessage and Message, as long as the body of the message can be assigned to a particular type.

An empty Message can be useful if you want to send a message that is simply a signal to the application. Some of the examples in Chapter 46, "Java Message Service Examples," send an empty message after sending a series of text messages. For example:

context.createProducer().send(dest, context.createMessage());

The consumer code can then interpret a non-text message as a signal that all the messages sent have now been received.

The examples in Chapter 46, "Java Message Service Examples," use messages of type TextMessage, MapMessage, and Message.

45.3.8 JMS Queue Browsers

Messages sent to a queue remain in the queue until the message consumer for that queue consumes them. The JMS API provides a QueueBrowser object that allows you to browse the messages in the queue and display the header values for each message. To create a QueueBrowser object, use the JMSContext.createBrowser method. For example:

QueueBrowser browser = context.createBrowser(queue);

See Browsing Messages on a Queue for an example of using a QueueBrowser object.

The createBrowser method allows you to specify a message selector as a second argument when you create a QueueBrowser. For information on message selectors, see JMS Message Selectors.

The JMS API provides no mechanism for browsing a topic. Messages usually disappear from a topic as soon as they appear: If there are no message consumers to consume them, the JMS provider removes them. Although durable subscriptions allow messages to remain on a topic while the message consumer is not active, JMS does not define any facility for examining them.

45.3.9 JMS Exception Handling

The root class for all checked exceptions in the JMS API is JMSException. The root cause for all unchecked exceptions in the JMS API is JMSRuntimeException.

Catching JMSException and JMSRuntimeException provides a generic way of handling all exceptions related to the JMS API.

The JMSException and JMSRuntimeException classes include the following subclasses, described in the API documentation:

IllegalStateException, IllegalStateRuntimeException

InvalidClientIDException, InvalidClientIDRuntimeException

InvalidDestinationException, InvalidDestinationRuntimeException

InvalidSelectorException, InvalidSelectorRuntimeException

JMSSecurityException, JMSSecurityRuntimeException

MessageEOFException

MessageFormatException, MessageFormatRuntimeException

MessageNotReadableException

MessageNotWriteableException, MessageNotWriteableRuntimeException

ResourceAllocationException, ResourceAllocationRuntimeException

TransactionInProgressException, TransactionInProgressRuntimeException

TransactionRolledBackException, TransactionRolledBackRuntimeException

All the examples in the tutorial catch and handle JMSException or JMSRuntimeException when it is appropriate to do so.

45.4 Using Advanced JMS Features

This section explains how to use features of the JMS API to achieve the level of reliability and performance your application requires. Many people use JMS in their applications because they cannot tolerate dropped or duplicate messages and because they require that every message be received once and only once. The JMS API provides this functionality.

The most reliable way to produce a message is to send a PERSISTENT message, and to do so within a transaction.

JMS messages are PERSISTENT by default; PERSISTENT messages will not be lost in the event of JMS provider failure. For details, see Specifying Message Persistence.

Transactions allow multiple messages to be sent or received in an atomic operation. In the Java EE platform they also allow message sends and receives to be combined with database reads and writes in an atomic transaction. A transaction is a unit of work into which you can group a series of operations, such as message sends and receives, so that the operations either all succeed or all fail. For details, see Using JMS Local Transactions.

The most reliable way to consume a message is to do so within a transaction, either from a queue or from a durable subscription to a topic. For details, see Creating Durable Subscriptions, Creating Temporary Destinations, and Using JMS Local Transactions.

Some features primarily allow an application to improve performance. For example, you can set messages to expire after a certain length of time (see Allowing Messages to Expire), so that consumers do not receive unnecessary outdated information. You can send messages asynchronously; see Sending Messages Asynchronously.

You can also specify various levels of control over message acknowledgment; see Controlling Message Acknowledgment.

Other features can provide useful capabilities unrelated to reliability. For example, you can create temporary destinations that last only for the duration of the connection in which they are created. See Creating Temporary Destinations for details.

The following sections describe these features as they apply to application clients or Java SE clients. Some of the features work differently in the Java EE web or EJB container; in these cases, the differences are noted here and are explained in detail in Using the JMS API in Java EE Applications.

45.4.1 Controlling Message Acknowledgment

Until a JMS message has been acknowledged, it is not considered to be successfully consumed. The successful consumption of a message ordinarily takes place in three stages.

The client receives the message.

The client processes the message.

The message is acknowledged. Acknowledgment is initiated either by the JMS provider or by the client, depending on the session acknowledgment mode.

In locally transacted sessions (see Using JMS Local Transactions), a message is acknowledged when the session is committed. If a transaction is rolled back, all consumed messages are redelivered.

In a JTA transaction (in the Java EE web or EJB container) a message is acknowledged when the transaction is committed.

In nontransacted sessions, when and how a message is acknowledged depend on a value that may be specified as an argument of the createContext method. The possible argument values are as follows.

JMSContext.AUTO_ACKNOWLEDGE: This setting is the default for application clients and Java SE clients. The JMSContext automatically acknowledges a client's receipt of a message either when the client has successfully returned from a call to receive or when the MessageListener it has called to process the message returns successfully.

A synchronous receive in a JMSContext that is configured to use auto-acknowledgment is the one exception to the rule that message consumption is a three-stage process as described earlier. In this case, the receipt and acknowledgment take place in one step, followed by the processing of the message.

JMSContext.CLIENT_ACKNOWLEDGE: A client acknowledges a message by calling the message's acknowledge method. In this mode, acknowledgment takes place on the session level: Acknowledging a consumed message automatically acknowledges the receipt of all messages that have been consumed by its session. For example, if a message consumer consumes ten messages and then acknowledges the fifth message delivered, all ten messages are acknowledged.

Note:

In the Java EE platform, the JMSContext.CLIENT_ACKNOWLEDGE setting can be used only in an application client, not in a web component or enterprise bean.

JMSContext.DUPS_OK_ACKNOWLEDGE: This option instructs the JMSContext to lazily acknowledge the delivery of messages. This is likely to result in the delivery of some duplicate messages if the JMS provider fails, so it should be used only by consumers that can tolerate duplicate messages. (If the JMS provider redelivers a message, it must set the value of the JMSRedelivered message header to true.) This option can reduce session overhead by minimizing the work the session does to prevent duplicates.

If messages have been received from a queue but not acknowledged when a JMSContext is closed, the JMS provider retains them and redelivers them when a consumer next accesses the queue. The provider also retains unacknowledged messages if an application closes a JMSContext that has been consuming messages from a durable subscription. (See Creating Durable Subscriptions.) Unacknowledged messages that have been received from a nondurable subscription will be dropped when the JMSContext is closed.

If you use a queue or a durable subscription, you can use the JMSContext.recover method to stop a nontransacted JMSContext and restart it with its first unacknowledged message. In effect, the JMSContext's series of delivered messages is reset to the point after its last acknowledged message. The messages it now delivers may be different from those that were originally delivered, if messages have expired or if higher-priority messages have arrived. For a consumer on a nondurable subscription, the provider may drop unacknowledged messages when the JMSContext.recover method is called.

The sample program in Acknowledging Messages demonstrates two ways to ensure that a message will not be acknowledged until processing of the message is complete.

45.4.2 Specifying Options for Sending Messages

You can set a number of options when you send a message. These options enable you to perform the following tasks:

Specify that messages are persistent, meaning they must not be lost in the event of a provider failure (Specifying Message Persistence)

Set priority levels for messages, which can affect the order in which the messages are delivered (Setting Message Priority Levels)

Specify an expiration time for messages so they will not be delivered if they are obsolete (Allowing Messages to Expire)

Specify a delivery delay for messages so that they will not be delivered until a specified amount of time has expired (Specifying a Delivery Delay)

Method chaining allows you to specify more than one of these options when you create a producer and call the send method; see Using JMSProducer Method Chaining.

45.4.2.1 Specifying Message Persistence

The JMS API supports two delivery modes specifying whether messages are lost if the JMS provider fails. These delivery modes are fields of the DeliveryMode interface.

The default delivery mode, PERSISTENT, instructs the JMS provider to take extra care to ensure that a message is not lost in transit in case of a JMS provider failure. A message sent with this delivery mode is logged to stable storage when it is sent.

The NON_PERSISTENT delivery mode does not require the JMS provider to store the message or otherwise guarantee that it is not lost if the provider fails.

To specify the delivery mode, use the setDeliveryMode method of the JMSProducer interface to set the delivery mode for all messages sent by that producer.

You can use method chaining to set the delivery mode when you create a producer and send a message. The following call creates a producer with a NON_PERSISTENT delivery mode and uses it to send a message:

context.createProducer()
       .setDeliveryMode(DeliveryMode.NON_PERSISTENT).send(dest, msg);

If you do not specify a delivery mode, the default is PERSISTENT. Using the NON_PERSISTENT delivery mode may improve performance and reduce storage overhead, but you should use it only if your application can afford to miss messages.

45.4.2.2 Setting Message Priority Levels

You can use message priority levels to instruct the JMS provider to deliver urgent messages first. Use the setPriority method of the JMSProducer interface to set the priority level for all messages sent by that producer.

You can use method chaining to set the priority level when you create a producer and send a message. For example, the following call sets a priority level of 7 for a producer and then sends a message:

context.createProducer().setPriority(7).send(dest, msg);

The ten levels of priority range from 0 (lowest) to 9 (highest). If you do not specify a priority level, the default level is 4. A JMS provider tries to deliver higher-priority messages before lower-priority ones, but does not have to deliver messages in exact order of priority.

45.4.2.3 Allowing Messages to Expire

By default, a message never expires. If a message will become obsolete after a certain period, however, you may want to set an expiration time. Use the setTimeToLive method of the JMSProducer interface to set a default expiration time for all messages sent by that producer.

For example, a message that contains rapidly changing data such as a stock price will become obsolete after a few minutes, so you might configure messages to expire after that time.

You can use method chaining to set the time to live when you create a producer and send a message. For example, the following call sets a time to live of five minutes for a producer and then sends a message:

context.createProducer().setTimeToLive(300000).send(dest, msg);

If the specified timeToLive value is 0, the message never expires.

When the message is sent, the specified timeToLive is added to the current time to give the expiration time. Any message not delivered before the specified expiration time is destroyed. The destruction of obsolete messages conserves storage and computing resources.

45.4.2.4 Specifying a Delivery Delay

You can specify a length of time that must elapse after a message is sent before the JMS provider delivers the message. Use the setDeliveryDelay method of the JMSProducer interface to set a delivery delay for all messages sent by that producer.

You can use method chaining to set the delivery delay when you create a producer and send a message. For example, the following call sets a delivery delay of 3 seconds for a producer and then sends a message:

context.createProducer().setDeliveryDelay(3000).send(dest, msg);

45.4.2.5 Using JMSProducer Method Chaining

The setter methods on the JMSProducer interface return JMSProducer objects, so you can use method chaining to create a producer, set multiple properties, and send a message. For example, the following chained method calls create a producer, set a user-defined property, set the expiration, delivery mode, and priority for the message, and then send a message to a queue:

context.createProducer()
        .setProperty("MyProperty", "MyValue")
        .setTimeToLive(10000)
        .setDeliveryMode(NON_PERSISTENT)
        .setPriority(2)
        .send(queue, body);

You can also call the JMSProducer methods to set properties on a message and then send the message in a separate send method call. You can also set message properties directly on a message.

45.4.3 Creating Temporary Destinations

Normally, you create JMS destinations (queues and topics) administratively rather than programmatically. Your JMS provider includes a tool to create and remove destinations, and it is common for destinations to be long-lasting.

The JMS API also enables you to create destinations (TemporaryQueue and TemporaryTopic objects) that last only for the duration of the connection in which they are created. You create these destinations dynamically using the JMSContext.createTemporaryQueue and the JMSContext.createTemporaryTopic methods, as in the following example:

TemporaryTopic replyTopic = context.createTemporaryTopic();

The only message consumers that can consume from a temporary destination are those created by the same connection that created the destination. Any message producer can send to the temporary destination. If you close the connection to which a temporary destination belongs, the destination is closed and its contents are lost.

You can use temporary destinations to implement a simple request/reply mechanism. If you create a temporary destination and specify it as the value of the JMSReplyTo message header field when you send a message, then the consumer of the message can use the value of the JMSReplyTo field as the destination to which it sends a reply. The consumer can also reference the original request by setting the JMSCorrelationID header field of the reply message to the value of the JMSMessageID header field of the request. For example, an onMessage method can create a JMSContext so that it can send a reply to the message it receives. It can use code such as the following:

replyMsg = context.createTextMessage("Consumer processed message: " 
        + msg.getText());
replyMsg.setJMSCorrelationID(msg.getJMSMessageID());
context.createProducer().send((Topic) msg.getJMSReplyTo(), replyMsg);

For an example, see Using an Entity to Join Messages from Two MDBs.

45.4.4 Using JMS Local Transactions

A transaction groups a series of operations into an atomic unit of work. If any one of the operations fails, the transaction can be rolled back, and the operations can be attempted again from the beginning. If all the operations succeed, the transaction can be committed.

In an application client or a Java SE client, you can use local transactions to group message sends and receives. You use the JMSContext.commit method to commit a transaction. You can send multiple messages in a transaction, and the messages will not be added to the queue or topic until the transaction is committed. If you receive multiple messages in a transaction, they will not be acknowledged until the transaction is committed.

You can use the JMSContext.rollback method to roll back a transaction. A transaction rollback means that all produced messages are destroyed and all consumed messages are recovered and redelivered unless they have expired (see Allowing Messages to Expire).

A transacted session is always involved in a transaction. To create a transacted session, call the createContext method as follows:

JMSContext context = 
        connectionFactory.createContext(JMSContext.SESSION_TRANSACTED);

As soon as the commit or the rollback method is called, one transaction ends and another transaction begins. Closing a transacted session rolls back its transaction in progress, including any pending sends and receives.

In an application running in the Java EE web or EJB container, you cannot use local transactions. Instead, you use JTA transactions, described in Using the JMS API in Java EE Applications.

You can combine several sends and receives in a single JMS local transaction, so long as they are all performed using the same JMSContext.

Do not use a single transaction if you use a request/reply mechanism, in which you send a message and then receive a reply to that message. If you try to use a single transaction, the program will hang, because the send cannot take place until the transaction is committed. The following code fragment illustrates the problem:

// Don't do this!
outMsg.setJMSReplyTo(replyQueue);
context.createProducer().send(outQueue, outMsg);
consumer = context.createConsumer(replyQueue);
inMsg = consumer.receive();
context.commit();

Because a message sent during a transaction is not actually sent until the transaction is committed, the transaction cannot contain any receives that depend on that message's having been sent.

The production and the consumption of a message cannot both be part of the same transaction. The reason is that the transactions take place between the clients and the JMS provider, which intervenes between the production and the consumption of the message. Figure 45-8 illustrates this interaction.

Figure 45-8 Using JMS Local Transactions

Description of "Figure 45-8 Using JMS Local Transactions"

The sending of one or more messages to one or more destinations by Client 1 can form a single transaction, because it forms a single set of interactions with the JMS provider using a single JMSContext. Similarly, the receiving of one or more messages from one or more destinations by Client 2 also forms a single transaction using a single JMSContext. But because the two clients have no direct interaction and are using two different JMSContext objects, no transactions can take place between them.

Another way of putting this is that a transaction is a contract between a client and a JMS provider that defines whether a message is sent to a destination or whether a message is received from the destination. It is not a contract between the sending client and the receiving client.

This is the fundamental difference between messaging and synchronized processing. Instead of tightly coupling the sender and the receiver of a message, JMS couples the sender of a message with the destination, and it separately couples the destination with the receiver of the message. Therefore, while the sends and receives each have a tight coupling with the JMS provider, they do not have any coupling with each other.

When you create a JMSContext, you can specify whether it is transacted by using the JMSContext.SESSION_TRANSACTED argument to the createContext method. For example:

try (JMSContext context = connectionFactory.createContext(
        JMSContext.SESSION_TRANSACTED);) {
    ...

The commit and the rollback methods for local transactions are associated with the session that underlies the JMSContext. You can combine operations on more than one queue or topic, or on a combination of queues and topics, in a single transaction if you use the same session to perform the operations. For example, you can use the same JMSContext to receive a message from a queue and send a message to a topic in the same transaction.

The example in Using Local Transactions shows how to use JMS local transactions.

45.4.5 Sending Messages Asynchronously

Normally, when you send a persistent message, the send method blocks until the JMS provider confirms that the message was sent successfully. The asynchronous send mechanism allows your application to send a message and continue work while waiting to learn whether the send completed.

This feature is currently available only in application clients and Java SE clients.

Sending a message asynchronously involves supplying a callback object. You specify a CompletionListener with an onCompletion method. For example, the following code instantiates a CompletionListener named SendListener. It then calls the setAsync method to specify that sends from this producer should be asynchronous and should use the specified listener:

CompletionListener listener = new SendListener();
context.createProducer().setAsync(listener).send(dest, message);

The CompletionListener class must implement two methods, onCompletion and onException. The onCompletion method is called if the send succeeds, and the onException method is called if it fails. A simple implementation of these methods might look like this:

@Override
public void onCompletion(Message message) {
    System.out.println("onCompletion method: Send has completed.");
}

@Override
public void onException(Message message, Exception e) {
    System.out.println("onException method: send failed: " + e.toString());
    System.out.println("Unsent message is: \n" + message);
}

45.5 Using the JMS API in Java EE Applications

This section describes how using the JMS API in enterprise bean applications or web applications differs from using it in application clients.

A general rule in the Java EE platform specification applies to all Java EE components that use the JMS API within EJB or web containers: Application components in the web and EJB containers must not attempt to create more than one active (not closed) Session object per connection. Multiple JMSContext objects are permitted, however, since they combine a single connection and a single session.

This rule does not apply to application clients. The application client container supports the creation of multiple sessions for each connection.

45.5.1 Creating Resources for Java EE Applications

You can use annotations to create application-specific connection factories and destinations for Java EE enterprise bean or web components. The resources you create in this way are visible only to the application for which you create them.

You can also use deployment descriptor elements to create these resources. Elements specified in the deployment descriptor override elements specified in annotations. See Packaging Applications for basic information about deployment descriptors. You must use a deployment descriptor to create application-specific resources for application clients.

To create a destination, use a @JMSDestinationDefinition annotation like the following on a class:

@JMSDestinationDefinition(
    name = "java:app/jms/myappTopic",
    interfaceName = "javax.jms.Topic",
    destinationName = "MyPhysicalAppTopic"
  )

The name, interfaceName, and destinationName elements are required. You can optionally specify a description element. To create multiple destinations, enclose them in a @JMSDestinationDefinitions annotation, separated by commas.

To create a connection factory, use a @JMSConnectionFactoryDefinition annotation like the following on a class:

@JMSConnectionFactoryDefinition(
    name="java:app/jms/MyConnectionFactory"
)

The name element is required. You can optionally specify a number of other elements, such as clientId if you want to use the connection factory for durable subscriptions, or description. If you do not specify the interfaceName element, the default interface is javax.jms.ConnectionFactory. To create multiple connection factories, enclose them in a @JMSConnectionFactoryDefinitions annotation, separated by commas.

You need to specify the annotation only once for a given application, in any of the components.

Note:

If your application contains one or more message-driven beans, you may want to place the annotation on one of the message-driven beans. If you place the annotation on a sending component such as an application client, you need to specify the mappedName element to look up the topic, instead of using the destinationLookup property of the activation configuration specification.

When you inject the resource into a component, use the value of the name element in the definition annotation as the value of the lookup element in the @Resource annotation:

@Resource(lookup = "java:app/jms/myappTopic")
private Topic topic;

The following portable JNDI namespaces are available. Which ones you can use depends on how your application is packaged.

java:global: Makes the resource available to all deployed applications

java:app: Makes the resource available to all components in all modules in a single application

java:module: Makes the resource available to all components within a given module (for example, all enterprise beans within an EJB module)

java:comp: Makes the resource available to a single component only (except in a web application, where it is equivalent to java:module)

See the API documentation for details on these annotations. The examples in Sending and Receiving Messages Using a Simple Web Application, Sending Messages from a Session Bean to an MDB, and Using an Entity to Join Messages from Two MDBs all use the @JMSDestinationDefinition annotation. The other JMS examples do not use these annotations. The examples that consist only of application clients are not deployed in the application server and must therefore communicate with each other using administratively created resources that exist outside of individual applications.

45.5.2 Using Resource Injection in Enterprise Bean or Web Components

You may use resource injection to inject both administered objects and JMSContext objects in Java EE applications.

45.5.2.1 Injecting a ConnectionFactory, Queue, or Topic

Normally, you use the @Resource annotation to inject a ConnectionFactory, Queue, or Topic into your Java EE application. These objects must be created administratively before you deploy your application. You may want to use the default connection factory, whose JNDI name is java:comp/DefaultJMSConnectionFactory.

When you use resource injection in an application client component, you normally declare the JMS resource static:

@Resource(lookup = "java:comp/DefaultJMSConnectionFactory")
private static ConnectionFactory connectionFactory;

@Resource(lookup = "jms/MyQueue")
private static Queue queue;

However, when you use this annotation in a session bean, a message-driven bean, or a web component, do not declare the resource static:

@Resource(lookup = "java:comp/DefaultJMSConnectionFactory")
private ConnectionFactory connectionFactory;

@Resource(lookup = "jms/MyTopic")
private Topic topic;

If you declare the resource static in these components, runtime errors will result.

45.5.2.2 Injecting a JMSContext Object

To access a JMSContext object in an enterprise bean or web component, instead of injecting the ConnectionFactory resource and then creating a JMSContext, you can use the @Inject and @JMSConnectionFactory annotations to inject a JMSContext. To use the default connection factory, use code like the following:

@Inject
private JMSContext context1;

To use your own connection factory, use code like the following:

@Inject
@JMSConnectionFactory("jms/MyConnectionFactory")
private JMSContext context2;

45.5.3 Using Java EE Components to Produce and to Synchronously Receive Messages

An application that produces messages or synchronously receives them can use a Java EE web or EJB component, such as a managed bean, a servlet, or a session bean, to perform these operations. The example in Sending Messages from a Session Bean to an MDB uses a stateless session bean to send messages to a topic. The example in Sending and Receiving Messages Using a Simple Web Application uses managed beans to produce and to consume messages.

Because a synchronous receive with no specified timeout ties up server resources, this mechanism usually is not the best application design for a web or EJB component. Instead, use a synchronous receive that specifies a timeout value, or use a message-driven bean to receive messages asynchronously. For details about synchronous receives, see JMS Message Consumers.

Using the JMS API in a Java EE component is in many ways similar to using it in an application client. The main differences are the areas of resource management and transactions.

45.5.3.1 Managing JMS Resources in Web and EJB Components

The JMS resources are a connection and a session, usually combined in a JMSContext object. In general, it is important to release JMS resources when they are no longer being used. Here are some useful practices to follow.

If you wish to maintain a JMS resource only for the life span of a business method, use a try-with-resources statement to create the JMSContext so that it will be closed automatically at the end of the try block.

To maintain a JMS resource for the duration of a transaction or request, inject the JMSContext as described in Injecting a JMSContext Object. This will also cause the resource to be released when it is no longer needed.

If you would like to maintain a JMS resource for the life span of an enterprise bean instance, you can use a @PostConstruct callback method to create the resource and a @PreDestroy callback method to close the resource. However, there is normally no need to do this, since application servers usually maintain a pool of connections. If you use a stateful session bean and you wish to maintain the JMS resource in a cached state, you must close the resource in a @PrePassivate callback method and set its value to null, and you must create it again in a @PostActivate callback method.

45.5.3.2 Managing Transactions in Session Beans

Instead of using local transactions, you use JTA transactions. You can use either container-managed transactions or bean-managed transactions. Normally, you use container-managed transactions for bean methods that perform sends or receives, allowing the EJB container to handle transaction demarcation. Because container-managed transactions are the default, you do not have to specify them.

You can use bean-managed transactions and the javax.transaction.UserTransaction interface's transaction demarcation methods, but you should do so only if your application has special requirements and you are an expert in using transactions. Usually, container-managed transactions produce the most efficient and correct behavior. This tutorial does not provide any examples of bean-managed transactions.

45.5.4 Using Message-Driven Beans to Receive Messages Asynchronously

The sections What Is a Message-Driven Bean? and How Does the JMS API Work with the Java EE Platform? describe how the Java EE platform supports a special kind of enterprise bean, the message-driven bean, which allows Java EE applications to process JMS messages asynchronously. Other Java EE web and EJB components allow you to send messages and to receive them synchronously but not asynchronously.

A message-driven bean is a message listener to which messages can be delivered from either a queue or a topic. The messages can be sent by any Java EE component (from an application client, another enterprise bean, or a web component) or from an application or a system that does not use Java EE technology.

A message-driven bean class has the following requirements.

It must be annotated with the @MessageDriven annotation if it does not use a deployment descriptor.

The class must be defined as public, but not as abstract or final.

It must contain a public constructor with no arguments.

It is recommended, but not required, that a message-driven bean class implement the message listener interface for the message type it supports. A bean that supports the JMS API implements the javax.jms.MessageListener interface, which means that it must provide an onMessage method with the following signature:

void onMessage(Message inMessage)

The onMessage method is called by the bean's container when a message has arrived for the bean to service. This method contains the business logic that handles the processing of the message. It is the message-driven bean's responsibility to parse the message and perform the necessary business logic.

A message-driven bean differs from an application client's message listener in the following ways.

In an application client, you must create a JMSContext, then create a JMSConsumer, then call setMessageListener to activate the listener. For a message-driven bean, you need only define the class and annotate it, and the EJB container creates it for you.

The bean class uses the @MessageDriven annotation, which typically contains an activationConfig element containing @ActivationConfigProperty annotations that specify properties used by the bean or the connection factory. These properties can include the connection factory, a destination type, a durable subscription, a message selector, or an acknowledgment mode. Some of the examples in Chapter 46, "Java Message Service Examples" set these properties. You can also set the properties in the deployment descriptor.

The application client container has only one instance of a MessageListener, which is called on a single thread at a time. A message-driven bean, however, may have multiple instances, configured by the container, which may be called concurrently by multiple threads (although each instance is called by only one thread at a time). Message-driven beans may therefore allow much faster processing of messages than message listeners.

You do not need to specify a message acknowledgment mode unless you use bean-managed transactions. The message is consumed in the transaction in which the onMessage method is invoked.

Table 45-3 lists the activation configuration properties defined by the JMS specification.

Table 45-3 @ActivationConfigProperty Settings for Message-Driven Beans

Property Name | Description

acknowledgeMode

|

Acknowledgment mode, used only for bean-managed transactions; the default is Auto-acknowledge (Dups-ok-acknowledge is also permitted)

destinationLookup

|

The lookup name of the queue or topic from which the bean will receive messages

destinationType

|

Either javax.jms.Queue or javax.jms.Topic

subscriptionDurability

|

For durable subscriptions, set the value to Durable; see Creating Durable Subscriptions for more information

clientId

|

For durable subscriptions, the client ID for the connection (optional)

subscriptionName

|

For durable subscriptions, the name of the subscription

messageSelector

|

A string that filters messages; see JMS Message Selectors for information

connectionFactoryLookup

|

The lookup name of the connection factory to be used to connect to the JMS provider from which the bean will receive messages

For example, here is the message-driven bean used in Receiving Messages Asynchronously Using a Message-Driven Bean:

@MessageDriven(activationConfig = {
    @ActivationConfigProperty(propertyName = "destinationLookup",
            propertyValue = "jms/MyQueue"),
    @ActivationConfigProperty(propertyName = "destinationType",
            propertyValue = "javax.jms.Queue")
})
public class SimpleMessageBean implements MessageListener {

    @Resource
    private MessageDrivenContext mdc;
    static final Logger logger = Logger.getLogger("SimpleMessageBean");

    public SimpleMessageBean() {
    }

    @Override
    public void onMessage(Message inMessage) {

        try {
            if (inMessage instanceof TextMessage) {
                logger.log(Level.INFO,
                        "MESSAGE BEAN: Message received: {0}",
                        inMessage.getBody(String.class));
            } else {
                logger.log(Level.WARNING,
                        "Message of wrong type: {0}",
                        inMessage.getClass().getName());
            }
        } catch (JMSException e) {
            logger.log(Level.SEVERE,
                    "SimpleMessageBean.onMessage: JMSException: {0}",
                    e.toString());
            mdc.setRollbackOnly();
        }
    }
}

If JMS is integrated with the application server using a resource adapter, the JMS resource adapter handles these tasks for the EJB container.

The bean class commonly injects a MessageDrivenContext resource, which provides some additional methods you can use for transaction management (setRollbackOnly, for example):

    @Resource
    private MessageDrivenContext mdc;

A message-driven bean never has a local or remote interface. Instead, it has only a bean class.

A message-driven bean is similar in some ways to a stateless session bean: Its instances are relatively short-lived and retain no state for a specific client. The instance variables of the message-driven bean instance can contain some state across the handling of client messages: for example, an open database connection, or an object reference to an enterprise bean object.

Like a stateless session bean, a message-driven bean can have many interchangeable instances running at the same time. The container can pool these instances to allow streams of messages to be processed concurrently. The container attempts to deliver messages in chronological order when that would not impair the concurrency of message processing, but no guarantees are made as to the exact order in which messages are delivered to the instances of the message-driven bean class. If message order is essential to your application, you may want to configure your application server to use just one instance of the message-driven bean.

For details on the lifecycle of a message-driven bean, see The Lifecycle of a Message-Driven Bean.

45.5.5 Managing JTA Transactions

Java EE application clients and Java SE clients use JMS local transactions (described in Using JMS Local Transactions), which allow the grouping of sends and receives within a specific JMS session. Java EE applications that run in the web or EJB container commonly use JTA transactions to ensure the integrity of accesses to external resources. The key difference between a JTA transaction and a JMS local transaction is that a JTA transaction is controlled by the application server's transaction managers. JTA transactions may be distributed, which means that they can encompass multiple resources in the same transaction, such as a JMS provider and a database.

For example, distributed transactions allow multiple applications to perform atomic updates on the same database, and they allow a single application to perform atomic updates on multiple databases.

In a Java EE application that uses the JMS API, you can use transactions to combine message sends or receives with database updates and other resource manager operations. You can access resources from multiple application components within a single transaction. For example, a servlet can start a transaction, access multiple databases, invoke an enterprise bean that sends a JMS message, invoke another enterprise bean that modifies an EIS system using the Connector Architecture, and finally commit the transaction. Your application cannot, however, both send a JMS message and receive a reply to it within the same transaction.

JTA transactions within the EJB and web containers can be either of two kinds.

Container-managed transactions: The container controls the integrity of your transactions without your having to call commit or rollback. Container-managed transactions are easier to use than bean-managed transactions. You can specify appropriate transaction attributes for your enterprise bean methods.

Use the Required transaction attribute (the default) to ensure that a method is always part of a transaction. If a transaction is in progress when the method is called, the method will be part of that transaction; if not, a new transaction will be started before the method is called and will be committed when the method returns. See Transaction Attributes for more information.

Bean-managed transactions: You can use these in conjunction with the javax.transaction.UserTransaction interface, which provides its own commit and rollback methods you can use to delimit transaction boundaries. Bean-managed transactions are recommended only for those who are experienced in programming transactions.

You can use either container-managed transactions or bean-managed transactions with message-driven beans. To ensure that all messages are received and handled within the context of a transaction, use container-managed transactions and use the Required transaction attribute (the default) for the onMessage method.

When you use container-managed transactions, you can call the following MessageDrivenContext methods.

setRollbackOnly: Use this method for error handling. If an exception occurs, setRollbackOnly marks the current transaction so that the only possible outcome of the transaction is a rollback.

getRollbackOnly: Use this method to test whether the current transaction has been marked for rollback.

If you use bean-managed transactions, the delivery of a message to the onMessage method takes place outside the JTA transaction context. The transaction begins when you call the UserTransaction.begin method within the onMessage method, and it ends when you call UserTransaction.commit or UserTransaction.rollback. Any call to the Connection.createSession method must take place within the transaction.

Using bean-managed transactions allows you to process the message by using more than one transaction or to have some parts of the message processing take place outside a transaction context. However, if you use container-managed transactions, the message is received by the MDB and processed by the onMessage method within the same transaction. It is not possible to achieve this behavior with bean-managed transactions.

When you create a JMSContext in a JTA transaction (in the web or EJB container), the container ignores any arguments you specify, because it manages all transactional properties. When you create a JMSContext in the web or EJB container and there is no JTA transaction, the value (if any) passed to the createContext method should be JMSContext.AUTO_ACKNOWLEDGE or JMSContext.DUPS_OK_ACKNOWLEDGE.

When you use container-managed transactions, you normally use the Required transaction attribute (the default) for your enterprise bean's business methods.

You do not specify the activation configuration property acknowledgeMode when you create a message-driven bean that uses container-managed transactions. The container acknowledges the message automatically when it commits the transaction.

If a message-driven bean uses bean-managed transactions, the message receipt cannot be part of the bean-managed transaction. You can set the activation configuration property acknowledgeMode to Auto-acknowledge or Dups-ok-acknowledge to specify how you want the message received by the message-driven bean to be acknowledged.

If the onMessage method throws a RuntimeException, the container does not acknowledge processing the message. In that case, the JMS provider will redeliver the unacknowledged message in the future.

45.6 Further Information about JMS

For more information about JMS, see

Java Message Service website:

http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/index-jsp-142945.html

Java Message Service specification, version 2.0, available from:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=343

13 Using Ajax with JavaServer Faces Technology

Ajax is an acronym for Asynchronous JavaScript and XML, a group of web technologies that enable creation of dynamic and highly responsive web applications. Using Ajax, web applications can retrieve content from the server without interfering with the display on the client. In the Java EE 7 platform, JavaServer Faces technology provides built-in support for Ajax.

Early web applications were created mostly as static web pages. When a static web page is updated by a client, the entire page has to reload to reflect the update. In effect, every update needs a page reload to reflect the change. Repetitive page reloads can result in excessive network access and can impact application performance. Technologies such as Ajax were created to overcome these deficiencies.

This chapter describes using Ajax functionality in JavaServer Faces web applications.

The following topics are addressed here:

Overview of Ajax

Using Ajax Functionality with JavaServer Faces Technology

Using Ajax with Facelets

Sending an Ajax Request

Monitoring Events on the Client

Handling Errors

Receiving an Ajax Response

Ajax Request Lifecycle

Grouping of Components

Loading JavaScript as a Resource

The ajaxguessnumber Example Application

Further Information about Ajax in JavaServer Faces Technology

13.1 Overview of Ajax

Ajax refers to JavaScript and XML, technologies that are widely used for creating dynamic and asynchronous web content. While Ajax is not limited to JavaScript and XML technologies, more often than not they are used together by web applications. The focus of this tutorial is on using JavaScript based Ajax functionality in JavaServer Faces web applications.

JavaScript is a dynamic scripting language for web applications. It allows users to add enhanced functionality to user interfaces and allows web pages to interact with clients asynchronously. JavaScript runs mainly on the client side (as in a browser) and thereby reduces server access by clients.

When a JavaScript function sends an asynchronous request from the client to the server, the server sends back a response that is used to update the page's Document Object Model (DOM). This response is often in the format of an XML document. The term Ajax refers to this interaction between the client and server.

The server response need not be in XML only; it can also be in other formats, such as JSON (see Introduction to JSON and http://www.json.org/). This tutorial does not focus on the response formats.

Ajax enables asynchronous and partial updating of web applications. Such functionality allows for highly responsive web pages that are rendered in near real time. Ajax-based web applications can access server and process information and can also retrieve data without interfering with the display and rendering of the current web page on a client (such as a browser).

Some of the advantages of using Ajax are as follows:

Form data validation in real time, eliminating the need to submit the form for verification

Enhanced functionality for web pages, such as user name and password prompts

Partial update of the web content, avoiding complete page reloads

13.2 Using Ajax Functionality with JavaServer Faces Technology

Ajax functionality can be added to a JavaServer Faces application in one of the following ways:

Adding the required JavaScript code to an application

Using the built-in Ajax resource library

In earlier releases of the Java EE platform, JavaServer Faces applications provided Ajax functionality by adding the necessary JavaScript to the web page. In the Java EE 7 platform, standard Ajax support is provided by a built-in JavaScript resource library.

With the support of this JavaScript resource library, JavaServer Faces standard UI components, such as buttons, labels, or text fields, can be enabled for Ajax functionality. You can also load this resource library and use its methods directly from within the managed bean code. The next sections of the tutorial describe the use of the built-in Ajax resource library.

In addition, because the JavaServer Faces technology component model can be extended, custom components can be created with Ajax functionality.

The tutorial examples include an Ajax version of the guessnumber application, ajaxguessnumber. See The ajaxguessnumber Example Application for more information.

The Ajax specific f:ajax tag and its attributes are explained in the next sections.

13.3 Using Ajax with Facelets

As mentioned in the previous section, JavaServer Faces technology supports Ajax by using a built-in JavaScript resource library that is provided as part of the JavaServer Faces core libraries. This built-in Ajax resource can be used in JavaServer Faces web applications in one of the following ways.

By using the f:ajax tag along with another standard component in a Facelets application. This method adds Ajax functionality to any UI component without additional coding and configuration.

By using the JavaScript API method jsf.ajax.request() directly within the Facelets application. This method provides direct access to Ajax methods and allows customized control of component behavior.

13.3.1 Using the f:ajax Tag

The f:ajax tag is a JavaServer Faces core tag that provides Ajax functionality to any regular UI component when used in conjunction with that component. In the following example, Ajax behavior is added to an input component by including the f:ajax core tag:

<h:inputText value="#{bean.message}">
    <f:ajax />
</h:inputText>

In this example, although Ajax is enabled, the other attributes of the f:ajax tag are not defined. If an event is not defined, the default action for the component is performed. For the inputText component, when no event attribute is specified, the default event is valueChange. Table 13-1 lists the attributes of the f:ajax tag and their default actions.

Table 13-1 Attributes of the f:ajax Tag

Name | Type | Description

disabled

|

javax.el.ValueExpression that evaluates to a Boolean

|

A Boolean value that identifies the tag status. A value of true indicates that the Ajax behavior should not be rendered. A value of false indicates that the Ajax behavior should be rendered. The default value is false.

event

|

javax.el.ValueExpression that evaluates to a String

|

A String that identifies the type of event to which the Ajax action will apply. If specified, it must be one of the events supported by the component. If not specified, the default event (the event that triggers the Ajax request) is determined for the component. The default event is action for javax.faces.component.ActionSource components and valueChange for javax.faces.component.EditableValueHolder components.

execute

|

javax.el.ValueExpression that evaluates to an Object

|

A Collection that identifies a list of components to be executed on the server. If a literal is specified, it must be a space-delimited String of component identifiers and/or one of the keywords. If a ValueExpression is specified, it must refer to a property that returns a Collection of String objects. If not specified, the default value is @this.

immediate

|

javax.el.ValueExpression that evaluates to a Boolean

|

A Boolean value that indicates whether inputs are to be processed early in the lifecycle. If true, behavior events generated from this behavior are broadcast during the Apply Request Values phase. Otherwise, the events will be broadcast during the Invoke Application phase.

listener

|

javax.el.MethodExpression

|

The name of the listener method that is called when a javax.faces.event.AjaxBehaviorEvent has been broadcast for the listener.

onevent

|

javax.el.ValueExpression that evaluates to a String

|

The name of the JavaScript function that handles UI events.

onerror

|

javax.el.ValueExpression that evaluates to a String

|

The name of the JavaScript function that handles errors.

render

|

javax.el.ValueExpression that evaluates to an Object

|

A Collection that identifies a list of components to be rendered on the client. If a literal is specified, it must be a space-delimited String of component identifiers and/or one of the keywords. If a ValueExpression is specified, it must refer to a property that returns a Collection of String objects. If not specified, the default value is @none.

The keywords listed in Table 13-2 can be used with the execute and render attributes of the f:ajax tag.

Table 13-2 Execute and Render Keywords

Keyword | Description

@all

|

All component identifiers

@form

|

The form that encloses the component

@none

|

No component identifiers

@this

|

The element that triggered the request

Note that when you use the f:ajax tag in a Facelets page, the JavaScript resource library is loaded implicitly. This resource library can also be loaded explicitly as described in Loading JavaScript as a Resource.

13.4 Sending an Ajax Request

To activate Ajax functionality, the web application must create an Ajax request and send it to the server. The server then processes the request.

The application uses the attributes of the f:ajax tag listed in Table 13-1 to create the Ajax request. The following sections explain the process of creating and sending an Ajax request using some of these attributes.

Note:

Behind the scenes, the jsf.ajax.request() method of the JavaScript resource library collects the data provided by the f:ajax tag and posts the request to the JavaServer Faces lifecycle.

13.4.1 Using the event Attribute

The event attribute defines the event that triggers the Ajax action. Some of the possible values for this attribute are click, keyup, mouseover, focus, and blur.

If not specified, a default event based on the parent component will be applied. The default event is action for javax.faces.component.ActionSource components, such as a commandButton, and valueChange for javax.faces.component.EditableValueHolder components, such as inputText. In the following example, an Ajax tag is associated with the button component, and the event that triggers the Ajax action is a mouse click:

<h:commandButton id="submit" value="Submit"> 
    <f:ajax event="click" />
</h:commandButton>
<h:outputText id="result" value="#{userNumberBean.response}" />

Note:

You may have noticed that the listed events are very similar to JavaScript events. In fact, they are based on JavaScript events, but do not have the on prefix.

For a command button, the default event is click, so you do not actually need to specify event="click" to obtain the desired behavior.

13.4.2 Using the execute Attribute

The execute attribute defines the component or components to be executed on the server. The component is identified by its id attribute. You can specify more than one executable component. If more than one component is to be executed, specify a space-delimited list of components.

When a component is executed, it participates in all phases of the request-processing lifecycle except the Render Response phase.

The execute attribute value can also be a keyword, such as @all, @none, @this, or @form. The default value is @this, which refers to the component within which the f:ajax tag is nested.

The following code specifies that the h:inputText component with the id value of userNo should be executed when the button is clicked:

<h:inputText id="userNo" 
             title="Type a number from 0 to 10:"
             value="#{userNumberBean.userNumber}">
    ...
</h:inputText>
<h:commandButton id="submit" value="Submit"> 
    <f:ajax event="click" execute="userNo" />
</h:commandButton>

13.4.3 Using the immediate Attribute

The immediate attribute indicates whether user inputs are to be processed early in the application lifecycle or later. If the attribute is set to true, events generated from this component are broadcast during the Apply Request Values phase. Otherwise, the events will be broadcast during the Invoke Application phase.

If not defined, the default value of this attribute is false.

13.4.4 Using the listener Attribute

The listener attribute refers to a method expression that is executed on the server side in response to an Ajax action on the client. The listener's javax.faces.event.AjaxBehaviorListener.processAjaxBehavior method is called once during the Invoke Application phase of the lifecycle. In the following code from the reservation example application (see The reservation Example Application), a listener attribute is defined by an f:ajax tag, which refers to a method from the bean:

<f:ajax event="change" render="total" 
        listener="#{reservationBean.calculateTotal}"/>

Whenever either the price or the number of tickets ordered changes, the calculateTotal method of ReservationBean recalculates the total cost of the tickets and displays it in the output component named total.

13.5 Monitoring Events on the Client

To monitor ongoing Ajax requests, use the onevent attribute of the f:ajax tag. The value of this attribute is the name of a JavaScript function. JavaServer Faces calls the onevent function at each stage of the processing of an Ajax request: begin, complete, and success.

When calling the JavaScript function assigned to the onevent property, JavaServer Faces passes a data object to it. The data object contains the properties listed in Table 13-3.

Table 13-3 Properties of the onevent Data Object

Property | Description

responseXML

|

The response to the Ajax call in XML format

responseText

|

The response to the Ajax call in text format

responseCode

|

The response to the Ajax call in numeric code

source

|

The source of the current Ajax event: the DOM element

status

|

The status of the current Ajax call: begin, complete, or success

type

|

The type of the Ajax call: event

By using the status property of the data object, you can identify the current status of the Ajax request and monitor its progress. In the following example, monitormyajaxevent is a JavaScript function that monitors the Ajax request sent by the event:

<f:ajax event="click" render="statusmessage" onevent="monitormyajaxevent"/>

13.6 Handling Errors

JavaServer Faces handles Ajax errors through use of the onerror attribute of the f:ajax tag. The value of this attribute is the name of a JavaScript function.

When there is an error in processing a Ajax request, JavaServer Faces calls the defined onerror JavaScript function and passes a data object to it. The data object contains all the properties available for the onevent attribute and, in addition, the following properties:

description

errorName

errorMessage

The type is error. The status property of the data object contains one of the valid error values listed in Table 13-4.

Table 13-4 Valid Error Values for the Data Object status Property

Values | Description

emptyResponse

|

No Ajax response from server.

httpError

|

One of the valid HTTP errors: request.status==null or request.status==undefined or request.status<200 or request.status>=300.

malformedXML

|

The Ajax response is not well formed.

serverError

|

The Ajax response contains an error element.

In the following example, any errors that occurred in processing the Ajax request are handled by the handlemyajaxerror JavaScript function:

<f:ajax event="click" render="errormessage" onerror="handlemyajaxerror"/>

13.7 Receiving an Ajax Response

After the application sends an Ajax request, it is processed on the server side, and a response is sent back to the client. As described earlier, Ajax allows for partial updating of web pages. To enable such partial updating, JavaServer Faces technology allows for partial processing of the view. The handling of the response is defined by the render attribute of the f:ajax tag.

Similar to the execute attribute, the render attribute defines which sections of the page will be updated. The value of a render attribute can be one or more component id values, one of the keywords @this, @all, @none, or @form, or an EL expression. In the following example, the render attribute identifies an output component to be displayed when the button component is clicked (the default event for a command button):

<h:commandButton id="submit" value="Submit"> 
    <f:ajax execute="userNo" render="result" />
</h:commandButton>
<h:outputText id="result" value="#{userNumberBean.response}" />

Note:

Behind the scenes, once again the jsf.ajax.request() method handles the response. It registers a response-handling callback when the original request is created. When the response is sent back to the client, the callback is invoked. This callback automatically updates the client-side DOM to reflect the rendered response.

13.8 Ajax Request Lifecycle

An Ajax request varies from other typical JavaServer Faces requests, and its processing is also handled differently by the JavaServer Faces lifecycle.

As described in Partial Processing and Partial Rendering, when an Ajax request is received, the state associated with that request is captured by the javax.faces.context.PartialViewContext. This object provides access to information such as which components are targeted for processing/rendering. The processPartial method of PartialViewContext uses this information to perform partial component tree processing and rendering.

The execute attribute of the f:ajax tag identifies which segments of the server-side component tree should be processed. Because components can be uniquely identified in the JavaServer Faces component tree, it is easy to identify and process a single component, a few components, or a whole tree. This is made possible by the visitTree method of the UIComponent class. The identified components then run through the JavaServer Faces request lifecycle phases.

Similar to the execute attribute, the render attribute identifies which segments of the JavaServer Faces component tree need to be rendered during the render response phase.

During the render response phase, the render attribute is examined. The identified components are found and asked to render themselves and their children. The components are then packaged up and sent back to the client as a response.

13.9 Grouping of Components

The previous sections describe how to associate a single UI component with Ajax functionality. You can also associate Ajax with more than one component at a time by grouping them together on a page. The following example shows how a number of components can be grouped by using the f:ajax tag:

<f:ajax>
    <h:form>
        <h:inputText id="input1" value="#{user.name}"/> 
        <h:commandButton id="Submit"/>
    </h:form>
</f:ajax>

In the example, neither component is associated with any Ajax event or render attributes yet. Therefore, no action will take place in case of user input. You can associate the above components with an event and a render attribute as follows:

<f:ajax event="click" render="@all">
    <h:form>
        <h:inputText id="input1" value="#{user.name}"/> 
        <h:commandButton id="Submit"/> 
    </h:form>
</f:ajax>

In the updated example, when the user clicks either component, the updated results will be displayed for all components. You can further fine-tune the Ajax action by adding specific events to each of the components, in which case Ajax functionality becomes cumulative. Consider the following example:

<f:ajax event="click" render="@all">
    ...
    <h:commandButton id="Submit">
        <f:ajax event="mouseover"/>
    </h:commandButton>
    ...
</f:ajax>

Now the button component will fire an Ajax action in case of a mouseover event as well as a mouse-click event.

13.10 Loading JavaScript as a Resource

The JavaScript resource file bundled with JavaServer Faces technology is named jsf.js and is available in the javax.faces library. This resource library supports Ajax functionality in JavaServer Faces applications.

If you use the f:ajax tag on a page, the jsf.js resource is automatically delivered to the client. It is not necessary to use the h:outputScript tag to specify this resource. You may want to use the h:outputScript tag to specify other JavaScript libraries.

In order to use a JavaScript resource directly with a UIComponent, you must explicitly load the resource in either of the following ways:

By using the h:outputScript tag directly in a Facelets page

By using the javax.faces.application.ResourceDependency annotation on a UIComponent Java class

13.10.1 Using JavaScript API in a Facelets Application

To use the bundled JavaScript resource API directly in a web application, such as a Facelets page, you need to first identify the default JavaScript resource for the page with the help of the h:outputScript tag. For example, consider the following section of a Facelets page:

<h:form>
    <h:outputScript name="jsf.js" library="javax.faces" target="head"/>
</h:form>

Specifying the target as head causes the script resource to be rendered within the head element on the HTML page.

In the next step, identify the component to which you would like to attach the Ajax functionality. Add the Ajax functionality to the component by using the JavaScript API. For example, consider the following:

<h:form>
    <h:outputScript name="jsf.js" library="javax.faces" target="head">
    <h:inputText id="inputname" value="#{userBean.name}"/>
    <h:outputText id="outputname" value="#{userBean.name}"/>
    <h:commandButton id="submit" value="Submit"
                     onclick="jsf.ajax.request(this, event, 
                              {execute:'inputname',render:'outputname'});
                              return false;" />
</h:form>

The jsf.ajax.request method takes up to three parameters that specify source, event, and options. The source parameter identifies the DOM element that triggered the Ajax request, typically this. The optional event parameter identifies the DOM event that triggered this request. The optional options parameter contains a set of name/value pairs from Table 13-5.

Table 13-5 Possible Values for the Options Parameter

Name | Value

execute

|

A space-delimited list of client identifiers or one of the keywords listed in Table 13-2. The identifiers reference the components that will be processed during the Execute phase of the lifecycle.

render

|

A space-delimited list of client identifiers or one of the keywords listed in Table 13-2. The identifiers reference the components that will be processed during the render phase of the lifecycle.

onevent

|

A String that is the name of the JavaScript function to call when an event occurs.

onerror

|

A String that is the name of the JavaScript function to call when an error occurs.

params

|

An object that may include additional parameters to include in the request.

If no identifier is specified, the default assumed keyword for the execute attribute is @this, and for the render attribute it is @none.

You can also place the JavaScript method in a file and include it as a resource.

13.10.2 Using the @ResourceDependency Annotation in a Bean Class

Use the javax.faces.application.ResourceDependency annotation to cause the bean class to load the default jsf.js library.

To load the Ajax resource from the server side, use the jsf.ajax.request method within the bean class. This method is usually used when creating a custom component or a custom renderer for a component.

The following example shows how the resource is loaded in a bean class:

@ResourceDependency(name="jsf.js" library="javax.faces" target="head")

13.11 The ajaxguessnumber Example Application

To demonstrate the advantages of using Ajax, revisit the guessnumber example from Chapter 8, "Introduction to Facelets". If you modify this example to use Ajax, the response need not be displayed on the response.xhtml page. Instead, an asynchronous call is made to the bean on the server side, and the response is displayed on the originating page by executing just the input component rather than by form submission.

The source code for this application is in the tut-install/examples/web/jsf/ajaxguessnumber/ directory.

13.11.1 The ajaxguessnumber Source Files

The changes to the guessnumber application occur in two source files.

13.11.1.1 The ajaxgreeting.xhtml Facelets Page

The Facelets page for ajaxguessnumber, ajaxgreeting.xhtml, is almost the same as the greeting.xhtml page for the guessnumber application:

<h:head>
    <h:outputStylesheet library="css" name="default.css"/>
    <title>Ajax Guess Number Facelets Application</title>
</h:head>
<h:body>
    <h:form id="AjaxGuess">
        <h:graphicImage value="#{resource['images:wave.med.gif']}"
                        alt="Duke waving his hand"/>
        <h2>
            Hi, my name is Duke. I am thinking of a number from
            #{dukesNumberBean.minimum} to #{dukesNumberBean.maximum}.
            Can you guess it?
        </h2>
        <p>
            <h:inputText id="userNo" 
                         title="Enter a number from 0 to 10:"
                         value="#{userNumberBean.userNumber}">
                <f:validateLongRange minimum="#{dukesNumberBean.minimum}"
                                     maximum="#{dukesNumberBean.maximum}"/>
            </h:inputText>

            <h:commandButton id="submit" value="Submit">
                <f:ajax execute="userNo" render="outputGroup" />
            </h:commandButton>
        </p>
        <p>
            <h:panelGroup layout="block" id="outputGroup">
                <h:outputText id="result" style="color:blue"
                              value="#{userNumberBean.response}"
                              rendered="#{!facesContext.validationFailed}"/>
                <h:message id="errors1" 
                           showSummary="true" 
                           showDetail="false"
                           style="color: #d20005;
                           font-family: 'New Century Schoolbook', serif;
                           font-style: oblique;
                           text-decoration: overline" 
                           for="userNo"/>
            </h:panelGroup>
        </p>
    </h:form>
</h:body>

The most important change is in the h:commandButton tag. The action attribute is removed from the tag, and an f:ajax tag is added.

The f:ajax tag specifies that when the button is clicked the h:inputText component with the id value userNo is executed. The components within the outputGroup panel group are then rendered. If a validation error occurs, the managed bean is not executed, and the validation error message is displayed in the message pane. Otherwise, the result of the guess is rendered in the result component.

13.11.1.2 The UserNumberBean Backing Bean

A small change is also made in the UserNumberBean code so that the output component does not display any message for the default (null) value of the property response. Here is the modified bean code:

public String getResponse() {
    if ((userNumber != null)
            && (userNumber.compareTo(dukesNumberBean.getRandomInt()) == 0)) {
        return "Yay! You got it!";
    }
    if (userNumber == null) {
        return null;
    } else {
        return "Sorry, " + userNumber + " is incorrect.";
    }
}

13.11.1.3 The DukesNumberBean CDI Managed Bean

The DukesNumberBean session-scoped CDI managed bean stores the range of guessable numbers and the randomly chosen number from that range. It is injected into UserNumberBean with the CDI @Inject annotation so that the value of the random number can be compared to the number the user submitted:

@Inject
DukesNumberBean dukesNumberBean;

You will learn more about CDI in Chapter 23, "Introduction to Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE".

13.11.2 Running the ajaxguessnumber Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the ajaxguessnumber application.

13.11.2.1 To Build, Package, and Deploy the ajaxguessnumber Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf

Select the ajaxguessnumber folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the ajaxguessnumber project and select Build.

This command builds and deploys the project.

13.11.2.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the ajaxguessnumber Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf/ajaxguessnumber/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, ajaxguessnumber.war, located in the target directory. It then deploys the application.

13.11.2.3 To Run the ajaxguessnumber Example

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/ajaxguessnumber

Enter a value in the field and click Submit.

If the value is in the range of 0 to 10, a message states whether the guess is correct or incorrect. If the value is outside that range or if the value is not a number, an error message appears in red.

13.12 Further Information about Ajax in JavaServer Faces Technology

For more information on Ajax in JavaServer Faces Technology, see

JavaServer Faces project website:

https://javaserverfaces.java.net/

JavaServer Faces JavaScript Library APIs:

http://docs.oracle.com/javaee/7/javaserverfaces/2.2/jsdocs/symbols/jsf.ajax.html

16 Configuring JavaServer Faces Applications

The process of building and deploying simple JavaServer Faces applications is described in earlier chapters of this tutorial, including Chapter 6, "Getting Started with Web Applications," Chapter 8, "Introduction to Facelets," Chapter 13, "Using Ajax with JavaServer Faces Technology," and Chapter 14, "Composite Components: Advanced Topics and an Example." When you create large and complex applications, however, various additional configuration tasks are required. These tasks include the following:

Registering managed beans with the application so that all parts of the application have access to them

Configuring managed beans and model beans so that they are instantiated with the proper values when a page makes reference to them

Defining navigation rules for each of the pages in the application so that the application has a smooth page flow, if nondefault navigation is needed

Packaging the application to include all the pages, resources, and other files so that the application can be deployed on any compliant container

The following topics are addressed here:

Using Annotations to Configure Managed Beans

Application Configuration Resource File

Using Faces Flows

Configuring Managed Beans

Registering Application Messages

Using Default Validators

Registering a Custom Validator

Registering a Custom Converter

Configuring Navigation Rules

Registering a Custom Renderer with a Render Kit

Registering a Custom Component

Basic Requirements of a JavaServer Faces Application

16.1 Using Annotations to Configure Managed Beans

JavaServer Faces support for bean annotations is introduced in Chapter 7, "JavaServer Faces Technology". Bean annotations can be used for configuring JavaServer Faces applications.

The @Named (javax.inject.Named) annotation in a class, along with a scope annotation, automatically registers that class as a resource with the JavaServer Faces implementation. A bean that uses these annotations is a CDI managed bean.

The following shows the use of the @Named and @SessionScoped annotations in a class:

@Named("cart")
@SessionScoped
public class ShoppingCart ... { ... }

The above code snippet shows a bean that is managed by the JavaServer Faces implementation and is available for the length of the session.

You can annotate beans with any of the scopes listed in the next section, Using Managed Bean Scopes.

All classes will be scanned for annotations at startup unless the faces-config element in the faces-config.xml file has the metadata-complete attribute set to true.

Annotations are also available for other artifacts, such as components, converters, validators, and renderers, to be used in place of application configuration resource file entries. These are discussed, along with registration of custom listeners, custom validators, and custom converters, in Chapter 15, "Creating Custom UI Components and Other Custom Objects".

16.1.1 Using Managed Bean Scopes

You can use annotations to define the scope in which the bean will be stored. You can specify one of the following scopes for a bean class.

Application (javax.enterprise.context.ApplicationScoped): Application scope persists across all users' interactions with a web application.

Session (javax.enterprise.context.SessionScoped): Session scope persists across multiple HTTP requests in a web application.

Flow (javax.faces.flows.FlowScoped): Flow scope persists during a user's interaction with a specific flow of a web application. See Using Faces Flows for more information.

Request (javax.enterprise.context.RequestScoped): Request scope persists during a single HTTP request in a web application.

Dependent (javax.enterprise.context.Dependent): Indicates that the bean depends on some other bean.

You may want to use @Dependent when a managed bean references another managed bean. The second bean should not be in a scope (@Dependent) if it is supposed to be created only when it is referenced. If you define a bean as @Dependent, the bean is instantiated anew each time it is referenced, so it does not get saved in any scope.

If your managed bean is referenced by the binding attribute of a component tag, you should define the bean with a request scope. If you placed the bean in session or application scope instead, the bean would need to take precautions to ensure thread safety, because javax.faces.component.UIComponent instances each depend on running inside of a single thread.

If you are configuring a bean that allows attributes to be associated with the view, you can use the view scope. The attributes persist until the user has navigated to the next view.

16.2 Application Configuration Resource File

JavaServer Faces technology provides a portable configuration format (as an XML document) for configuring application resources. One or more XML documents, called application configuration resource files, may use this format to register and configure objects and resources and to define navigation rules for applications. An application configuration resource file is usually named faces-config.xml.

You need an application configuration resource file in the following cases:

To specify configuration elements for your application that are not available through managed bean annotations, such as localized messages and navigation rules

To override managed bean annotations when the application is deployed

The application configuration resource file must be valid against the XML schema located at http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee/web-facesconfig_2_2.xsd.

In addition, each file must include the following information, in the following order:

The XML version number, usually with an encoding attribute:

<?xml version="1.0" encoding='UTF-8'?>

A faces-config tag enclosing all the other declarations:

<faces-config version="2.2" xmlns="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee" 
              xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
              xsi:schemaLocation="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee 
              http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee/web-facesconfig_2_2.xsd"> 
    ...
</faces-config>

You can have more than one application configuration resource file for an application. The JavaServer Faces implementation finds the configuration file or files by looking for the following.

A resource named /META-INF/faces-config.xml in any of the JAR files in the web application's /WEB-INF/lib/ directory and in parent class loaders. If a resource with this name exists, it is loaded as a configuration resource. This method is practical for a packaged library containing some components and renderers. In addition, any file with a name that ends in faces-config.xml is also considered a configuration resource and is loaded as such.

A context initialization parameter, javax.faces.application.CONFIG_FILES, in your web deployment descriptor file that specifies one or more (comma-delimited) paths to multiple configuration files for your web application. This method is most often used for enterprise-scale applications that delegate to separate groups the responsibility for maintaining the file for each portion of a big application.

A resource named faces-config.xml in the /WEB-INF/ directory of your application. Simple web applications make their configuration files available in this way.

To access the resources registered with the application, an application developer can use an instance of the javax.faces.application.Application class, which is automatically created for each application. The Application instance acts as a centralized factory for resources that are defined in the XML file.

When an application starts up, the JavaServer Faces implementation creates a single instance of the Application class and configures it with the information you provided in the application configuration resource file.

16.2.1 Configuring Eager Application-Scoped Managed Beans

JavaServer Faces managed beans (either specified in the faces-config.xml file or annotated with javax.faces.bean.ManagedBean) are lazily instantiated. That is, that they are instantiated when a request is made from the application.

To force an application-scoped bean to be instantiated and placed in the application scope as soon as the application is started and before any request is made, the eager attribute of the managed bean should be set to true, as shown in the following examples.

The faces-config.xml file declaration is as follows:

<managed-bean eager="true">

The annotation is as follows:

@ManagedBean(eager=true)
@ApplicationScoped

16.2.2 Ordering of Application Configuration Resource Files

Because JavaServer Faces technology allows the use of multiple application configuration resource files stored in different locations, the order in which they are loaded by the implementation becomes important in certain situations (for example, when using application-level objects). This order can be defined through an ordering element and its subelements in the application configuration resource file itself. The ordering of application configuration resource files can be absolute or relative.

Absolute ordering is defined by an absolute-ordering element in the file. With absolute ordering, the user specifies the order in which application configuration resource files will be loaded. The following example shows an entry for absolute ordering.

File my-faces-config.xml contains the following elements:

<faces-config>
    <name>myJSF</name>
    <absolute-ordering>
        <name>A</name>
        <name>B</name>
        <name>C</name>
    </absolute-ordering>
</faces-config>

In this example, A, B, and C are different application configuration resource files and are to be loaded in the listed order.

If there is an absolute-ordering element in the file, only the files listed by the subelement name are processed. To process any other application configuration resource files, an others subelement is required. In the absence of the others subelement, all other unlisted files will be ignored at load time.

Relative ordering is defined by an ordering element and its subelements before and after. With relative ordering, the order in which application configuration resource files will be loaded is calculated by considering ordering entries from the different files. The following example shows some of these considerations. In the following example, config-A, config-B, and config-C are different application configuration resource files.

File config-A contains the following elements:

<faces-config>
    <name>config-A</name>
    <ordering>
        <before>
            <name>config-B</name>
        </before>
    </ordering>
</faces-config>

File config-B (not shown here) does not contain any ordering elements.

File config-C contains the following elements:

<faces-config>
    <name>config-C</name>
    <ordering>
        <after>
            <name>config-B</name>
        </after>
    </ordering>
</faces-config>

Based on the before subelement entry, file config-A will be loaded before the config-B file. Based on the after subelement entry, file config-C will be loaded after the config-B file.

In addition, a subelement others can also be nested within the before and after subelements. If the others element is present, the specified file may receive highest or lowest preference among both listed and unlisted configuration files.

If an ordering element is not present in an application configuration file, then that file will be loaded after all the files that contain ordering elements.

16.3 Using Faces Flows

The Faces Flows feature of JavaServer Faces technology allows you to create a set of pages with a scope, FlowScoped, that is greater than request scope but less than session scope. For example, you might want to create a series of pages for the checkout process in an online store. You could create a set of self-contained pages that could be transferred from one store to another as needed.

Faces Flows are somewhat analogous to subroutines in procedural programming, in the following ways.

Like a subroutine, a flow has a well defined entry point, list of parameters, and return value. However, unlike a subroutine, a flow can return multiple values.

Like a subroutine, a flow has a scope, allowing information to be available only during the invocation of the flow. Such information is not available outside the scope of the flow and does not consume any resources once the flow returns.

Like a subroutine, a flow may call other flows before returning. The invocation of flows is maintained in a call stack: a new flow causes a push onto the stack, and a return causes a pop.

An application can have any number of flows. Each flow includes a set of pages and, usually, one or more managed beans scoped to that flow. Each flow has a starting point, called a start node, and an exit point, called a return node.

The data in a flow is scoped to that flow alone, but you can pass data from one flow to another by specifying parameters and calling the other flow.

Flows can be nested, so that if you call one flow from another and then exit the second flow, you return to the calling flow rather than to the second flow's return node.

You can configure a flow programmatically, by creating a class annotated @FlowDefinition, or you can configure a flow by using a configuration file. The configuration file can be limited to one flow, or you can use the faces-config.xml file to put all the flows in one place, if you have many flows in an application. The programmatic configuration places the code closer to the rest of the flow code and enables you to modularize the flows.

Figure 16-1 shows two flows and illustrates how they interact.

Figure 16-1 Two Faces Flows and Their Interactions

Description of "Figure 16-1 Two Faces Flows and Their Interactions"

In this figure, Flow A has a start node named flow-a and two additional pages, next_a1 and next_a2. From next_a2, a user can either exit the flow using the defined return node, taskFlowReturn1, or call Flow B, passing two parameters. Flow A also defines two inbound parameters that it can accept from Flow B. Flow B is identical to Flow A except for the names of the flow and files. Each flow also has an associated managed bean; the beans are Flow_a_Bean and Flow_b_Bean.

16.3.1 Packaging Flows in an Application

Typically, you package flows in a web application using a directory structure that modularizes the flows. In the src/main/webapp directory of a Maven project, for example, you would place the Facelets files that are outside the flow at the top level as usual. Then the webapp files for each flow would be in a separate directory, and the Java files would be under src/main/java. For example, the files for the application shown in Figure 16-1 might look like this:

src/main/webapp/
    index.xhtml
    return.xhtml
    WEB_INF/
        beans.xml
        web.xml
    flow-a/
        flow-a.xhtml
        next_a1.xhtml
        next_a2.xhtml
    flow-b/
        flow-b-flow.xml
        next_b1.xhtml
        next_b2.xhtml
src/main/java/javaeetutorial/flowexample
            FlowA.java
            Flow_a_Bean.java
            Flow_b_Bean.java

In this example, flow-a is defined programmatically in FlowA.java, while flow-b is defined by the configuration file flow-b-flow.xml.

16.3.2 The Simplest Possible Flow: The simple-flow Example Application

The simple-flow example application demonstrates the most basic building blocks of a Faces Flows application and illustrates some of the conventions that make it easy to get started with iterative development using flows. You may want to start with a simple example like this one and build upon it.

This example provides an implicit flow definition by including an empty configuration file. A configuration file that has content, or a class annotated @FlowDefinition, provides an explicit flow definition.

The source code for this application is in the tut-install/examples/web/jsf/simple-flow/ directory.

The file layout of the simple-flow example looks like this:

src/main/webapp
    index.xhtml
    simple-flow-return.xhtml
    WEB_INF/
        web.xml
    simple-flow
        simple-flow-flow.xml
        simple-flow.xhtml
        simple-flow-page2.xhtml

The simple-flow example has an empty configuration file, which is by convention named flow-name-flow.xml. The flow does not require any configuration for the following reasons.

The flow does not call another flow, nor does it pass parameters to another flow.

The flow uses default names for the first page of the flow, flow-name.xhtml, and the return page, flow-name-return.xhtml.

This example has only four Facelets pages.

index.xhtml, the start page, which contains almost nothing but a button that navigates to the first page of the flow:

<p><h:commandButton value="Enter Flow" action="simple-flow"/></p>

simple-flow.xhtml and simple-flow-page2.xhtml, the two pages of the flow itself. In the absence of an explicit flow definition, the page whose name is the same as the name of the flow is assumed to be the start node of the flow. In this case, the flow is named simple-flow, so the page named simple-flow.xhtml is assumed to be the start node of the flow. The start node is the node navigated to upon entry into the flow. It can be thought of as the home page of the flow.

The simple-flow.xhtml page asks you to enter a flow-scoped value and provides a button that navigates to the next page of the flow:

<p>Value: <h:inputText id="input" value="#{flowScope.value}" /></p>

<p><h:commandButton value="Next" action="simple-flow-page2" /></p>

The second page, which can have any name, displays the flow-scoped value and provides a button that navigates to the return page:

<p>Value: #{flowScope.value}</p>

<p><h:commandButton value="Return" action="simple-flow-return" /></p>

simple-flow-return.xhtml, the return page. The return page, which by convention is named flow-name-return.xhtml, must be located outside of the flow. This page displays the flow-scoped value, to show that it has no value outside of the flow, and provides a link that navigates to the index.xhtml page:

<p>Value (should be empty): 
    "<h:outputText id="output" value="#{flowScope.value}" />"</p>

<p><h:link outcome="index" value="Back to Start" /></p>

The Facelets pages use only flow-scoped data, so the example does not need a managed bean.

16.3.2.1 To Build, Package, and Deploy the simple-flow Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf

Select the simple-flow folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the simple-flow project and select Build.

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, simple-flow.war, that is located in the target directory. It then deploys the application to the server.

16.3.2.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the simple-flow Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf/simple-flow/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, simple-flow.war, that is located in the target directory. It then deploys the application to the server.

16.3.2.3 To Run the simple-flow Example

Enter the following URL in your web browser:

http://localhost:8080/simple-flow

On the index.xhtml page, click Enter Flow.

On the first page of the flow, enter any string in the Value field, then click Next.

On the second page of the flow, you can see the value you entered. Click Return.

On the return page, an empty pair of quotation marks encloses the inaccessible value. Click Back to Start to return to the index.xhtml page.

16.3.3 The checkout-module Example Application

The checkout-module example application is considerably more complex than simple-flow. It shows how you might use the Faces Flows feature to implement a checkout module for an online store.

Like the hypothetical example in Figure 16-1, the example application contains two flows, each of which can call the other. Both flows have explicit flow definitions. One flow, checkoutFlow, is specified programmatically. The other flow, joinFlow, is specified in a configuration file.

The source code for this application is in the tut-install/examples/web/jsf/checkout-module/ directory.

For the checkout-module application, the directory structure is as follows (there is also a src/main/webapp/resources directory with a stylesheet and an image):

src/main/webapp/
    index.xhtml
    exithome.xhtml
    WEB_INF/
        beans.xml
        web.xml
    checkoutFlow/
        checkoutFlow.xhtml
        checkoutFlow2.xhtml
        checkoutFlow3.xhtml
        checkoutFlow4.xhtml
    joinFlow/
        joinFlow-flow.xml
        joinFlow.xhtml
        joinFlow2.xhtml
src/main/java/javaeetutorial/checkoutmodule
            CheckoutBean.java
            CheckoutFlow.java
            CheckoutFlowBean.java
            JoinFlowBean.java

For the example, index.xhtml is the beginning page for the application as well as the return node for the checkout flow. The exithome.xhtml page is the return node for the join flow.

The configuration file joinFlow-flow.xml defines the join flow, and the source file CheckoutFlow.java defines the checkout flow.

The checkout flow contains four Facelets pages, whereas the join flow contains two.

The managed beans scoped to each flow are CheckoutFlowBean.java and JoinFlowBean.java, whereas CheckoutBean.java is the backing bean for the index.html page.

16.3.3.1 The Facelets Pages for the checkout-module Example

The starting page for the example, index.xhtml, summarizes the contents of a hypothetical shopping cart. It allows the user to click either of two buttons to enter one of the two flows:

<p><h:commandButton value="Check Out" action="checkoutFlow"/></p>
...
<p><h:commandButton value="Join" action="joinFlow"/></p>

This page is also the return node for the checkout flow.

The Facelets page exithome.xhtml is the return node for the join flow. This page has a button that allows you to return to the index.xhtml page.

The four Facelets pages within the checkout flow, starting with checkoutFlow.xhtml and ending with checkoutFlow4.xhtml, allow you to proceed to the next page or, in some cases, to return from the flow. The checkoutFlow.xhtml page allows you to access parameters passed from the join flow through the flow scope. These appear as empty quotation marks if you have not called the checkout flow from the join flow.

<p>If you called this flow from the Join flow, you can see these parameters:
    "<h:outputText value="#{flowScope.param1Value}"/>" and
    "<h:outputText value="#{flowScope.param2Value}"/>"
</p>

Only checkoutFlow2.xhtml has a button to return to the previous page, but moving between pages is generally permitted within flows. Here are the buttons for checkoutFlow2.xhtml:

<p><h:commandButton value="Continue" action="checkoutFlow3"/></p>
<p><h:commandButton value="Go Back" action="checkoutFlow"/></p>
<p><h:commandButton value="Exit Flow" action="returnFromCheckoutFlow"/></p>

The action returnFromCheckoutFlow is defined in the configuration source code file, CheckoutFlow.java.

The final page of the checkout flow, checkoutFlow4.xhtml, contains a button that calls the join flow:

<p><h:commandButton value="Join" action="calljoin"/></p>
<p><h:commandButton value="Exit Flow" action="returnFromCheckoutFlow"/></p>

The calljoin action is also defined in the configuration source code file, CheckoutFlow.java. This action enters the join flow, passing two parameters from the checkout flow.

The two pages in the join flow, joinFlow.xhtml and joinFlow2.xhtml, are similar to those in the checkout flow. The second page has a button to call the checkout flow as well as one to return from the join flow:

<p><h:commandButton value="Check Out" action="callcheckoutFlow"/></p>
<p><h:commandButton value="Exit Flow" action="returnFromJoinFlow"/></p>

For this flow, the actions callcheckoutFlow and returnFromJoinFlow are defined in the configuration file joinFlow-flow.xml.

16.3.3.2 Using a Configuration File to Configure a Flow

If you use an application configuration resource file to configure a flow, it must be named flowName-flow.xml. In this example, the join flow uses a configuration file named joinFlow-flow.xml. The file is a faces-config file that specifies a flow-definition element. This element must define the flow name using the id attribute. Under the flow-definition element, there must be a flow-return element that specifies the return point for the flow. Any inbound parameters are specified with inbound-parameter elements. If the flow calls another flow, the call-flow element must use the flow-reference element to name the called flow and may use the outbound-parameter element to specify any outbound parameters.

The configuration file for the join flow looks like this:

<faces-config version="2.2" xmlns="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee"
              xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
              xsi:schemaLocation="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee \
              http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee/web-facesconfig_2_2.xsd">
 
    <flow-definition id="joinFlow">
        <flow-return id="returnFromJoinFlow">
            <from-outcome>#{joinFlowBean.returnValue}</from-outcome>
        </flow-return>
 
        <inbound-parameter>
            <name>param1FromCheckoutFlow</name>
            <value>#{flowScope.param1Value}</value>
        </inbound-parameter>
        <inbound-parameter>
            <name>param2FromCheckoutFlow</name>
            <value>#{flowScope.param2Value}</value>
        </inbound-parameter>
        
        <flow-call id="callcheckoutFlow">
            <flow-reference>
                <flow-id>checkoutFlow</flow-id>
            </flow-reference>
            <outbound-parameter>
                <name>param1FromJoinFlow</name>
                <value>param1 joinFlow value</value>
            </outbound-parameter>
            <outbound-parameter>
                <name>param2FromJoinFlow</name>
                <value>param2 joinFlow value</value>
            </outbound-parameter>
        </flow-call>
    </flow-definition>
</faces-config>

The id attribute of the flow-definition element defines the name of the flow as joinFlow. The value of the id attribute of the flow-return element identifies the name of the return node, and its value is defined in the from-outcome element as the returnValue property of the flow-scoped managed bean for the join flow, JoinFlowBean.

The names and values of the inbound parameters are retrieved from the flow scope in order (flowScope.param1Value, flowScope.param2Value), based on the way they were defined in the checkout flow configuration.

The flow-call element defines how the join flow calls the checkout flow. The id attribute of the element, callcheckoutFlow, defines the action of calling the flow. Within the flow-call element, the flow-reference element defines the actual name of the flow to call, checkoutFlow. The outbound-parameter elements define the parameters to be passed when checkoutFlow is called. Here they are just arbitrary strings.

16.3.3.3 Using a Java Class to Configure a Flow

If you use a Java class to configure a flow, it must have the name of the flow. The class for the checkout flow is called CheckoutFlow.java.

import java.io.Serializable;
import javax.enterprise.inject.Produces;
import javax.faces.flow.Flow;
import javax.faces.flow.builder.FlowBuilder;
import javax.faces.flow.builder.FlowBuilderParameter;
import javax.faces.flow.builder.FlowDefinition;

class CheckoutFlow implements Serializable {
 
    private static final long serialVersionUID = 1L;
 
    @Produces
    @FlowDefinition
    public Flow defineFlow(@FlowBuilderParameter FlowBuilder flowBuilder) {
 
        String flowId = "checkoutFlow";
        flowBuilder.id("", flowId);
        flowBuilder.viewNode(flowId, 
                "/" + flowId + "/" + flowId + ".xhtml").
                markAsStartNode();
 
        flowBuilder.returnNode("returnFromCheckoutFlow").
                fromOutcome("#{checkoutFlowBean.returnValue}");
 
        flowBuilder.inboundParameter("param1FromJoinFlow", 
                "#{flowScope.param1Value}");
        flowBuilder.inboundParameter("param2FromJoinFlow", 
                "#{flowScope.param2Value}");
 
        flowBuilder.flowCallNode("calljoin").flowReference("", "joinFlow").
                outboundParameter("param1FromCheckoutFlow", 
                    "#{checkoutFlowBean.name}").
                outboundParameter("param2FromCheckoutFlow", 
                    "#{checkoutFlowBean.city}");
        return flowBuilder.getFlow();
    }
}

The class performs actions that are almost identical to those performed by the configuration file joinFlow-flow.xml. It contains a single method, defineFlow, as a producer method with the @FlowDefinition qualifier that returns a javax.faces.flow.Flow class. The defineFlow method takes one parameter, a FlowBuilder with the qualifier @FlowBuilderParameter, which is passed in from the JavaServer Faces implementation. The method then calls methods from the javax.faces.flow.Builder.FlowBuilder class to configure the flow.

First, the method defines the flow id as checkoutFlow. Then, it explicitly defines the start node for the flow. By default, this is the name of the flow with an .xhtml suffix.

The method then defines the return node similarly to the way the configuration file does. The returnNode method sets the name of the return node as returnFromCheckoutFlow, and the chained fromOutcome method specifies its value as the returnValue property of the flow-scoped managed bean for the checkout flow, CheckoutFlowBean.

The inboundParameter method sets the names and values of the inbound parameters from the join flow, which are retrieved from the flow scope in order (flowScope.param1Value, flowScope.param2Value), based on the way they were defined in the join flow configuration.

The flowCallNode method defines how the checkout flow calls the join flow. The argument, calljoin, specifies the action of calling the flow. The chained flowReference method defines the actual name of the flow to call, joinFlow, then calls outboundParameter methods to define the parameters to be passed when joinFlow is called. Here they are values from the CheckoutFlowBean managed bean.

Finally, the defineFlow method calls the getFlow method and returns the result.

16.3.3.4 The Flow-Scoped Managed Beans

Each of the two flows has a managed bean that defines properties for the pages within the flow. For example, the CheckoutFlowBean defines properties whose values are entered by the user on both the checkoutFlow.xhtml page and the checkoutFlow3.xhtml page.

Each managed bean has a getReturnValue method that sets the value of the return node. For the CheckoutFlowBean, the return node is the index.xhtml page, specified using implicit navigation:

public String getReturnValue() {
    return "index";
}

For the JoinFlowBean, the return node is the exithome.xhtml page.

16.3.3.5 To Build, Package, and Deploy the checkout-module Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf

Select the checkout-module folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the checkout-module project and select Build.

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, checkout-module.war, that is located in the target directory. It then deploys the application to the server.

16.3.3.6 To Build, Package, and Deploy the checkout-module Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf/checkout-module/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, checkout-module.war, that is located in the target directory. It then deploys the application to the server.

16.3.3.7 To Run the checkout-module Example

Enter the following URL in your web browser:

http://localhost:8080/checkout-module

The index.xhtml page presents hypothetical results of the shopping expedition. Click either Check Out or Join to enter one of the two flows.

Follow the flow, providing input as needed and choosing whether to continue, go back, or exit the flow.

In the checkout flow, only one of the input fields is validated (the credit card field expects 16 digits), so you can enter any values you like. The join flow does not require you to check any boxes in its checkbox menus.

On the last page of a flow, select the option to enter the other flow. This allows you to view the inbound parameters from the previous flow.

Because flows are nested, if you click Exit Flow from a called flow, you will return to the first page of the calling flow. (You may see a warning, which you can ignore.) Click Exit Flow on that page to go to the specified return node.

16.4 Configuring Managed Beans

When a page references a managed bean for the first time, the JavaServer Faces implementation initializes it either based on a @Named annotation and scope annotation in the bean class or according to its configuration in the application configuration resource file. For information on using annotations to initialize beans, see Using Annotations to Configure Managed Beans.

You can use either annotations or the application configuration resource file to instantiate managed beans that are used in a JavaServer Faces application and to store them in scope. The managed bean creation facility is configured in the application configuration resource file using managed-bean XML elements to define each bean. This file is processed at application startup time. For information on using this facility, see Using the managed-bean Element.

Managed beans created in the application configuration resource file are JavaServer Faces managed beans, not CDI managed beans.

With the managed bean creation facility, you can

Create beans in one centralized file that is available to the entire application, rather than conditionally instantiate beans throughout the application

Customize a bean's properties without any additional code

Customize a bean's property values directly from within the configuration file so that it is initialized with these values when it is created

Using value elements, set a property of one managed bean to be the result of evaluating another value expression

This section shows you how to initialize beans using the managed bean creation facility. See Writing Bean Properties and Writing Managed Bean Methods for information on programming managed beans.

16.4.1 Using the managed-bean Element

A managed bean is initiated in the application configuration resource file using a managed-bean element, which represents an instance of a bean class that must exist in the application. At runtime, the JavaServer Faces implementation processes the managed-bean element. If a page references the bean and no bean instance exists, the JavaServer Faces implementation instantiates the bean as specified by the element configuration.

Here is an example managed bean configuration from the Duke's Bookstore case study:

<managed-bean eager="true">
    <managed-bean-name>Book201</managed-bean-name>
    <managed-bean-class>dukesbookstore.model.ImageArea</managed-bean-class>
    <managed-bean-scope>application</managed-bean-scope>
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>shape</property-name>
        <value>rect</value>
    </managed-property>
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>alt</property-name>
        <value>Duke</value>
    </managed-property>
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>coords</property-name>
        <value>67,23,212,268</value>
    </managed-property>
</managed-bean>

The managed-bean-name element defines the key under which the bean will be stored in a scope. For a component's value to map to this bean, the component tag's value attribute must match the managed-bean-name up to the first period.

The managed-bean-class element defines the fully qualified name of the JavaBeans component class used to instantiate the bean.

The managed-bean element can contain zero or more managed-property elements, each corresponding to a property defined in the bean class. These elements are used to initialize the values of the bean properties. If you don't want a particular property initialized with a value when the bean is instantiated, do not include a managed-property definition for it in your application configuration resource file.

If a managed-bean element does not contain other managed-bean elements, it can contain one map-entries element or list-entries element. The map-entries element configures a set of beans that are instances of Map. The list-entries element configures a set of beans that are instances of List.

In the following example, the newsletters managed bean, representing a UISelectItems component, is configured as an ArrayList that represents a set of SelectItem objects. Each SelectItem object is in turn configured as a managed bean with properties:

<managed-bean>
    <managed-bean-name>newsletters</managed-bean-name>
    <managed-bean-class>java.util.ArrayList</managed-bean-class>
    <managed-bean-scope>application</managed-bean-scope>
    <list-entries>
        <value-class>javax.faces.model.SelectItem</value-class>
        <value>#{newsletter0}</value>
        <value>#{newsletter1}</value>
        <value>#{newsletter2}</value>
        <value>#{newsletter3}</value>
    </list-entries>
</managed-bean>
<managed-bean>
    <managed-bean-name>newsletter0</managed-bean-name>
    <managed-bean-class>javax.faces.model.SelectItem</managed-bean-class>
    <managed-bean-scope>none</managed-bean-scope>
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>label</property-name>
        <value>Duke's Quarterly</value>
    </managed-property>
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>value</property-name>
        <value>200</value>
    </managed-property>
</managed-bean>
...

This approach may be useful for quick-and-dirty creation of selection item lists before a development team has had time to create such lists from the database. Note that each of the individual newsletter beans has a managed-bean-scope setting of none so that they will not themselves be placed into any scope.

See Initializing Array and List Properties for more information on configuring collections as beans.

To map to a property defined by a managed-property element, you must ensure that the part of a component tag's value expression after the period matches the managed-property element's property-name element. The next section, Initializing Properties Using the managed-property Element, explains in more detail how to use the managed-property element. See Initializing Managed Bean Properties for an example of initializing a managed bean property.

16.4.2 Initializing Properties Using the managed-property Element

A managed-property element must contain a property-name element, which must match the name of the corresponding property in the bean. A managed-property element must also contain one of a set of elements that defines the value of the property. This value must be of the same type as that defined for the property in the corresponding bean. Which element you use to define the value depends on the type of the property defined in the bean. Table 16-1 lists all the elements that are used to initialize a value.

Table 16-1 Subelements of managed-property Elements That Define Property Values

Element | Value It Defines

list-entries

|

Defines the values in a list

map-entries

|

Defines the values of a map

null-value

|

Explicitly sets the property to null

value

|

Defines a single value, such as a String, int, or JavaServer Faces EL expression

Using the managed-bean Element includes an example of initializing an int property (a primitive type) using the value subelement. You also use the value subelement to initialize String and other reference types. The rest of this section describes how to use the value subelement and other subelements to initialize properties of Java Enum types, Map, array, and Collection, as well as initialization parameters.

16.4.2.1 Referencing a Java Enum Type

A managed bean property can also be a Java Enum type (see http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/lang/Enum.html). In this case, the value element of the managed-property element must be a String that matches one of the String constants of the Enum. In other words, the String must be one of the valid values that can be returned if you were to call valueOf(Class, String) on enum, where Class is the Enum class and String is the contents of the value subelement. For example, suppose the managed bean property is the following:

public enum Suit { Hearts, Spades, Diamonds, Clubs }
 ...
public Suit getSuit() { ... return Suit.Hearts; }

Assuming you want to configure this property in the application configuration resource file, the corresponding managed-property element looks like this:

<managed-property>
    <property-name>Suit</property-name>
    <value>Hearts</value>
</managed-property>

When the system encounters this property, it iterates over each of the members of the enum and calls toString() on each member until it finds one that is exactly equal to the value from the value element.

16.4.2.2 Referencing a Context Initialization Parameter

Another powerful feature of the managed bean creation facility is the ability to reference implicit objects from a managed bean property.

Suppose you have a page that accepts data from a customer, including the customer's address. Suppose also that most of your customers live in a particular area code. You can make the area code component render this area code by saving it in an implicit object and referencing it when the page is rendered.

You can save the area code as an initial default value in the context initParam implicit object by adding a context parameter to your web application and setting its value in the deployment descriptor. For example, to set a context parameter called defaultAreaCode to 650, add a context-param element to the deployment descriptor and give the parameter the name defaultAreaCode and the value 650.

Next, write a managed-bean declaration that configures a property that references the parameter:

<managed-bean>
    <managed-bean-name>customer</managed-bean-name>
        <managed-bean-class>CustomerBean</managed-bean-class>
        <managed-bean-scope>request</managed-bean-scope>
        <managed-property>
            <property-name>areaCode</property-name>
                <value>#{initParam.defaultAreaCode}</value>
            </managed-property>
            ...
</managed-bean>

To access the area code at the time the page is rendered, refer to the property from the area component tag's value attribute:

<h:inputText id=area value="#{customer.areaCode}"

Values are retrieved from other implicit objects in a similar way.

16.4.2.3 Initializing Map Properties

The map-entries element is used to initialize the values of a bean property with a type of Map if the map-entries element is used within a managed-property element. A map-entries element contains an optional key-class element, an optional value-class element, and zero or more map-entry elements.

Each of the map-entry elements must contain a key element and either a null-value or value element. Here is an example that uses the map-entries element:

<managed-bean>
    ...
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>prices</property-name>
        <map-entries>
            <map-entry>
                <key>My Early Years: Growing Up on *7</key>
                <value>30.75</value>
            </map-entry>
            <map-entry>
                <key>Web Servers for Fun and Profit</key>
                <value>40.75</value>
            </map-entry>
        </map-entries>
    </managed-property>
</managed-bean>

The map created from this map-entries tag contains two entries. By default, all the keys and values are converted to String. If you want to specify a different type for the keys in the map, embed the key-class element just inside the map-entries element:

<map-entries>
    <key-class>java.math.BigDecimal</key-class>
    ...
</map-entries>

This declaration will convert all the keys into java.math.BigDecimal. Of course, you must make sure that the keys can be converted to the type you specify. The key from the example in this section cannot be converted to a BigDecimal, because it is a String.

If you want to specify a different type for all the values in the map, include the value-class element after the key-class element:

<map-entries>
    <key-class>int</key-class>
    <value-class>java.math.BigDecimal</value-class>
    ...
</map-entries>

Note that this tag sets only the type of all the value subelements.

Each map-entry in the preceding example includes a value subelement. The value subelement defines a single value, which will be converted to the type specified in the bean.

Instead of using a map-entries element, it is also possible to assign the entire map using a value element that specifies a map-typed expression.

16.4.2.4 Initializing Array and List Properties

The list-entries element is used to initialize the values of an array or List property. Each individual value of the array or List is initialized using a value or null-value element. Here is an example:

<managed-bean>
    ...
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>books</property-name>
        <list-entries>
            <value-class>java.lang.String</value-class>
            <value>Web Servers for Fun and Profit</value>
            <value>#{myBooks.bookId[3]}</value>
            <null-value/>
        </list-entries>
    </managed-property>
</managed-bean>

This example initializes an array or a List. The type of the corresponding property in the bean determines which data structure is created. The list-entries element defines the list of values in the array or List. The value element specifies a single value in the array or List and can reference a property in another bean. The null-value element will cause the setBooks method to be called with an argument of null. A null property cannot be specified for a property whose data type is a Java primitive, such as int or boolean.

16.4.2.5 Initializing Managed Bean Properties

Sometimes you might want to create a bean that also references other managed beans so that you can construct a graph or a tree of beans. For example, suppose you want to create a bean representing a customer's information, including the mailing address and street address, each of which is also a bean. The following managed-bean declarations create a CustomerBean instance that has two AddressBean properties: one representing the mailing address and the other representing the street address. This declaration results in a tree of beans with CustomerBean as its root and the two AddressBean objects as children.

<managed-bean>
    <managed-bean-name>customer</managed-bean-name>
    <managed-bean-class>
        com.example.mybeans.CustomerBean
    </managed-bean-class>
    <managed-bean-scope> request </managed-bean-scope>
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>mailingAddress</property-name>
        <value>#{addressBean}</value>
    </managed-property>
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>streetAddress</property-name>
        <value>#{addressBean}</value>
    </managed-property>
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>customerType</property-name>
        <value>New</value>
    </managed-property>
</managed-bean>
<managed-bean>
    <managed-bean-name>addressBean</managed-bean-name>
    <managed-bean-class>
        com.example.mybeans.AddressBean
    </managed-bean-class>
    <managed-bean-scope> none </managed-bean-scope>
    <managed-property>
        <property-name>street</property-name>
        <null-value/>
    <managed-property>
    ...
</managed-bean>

The first CustomerBean declaration (with the managed-bean-name of customer) creates a CustomerBean in request scope. This bean has two properties, mailingAddress and streetAddress. These properties use the value element to reference a bean named addressBean.

The second managed bean declaration defines an AddressBean but does not create it, because its managed-bean-scope element defines a scope of none. Recall that a scope of none means that the bean is created only when something else references it. Because both the mailingAddress and the streetAddress properties reference addressBean using the value element, two instances of AddressBean are created when CustomerBean is created.

When you create an object that points to other objects, do not try to point to an object with a shorter life span, because it might be impossible to recover that scope's resources when it goes away. A session-scoped object, for example, cannot point to a request-scoped object. And objects with none scope have no effective life span managed by the framework, so they can point only to other none-scoped objects. Table 16-2 outlines all of the allowed connections.

Table 16-2 Allowable Connections between Scoped Objects

An Object of This Scope | May Point to an Object of This Scope

none

|

none

application

|

none, application

session

|

none, application, session

request

|

none, application, session, request, view

view

|

none, application, session, view

Be sure not to allow cyclical references between objects. For example, neither of the AddressBean objects in the preceding example should point back to the CustomerBean object, because CustomerBean already points to the AddressBean objects.

16.4.3 Initializing Maps and Lists

In addition to configuring Map and List properties, you can also configure a Map and a List directly so that you can reference them from a tag rather than referencing a property that wraps a Map or a List.

16.5 Registering Application Messages

Application messages can include any strings displayed to the user as well as custom error messages (which are displayed by the message and messages tags) for your custom converters or validators. To make messages available at application startup time, do one of the following:

Queue an individual message onto the javax.faces.context.FacesContext instance programmatically, as described in Using FacesMessage to Create a Message

Register all the messages with your application using the application configuration resource file

Here is the section of the faces-config.xml file that registers the messages for the Duke's Bookstore case study application:

<application>
    <resource-bundle>
        <base-name>
            javaeetutorial.dukesbookstore.web.messages.Messages
        </base-name>
        <var>bundle</var>
    </resource-bundle>
    <locale-config>
        <default-locale>en</default-locale>
        <supported-locale>es</supported-locale>
        <supported-locale>de</supported-locale>
        <supported-locale>fr</supported-locale>
    </locale-config>
</application>

This set of elements causes the application to be populated with the messages that are contained in the specified resource bundle.

The resource-bundle element represents a set of localized messages. It must contain the fully qualified path to the resource bundle containing the localized messages (in this case, dukesbookstore.web.messages.Messages). The var element defines the EL name by which page authors refer to the resource bundle.

The locale-config element lists the default locale and the other supported locales. The locale-config element enables the system to find the correct locale based on the browser's language settings.

The supported-locale and default-locale tags accept the lowercase, two-character codes defined by ISO 639-1 (see http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/php/English_list.php). Make sure that your resource bundle actually contains the messages for the locales you specify with these tags.

To access the localized message, the application developer merely references the key of the message from the resource bundle.

You can pull localized text into an alt tag for a graphic image, as in the following example:

<h:graphicImage id="mapImage" 
                name="book_all.jpg"
                library="images"
                alt="#{bundle.ChooseBook}"
                usemap="#bookMap" />

The alt attribute can accept value expressions. In this case, the alt attribute refers to localized text that will be included in the alternative text of the image rendered by this tag.

16.5.1 Using FacesMessage to Create a Message

Instead of registering messages in the application configuration resource file, you can access the java.util.ResourceBundle directly from managed bean code. The code snippet below locates an email error message:

String message = "";
...
message = ExampleBean.loadErrorMessage(context,
    ExampleBean.EX_RESOURCE_BUNDLE_NAME,
         "EMailError");
context.addMessage(toValidate.getClientId(context),
    new FacesMessage(message));

These lines call the bean's loadErrorMessage method to get the message from the ResourceBundle. Here is the loadErrorMessage method:

public static String loadErrorMessage(FacesContext context,
     String basename, String key) {
    if ( bundle == null ) {
         try {
            bundle = ResourceBundle.getBundle(basename,
                 context.getViewRoot().getLocale());
        } catch (Exception e) {
            return null;
        }
    }
    return bundle.getString(key);
}

16.5.2 Referencing Error Messages

A JavaServer Faces page uses the message or messages tags to access error messages, as explained in Displaying Error Messages with the h:message and h:messages Tags.

The error messages these tags access include

The standard error messages that accompany the standard converters and validators that ship with the API. (see Section 2.5.2.4 of the JavaServer Faces specification for a complete list of standard error messages)

Custom error messages contained in resource bundles registered with the application by the application architect using the resource-bundle element in the configuration file

When a converter or validator is registered on an input component, the appropriate error message is automatically queued on the component.

A page author can override the error messages queued on a component by using the following attributes of the component's tag:

converterMessage: References the error message to display when the data on the enclosing component cannot be converted by the converter registered on this component.

requiredMessage: References the error message to display when no value has been entered into the enclosing component.

validatorMessage: References the error message to display when the data on the enclosing component cannot be validated by the validator registered on this component.

All three attributes are enabled to take literal values and value expressions. If an attribute uses a value expression, this expression references the error message in a resource bundle. This resource bundle must be made available to the application in one of the following ways:

By the application architect using the resource-bundle element in the configuration file

By the page author using the f:loadBundle tag

Conversely, the resource-bundle element must be used to make available to the application those resource bundles containing custom error messages that are queued on the component as a result of a custom converter or validator being registered on the component.

The following tags show how to specify the requiredMessage attribute using a value expression to reference an error message:

<h:inputText id="ccno" size="19"
    required="true"
    requiredMessage="#{customMessages.ReqMessage}">
    ...
</h:inputText>
<h:message styleClass="error-message" for="ccno"/>

The value expression used by requiredMessage in this example references the error message with the ReqMessage key in the resource bundle customMessages.

This message replaces the corresponding message queued on the component and will display wherever the message or messages tag is placed on the page.

16.6 Using Default Validators

In addition to the validators you declare on the components, you can also specify zero or more default validators in the application configuration resource file. The default validator applies to all javax.faces.component.UIInput instances in a view or component tree and is appended after the local defined validators. Here is an example of a default validator registered in the application configuration resource file:

<faces-config>
    <application>
        <default-validators>
            <validator-id>javax.faces.Bean</validator-id>
        </default-validators>
    <application/>
</faces-config>

16.7 Registering a Custom Validator

If the application developer provides an implementation of the javax.faces.validator.Validator interface to perform validation, you must register this custom validator either by using the @FacesValidator annotation, as described in Implementing the Validator Interface, or by using the validator XML element in the application configuration resource file:

<validator>
    ...
    <validator-id>FormatValidator</validator-id>
    <validator-class>
        myapplication.validators.FormatValidator
    </validator-class>
    <attribute>
        ...
        <attribute-name>formatPatterns</attribute-name>
        <attribute-class>java.lang.String</attribute-class>
    </attribute>
</validator>

Attributes specified in a validator tag override any settings in the @FacesValidator annotation.

The validator-id and validator-class elements are required subelements. The validator-id element represents the identifier under which the Validator class should be registered. This ID is used by the tag class corresponding to the custom validator tag.

The validator-class element represents the fully qualified class name of the Validator class.

The attribute element identifies an attribute associated with the Validator implementation. It has required attribute-name and attribute-class subelements. The attribute-name element refers to the name of the attribute as it appears in the validator tag. The attribute-class element identifies the Java type of the value associated with the attribute.

Creating and Using a Custom Validator explains how to implement the Validator interface.

Using a Custom Validator explains how to reference the validator from the page.

16.8 Registering a Custom Converter

As is the case with a custom validator, if the application developer creates a custom converter, you must register it with the application either by using the @FacesConverter annotation, as described in Creating a Custom Converter, or by using the converter XML element in the application configuration resource file. Here is a hypothetical converter configuration for CreditCardConverter from the Duke's Bookstore case study:

<converter>
    <description>
        Converter for credit card numbers that normalizes
        the input to a standard format
    </description>
    <converter-id>CreditCardConverter</converter-id>
    <converter-class>
        dukesbookstore.converters.CreditCardConverter
    </converter-class>
</converter>

Attributes specified in a converter tag override any settings in the @FacesConverter annotation.

The converter element represents a javax.faces.convert.Converter implementation and contains required converter-id and converter-class elements.

The converter-id element identifies an ID that is used by the converter attribute of a UI component tag to apply the converter to the component's data. Using a Custom Converter includes an example of referencing the custom converter from a component tag.

The converter-class element identifies the Converter implementation.

Creating and Using a Custom Converter explains how to create a custom converter.

16.9 Configuring Navigation Rules

Navigation between different pages of a JavaServer Faces application, such as choosing the next page to be displayed after a button or link component is clicked, is defined by a set of rules. Navigation rules can be implicit, or they can be explicitly defined in the application configuration resource file. For more information on implicit navigation rules, see Navigation Model.

Each navigation rule specifies how to navigate from one page to another page or set of pages. The JavaServer Faces implementation chooses the proper navigation rule according to which page is currently displayed.

After the proper navigation rule is selected, the choice of which page to access next from the current page depends on two factors:

The action method invoked when the component was clicked

The logical outcome referenced by the component's tag or returned from the action method

The outcome can be anything the developer chooses, but Table 16-3 lists some outcomes commonly used in web applications.

Table 16-3 Common Outcome Strings

Outcome | What It Means

success

|

Everything worked. Go on to the next page.

failure

|

Something is wrong. Go on to an error page.

login

|

The user needs to log in first. Go on to the login page.

no results

|

The search did not find anything. Go to the search page again.

Usually, the action method performs some processing on the form data of the current page. For example, the method might check whether the user name and password entered in the form match the user name and password on file. If they match, the method returns the outcome success. Otherwise, it returns the outcome failure. As this example demonstrates, both the method used to process the action and the outcome returned are necessary to determine the correct page to access.

Here is a navigation rule that could be used with the example just described:

<navigation-rule>
    <from-view-id>/login.xhtml</from-view-id>
    <navigation-case>
        <from-action>#{LoginForm.login}</from-action>
        <from-outcome>success</from-outcome>
        <to-view-id>/storefront.xhtml</to-view-id>
    </navigation-case>
    <navigation-case>
        <from-action>#{LoginForm.logon}</from-action>
        <from-outcome>failure</from-outcome>
        <to-view-id>/logon.xhtml</to-view-id>
    </navigation-case>
</navigation-rule>

This navigation rule defines the possible ways to navigate from login.xhtml. Each navigation-case element defines one possible navigation path from login.xhtml. The first navigation-case says that if LoginForm.login returns an outcome of success, then storefront.xhtml will be accessed. The second navigation-case says that login.xhtml will be re-rendered if LoginForm.login returns failure.

The configuration of an application's page flow consists of a set of navigation rules. Each rule is defined by the navigation-rule element in the faces-config.xml file.

Each navigation-rule element corresponds to one component tree identifier defined by the optional from-view-id element. This means that each rule defines all the possible ways to navigate from one particular page in the application. If there is no from-view-id element, the navigation rules defined in the navigation-rule element apply to all the pages in the application. The from-view-id element also allows wildcard matching patterns. For example, this from-view-id element says that the navigation rule applies to all the pages in the books directory:

<from-view-id>/books/*</from-view-id>

A navigation-rule element can contain zero or more navigation-case elements. The navigation-case element defines a set of matching criteria. When these criteria are satisfied, the application will navigate to the page defined by the to-view-id element contained in the same navigation-case element.

The navigation criteria are defined by optional from-outcome and from-action elements. The from-outcome element defines a logical outcome, such as success. The from-action element uses a method expression to refer to an action method that returns a String, which is the logical outcome. The method performs some logic to determine the outcome and returns the outcome.

The navigation-case elements are checked against the outcome and the method expression in the following order.

Cases specifying both a from-outcome value and a from-action value. Both of these elements can be used if the action method returns different outcomes depending on the result of the processing it performs.

Cases specifying only a from-outcome value. The from-outcome element must match either the outcome defined by the action attribute of the javax.faces.component.UICommand component or the outcome returned by the method referred to by the UICommand component.

Cases specifying only a from-action value. This value must match the action expression specified by the component tag.

When any of these cases is matched, the component tree defined by the to-view-id element will be selected for rendering.

16.10 Registering a Custom Renderer with a Render Kit

When the application developer creates a custom renderer, as described in Delegating Rendering to a Renderer, you must register it using the appropriate render kit. Because the image map application implements an HTML image map, the AreaRenderer and MapRenderer classes in the Duke's Bookstore case study should be registered using the HTML render kit.

You register the renderer either by using the @FacesRenderer annotation, as described in Creating the Renderer Class, or by using the render-kit element of the application configuration resource file. Here is a hypothetical configuration of AreaRenderer:

<render-kit>
    <renderer>
        <component-family>Area</component-family>
        <renderer-type>DemoArea</renderer-type>
        <renderer-class>
            dukesbookstore.renderers.AreaRenderer
        </renderer-class>
        <attribute>
            <attribute-name>onmouseout</attribute-name>
            <attribute-class>java.lang.String</attribute-class>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
            <attribute-name>onmouseover</attribute-name>
            <attribute-class>java.lang.String</attribute-class>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
            <attribute-name>styleClass</attribute-name>
            <attribute-class>java.lang.String</attribute-class>
        </attribute>
    </renderer>
    ...

Attributes specified in a renderer tag override any settings in the @FacesRenderer annotation.

The render-kit element represents a javax.faces.render.RenderKit implementation. If no render-kit-id is specified, the default HTML render kit is assumed. The renderer element represents a javax.faces.render.Renderer implementation. By nesting the renderer element inside the render-kit element, you are registering the renderer with the RenderKit implementation associated with the render-kit element.

The renderer-class is the fully qualified class name of the Renderer.

The component-family and renderer-type elements are used by a component to find renderers that can render it. The component-family identifier must match that returned by the component class's getFamily method. The component family represents a component or set of components that a particular renderer can render. The renderer-type must match that returned by the getRendererType method of the tag handler class.

By using the component family and renderer type to look up renderers for components, the JavaServer Faces implementation allows a component to be rendered by multiple renderers and allows a renderer to render multiple components.

Each of the attribute tags specifies a render-dependent attribute and its type. The attribute element doesn't affect the runtime execution of your application. Rather, it provides information to tools about the attributes the Renderer supports.

The object responsible for rendering a component (be it the component itself or a renderer to which the component delegates the rendering) can use facets to aid in the rendering process. These facets allow the custom component developer to control some aspects of rendering the component. Consider this custom component tag example:

<d:dataScroller>
    <f:facet name="header">
        <h:panelGroup>
            <h:outputText value="Account Id"/>
            <h:outputText value="Customer Name"/>
            <h:outputText value="Total Sales"/>
        </h:panelGroup>
    </f:facet>
    <f:facet name="next">
        <h:panelGroup>
            <h:outputText value="Next"/>
            <h:graphicImage url="/images/arrow-right.gif" />
        </h:panelGroup>
    </f:facet>
    ...
</d:dataScroller>

The dataScroller component tag includes a component that will render the header and a component that will render the Next button. If the renderer associated with this component renders the facets, you can include the following facet elements in the renderer element:

<facet>
    <description>This facet renders as the header of the table. It should be
         a panelGroup with the same number of columns as the data.
    </description>
    <display-name>header</display-name>
    <facet-name>header</facet-name>
</facet>
<facet>
    <description>This facet renders as the content of the "next" button in
         the scroller. It should be a panelGroup that includes an outputText
         tag that has the text "Next" and a right arrow icon.
    </description>
    <display-name>Next</display-name>
    <facet-name>next</facet-name>
</facet>

If a component that supports facets provides its own rendering and you want to include facet elements in the application configuration resource file, you need to put them in the component's configuration rather than the renderer's configuration.

16.11 Registering a Custom Component

In addition to registering custom renderers (as explained in the preceding section), you also must register the custom components that are usually associated with the custom renderers. You use either a @FacesComponent annotation, as described in Creating Custom Component Classes, or the component element of the application configuration resource file.

Here is a hypothetical component element from the application configuration resource file that registers AreaComponent:

<component>
    <component-type>DemoArea</component-type>
    <component-class>
        dukesbookstore.components.AreaComponent
    </component-class>
    <property>
        <property-name>alt</property-name>
        <property-class>java.lang.String</property-class>
    </property>
    <property>
        <property-name>coords</property-name>
        <property-class>java.lang.String</property-class>
    </property>
    <property>
        <property-name>shape</property-name>
        <property-class>java.lang.String</property-class>
    </property>
</component>

Attributes specified in a component tag override any settings in the @FacesComponent annotation.

The component-type element indicates the name under which the component should be registered. Other objects referring to this component use this name. For example, the component-type element in the configuration for AreaComponent defines a value of DemoArea, which matches the value returned by the AreaTag class's getComponentType method.

The component-class element indicates the fully qualified class name of the component. The property elements specify the component properties and their types.

If the custom component can include facets, you can configure the facets in the component configuration using facet elements, which are allowed after the component-class elements. See Registering a Custom Renderer with a Render Kit for further details on configuring facets.

16.12 Basic Requirements of a JavaServer Faces Application

In addition to configuring your application, you must satisfy other requirements of JavaServer Faces applications, including properly packaging all the necessary files and providing a deployment descriptor. This section describes how to perform these administrative tasks.

JavaServer Faces applications can be packaged in a WAR file, which must conform to specific requirements to execute across different containers. At a minimum, a WAR file for a JavaServer Faces application may contain the following:

A web application deployment descriptor, called web.xml, to configure resources required by a web application (required)

A specific set of JAR files containing essential classes (optional)

A set of application classes, JavaServer Faces pages, and other required resources, such as image files

A WAR file may also contain:

An application configuration resource file, which configures application resources

A set of tag library descriptor files

For example, a Java Server Faces web application WAR file using Facelets typically has the following directory structure:

$PROJECT_DIR
[Web Pages]
+- /[xhtml or html documents]
+- /resources
+- /WEB-INF
   +- /web.xml
   +- /beans.xml (optional)
   +- /classes (optional)
   +- /lib (optional)
   +- /faces-config.xml (optional)
   +- /*.taglib.xml (optional)
   +- /glassfish-web.xml (optional)

The web.xml file (or web deployment descriptor), the set of JAR files, and the set of application files must be contained in the WEB-INF directory of the WAR file.

16.12.1 Configuring an Application with a Web Deployment Descriptor

Web applications are commonly configured using elements contained in the web application deployment descriptor, web.xml. The deployment descriptor for a JavaServer Faces application must specify certain configurations, including the following:

The servlet used to process JavaServer Faces requests

The servlet mapping for the processing servlet

The path to the configuration resource file, if it exists and is not located in a default location

The deployment descriptor can also include other, optional configurations, such as those that

Specify where component state is saved

Encrypt state saved on the client

Compress state saved on the client

Restrict access to pages containing JavaServer Faces tags

Turn on XML validation

Specify the Project Stage

Verify custom objects

This section gives more details on these configurations. Where appropriate, it also describes how you can make these configurations using NetBeans IDE.

16.12.1.1 Identifying the Servlet for Lifecycle Processing

A requirement of a JavaServer Faces application is that all requests to the application that reference previously saved JavaServer Faces components must go through javax.faces.webapp.FacesServlet. A FacesServlet instance manages the request-processing lifecycle for web applications and initializes the resources required by JavaServer Faces technology.

Before a JavaServer Faces application can launch its first web page, the web container must invoke the FacesServlet instance in order for the application lifecycle process to start. See The Lifecycle of a JavaServer Faces Application for more information.

The following example shows the default configuration of the FacesServlet:

<servlet>
    <servlet-name>Faces Servlet</servlet-name>
    <servlet-class>javax.faces.webapp.FacesServlet</servlet-class>
</servlet>

You will provide a mapping configuration entry to make sure that the FacesServlet instance is invoked. The mapping to FacesServlet can be a prefix mapping, such as /faces/*, or an extension mapping, such as *.xhtml. The mapping is used to identify a page as having JavaServer Faces content. Because of this, the URL to the first page of the application must include the URL pattern mapping.

The following elements specify a prefix mapping:

<servlet-mapping>
    <servlet-name>Faces Servlet</servlet-name>
    <url-pattern>/faces/*</url-pattern>
</servlet-mapping>
...
<welcome-file-list>
    <welcome-file>faces/greeting.xhtml</welcome-file>
</welcome-file-list>

The following elements, used in the tutorial examples, specify an extension mapping:

<servlet-mapping>
    <servlet-name>Faces Servlet</servlet-name>
    <url-pattern>*.xhtml</url-pattern>
</servlet-mapping>
...
<welcome-file-list>
    <welcome-file>index.xhtml</welcome-file>
</welcome-file-list>

When you use this mechanism, users access the application as shown in the following example:

http://localhost:8080/guessNumber

In the case of extension mapping, if a request comes to the server for a page with an .xhtml extension, the container will send the request to the FacesServlet instance, which will expect a corresponding page of the same name containing the content to exist.

If you are using NetBeans IDE to create your application, a web deployment descriptor is automatically created for you with default configurations. If you created your application without an IDE, you can create a web deployment descriptor.

16.12.1.2 To Specify a Path to an Application Configuration Resource File

As explained in Application Configuration Resource File, an application can have multiple application configuration resource files. If these files are not located in the directories that the implementation searches by default or the files are not named faces-config.xml, you need to specify paths to these files.

To specify these paths using NetBeans IDE, do the following.

Expand the node of your project in the Projects tab.

Expand the Web Pages and WEB-INF nodes that are under the project node.

Double-click web.xml.

After the web.xml file appears in the editor, click General at the top of the editor window.

Expand the Context Parameters node.

Click Add.

In the Add Context Parameter dialog box:

Enter javax.faces.CONFIG_FILES in the Parameter Name field.

Enter the path to your configuration file in the Parameter Value field.

Click OK.

Repeat steps 1 through 7 for each configuration file.

16.12.1.3 To Specify Where State Is Saved

For all the components in a web application, you can specify in your deployment descriptor where you want the state to be saved, on either client or server. You do this by setting a context parameter in your deployment descriptor. By default, state is saved on the server, so you need to specify this context parameter only if you want to save state on the client. See Saving and Restoring State for information on the advantages and disadvantages of each location.

To specify where state is saved using NetBeans IDE, do the following.

Expand the node of your project in the Projects tab.

Expand the Web Pages and WEB-INF nodes under the project node.

Double-click web.xml.

After the web.xml file appears in the editor window, click General at the top of the editor window.

Expand the Context Parameters node.

Click Add.

In the Add Context Parameter dialog box:

Enter javax.faces.STATE_SAVING_METHOD in the Parameter Name field.

Enter client or server in the Parameter Value field.

Click OK.

If state is saved on the client, the state of the entire view is rendered to a hidden field on the page. The JavaServer Faces implementation saves the state on the server by default. Duke's Forest saves its state on the client.

16.12.2 Configuring Project Stage

Project Stage is a context parameter identifying the status of a JavaServer Faces application in the software lifecycle. The stage of an application can affect the behavior of the application. For example, error messages can be displayed during the Development stage but suppressed during the Production stage.

The possible Project Stage values are as follows:

Development

UnitTest

SystemTest

Production

Project Stage is configured through a context parameter in the web deployment descriptor file. Here is an example:

<context-param>
    <param-name>javax.faces.PROJECT_STAGE</param-name>
    <param-value>Development</param-value>
</context-param>

If no Project Stage is defined, the default stage is Production. You can also add custom stages according to your requirements.

16.12.3 Including the Classes, Pages, and Other Resources

When packaging web applications using the included build scripts, you'll notice that the scripts package resources in the following ways.

All web pages are placed at the top level of the WAR file.

The faces-config.xml file and the web.xml file are packaged in the WEB-INF directory.

All packages are stored in the WEB-INF/classes/ directory.

All application JAR files are packaged in the WEB-INF/lib/ directory.

All resource files are either under the root of the web application /resources directory or in the web application's classpath, the META-INF/resources/resourceIdentifier directory. For more information on resources, see Web Resources.

When packaging your own applications, you can use NetBeans IDE or you can use XML files such as those created for Maven. You can modify the XML files to fit your situation. However, you can continue to package your WAR files by using the directory structure described in this section, because this technique complies with the commonly accepted practice for packaging web applications.

15 Creating Custom UI Components and Other Custom Objects

JavaServer Faces technology offers a basic set of standard, reusable UI components that enable quick and easy construction of user interfaces for web applications. These components mostly map one-to-one to the elements in HTML 4. But often an application requires a component that has additional functionality or requires a completely new component. JavaServer Faces technology allows extension of standard components to enhance their functionality or to create custom components. A rich ecosystem of third-party component libraries is built on this extension capability, but it is beyond the scope of this tutorial to examine them. A web search for "JSF Component Libraries" is a good starting point to learn more about this important aspect of using JavaServer Faces technology.

In addition to extending the functionality of standard components, a component writer might want to give a page author the ability to change the appearance of the component on the page or to alter listener behavior. Alternatively, the component writer might want to render a component to a different kind of client device type, such as a smartphone or a tablet instead of a desktop computer. Enabled by the flexible JavaServer Faces architecture, a component writer can separate the definition of the component behavior from its appearance by delegating the rendering of the component to a separate renderer. In this way, a component writer can define the behavior of a custom component once but create multiple renderers, each of which defines a different way to render the component to a particular kind of client device.

A javax.faces.component.UIComponent is a Java class that is responsible for representing a self-contained piece of the user interface during the request-processing lifecycle. It is intended to represent the meaning of the component; the visual representation of the component is the responsibility of the javax.faces.render.Renderer. There can be multiple instances of the same UIComponent class in any given JavaServer Faces view, just as there can be multiple instances of any Java class in any given Java program.

JavaServer Faces technology provides the ability to create custom components by extending the UIComponent class, the base class for all standard UI components. A custom component can be used anywhere an ordinary component can be used, such as within a composite component. A UIComponent is identified by two names: component-family specifies the general purpose of the component (input or output, for instance), and component-type indicates the specific purpose of a component, such as a text input field or a command button.

A Renderer is a helper to the UIComponent that deals with how that specific UIComponent class should appear in a specific kind of client device. Renderers are identified by two names: render-kit-id and renderer-type. A render kit is just a bucket into which a particular group of renderers is placed, and the render-kit-id identifies the group. Most JavaServer Faces component libraries provide their own render kits.

A javax.faces.view.facelets.Tag object is a helper to the UIComponent and Renderer that allows the page author to include an instance of a UIComponent in a JavaServer Faces view. A tag represents a specific combination of component-type and renderer-type.

See Component, Renderer, and Tag Combinations for information on how components, renderers, and tags interact.

This chapter uses the image map component from the Duke's Bookstore case study example to explain how you can create simple custom components, custom renderers, and associated custom tags, and take care of all the other details associated with using the components and renderers in an application. See Chapter 57, "Duke's Bookstore Case Study Example" for more information about this example.

The chapter also describes how to create other custom objects: custom converters, custom listeners, and custom validators. It also describes how to bind component values and instances to data objects and how to bind custom objects to managed bean properties.

The following topics are addressed here:

Determining Whether You Need a Custom Component or Renderer

Understanding the Image Map Example

Steps for Creating a Custom Component

Creating Custom Component Classes

Delegating Rendering to a Renderer

Implementing an Event Listener

Handling Events for Custom Components

Defining the Custom Component Tag in a Tag Library Descriptor

Using a Custom Component

Creating and Using a Custom Converter

Creating and Using a Custom Validator

Binding Component Values and Instances to Managed Bean Properties

Binding Converters, Listeners, and Validators to Managed Bean Properties

15.1 Determining Whether You Need a Custom Component or Renderer

The JavaServer Faces implementation supports a very basic set of components and associated renderers. This section helps you to decide whether you can use standard components and renderers in your application or need a custom component or custom renderer.

15.1.1 When to Use a Custom Component

A component class defines the state and behavior of a UI component. This behavior includes converting the value of a component to the appropriate markup, queuing events on components, performing validation, and any other behavior related to how the component interacts with the browser and the request-processing lifecycle.

You need to create a custom component in the following situations.

You need to add new behavior to a standard component, such as generating an additional type of event (for example, notifying another part of the page that something changed in this component as a result of user interaction).

You need to take a different action in the request processing of the value of a component from what is available in any of the existing standard components.

You want to take advantage of an HTML capability offered by your target browser, but none of the standard JavaServer Faces components take advantage of the capability in the way you want, if at all. The current release does not contain standard components for complex HTML components, such as frames; however, because of the extensibility of the component architecture, you can use JavaServer Faces technology to create components like these. The Duke's Bookstore case study creates custom components that correspond to the HTML map and area tags.

You need to render to a non-HTML client that requires extra components not supported by HTML. Eventually, the standard HTML render kit will provide support for all standard HTML components. However, if you are rendering to a different client, such as a phone, you might need to create custom components to represent the controls uniquely supported by the client. For example, some component architectures for wireless clients include support for tickers and progress bars, which are not available on an HTML client. In this case, you might also need a custom renderer along with the component, or you might need only a custom renderer.

You do not need to create a custom component in the following cases.

You need to aggregate components to create a new component that has its own unique behavior. In this situation, you can use a composite component to combine existing standard components. For more information on composite components, see Composite Components and Chapter 14, "Composite Components: Advanced Topics and an Example".

You simply need to manipulate data on the component or add application-specific functionality to it. In this situation, you should create a managed bean for this purpose and bind it to the standard component rather than create a custom component. See Managed Beans in JavaServer Faces Technology for more information on managed beans.

You need to convert a component's data to a type not supported by its renderer. See Using the Standard Converters for more information about converting a component's data.

You need to perform validation on the component data. Standard validators and custom validators can be added to a component by using the validator tags from the page. See Using the Standard Validators and Creating and Using a Custom Validator for more information about validating a component's data.

You need to register event listeners on components. You can either register event listeners on components using the f:valueChangeListener and f:actionListener tags, or you can point at an event-processing method on a managed bean using the component's actionListener or valueChangeListener attributes. See Implementing an Event Listener and Writing Managed Bean Methods for more information.

15.1.2 When to Use a Custom Renderer

A renderer, which generates the markup to display a component on a web page, allows you to separate the semantics of a component from its appearance. By keeping this separation, you can support different kinds of client devices with the same kind of authoring experience. You can think of a renderer as a "client adapter." It produces output suitable for consumption and display by the client and accepts input from the client when the user interacts with that component.

If you are creating a custom component, you need to ensure, among other things, that your component class performs these operations that are central to rendering the component:

Decoding: Converting the incoming request parameters to the local value of the component

Encoding: Converting the current local value of the component into the corresponding markup that represents it in the response

The JavaServer Faces specification supports two programming models for handling encoding and decoding.

Direct implementation: The component class itself implements the decoding and encoding.

Delegated implementation: The component class delegates the implementation of encoding and decoding to a separate renderer.

By delegating the operations to the renderer, you have the option of associating your custom component with different renderers so that you can render the component on different clients. If you don't plan to render a particular component on different clients, it may be simpler to let the component class handle the rendering. However, a separate renderer enables you to preserve the separation of semantics from appearance. The Duke's Bookstore application separates the renderers from the components, although it renders only to HTML 4 web browsers.

If you aren't sure whether you will need the flexibility offered by separate renderers but you want to use the simpler direct-implementation approach, you can actually use both models. Your component class can include some default rendering code, but it can delegate rendering to a renderer if there is one.

15.1.3 Component, Renderer, and Tag Combinations

When you create a custom component, you can create a custom renderer to go with it. To associate the component with the renderer and to reference the component from the page, you will also need a custom tag.

Although you need to write the custom component and renderer, there is no need to write code for a custom tag (called a tag handler). If you specify the component and renderer combination, Facelets creates the tag handler automatically.

In rare situations, you might use a custom renderer with a standard component rather than a custom component. Or you might use a custom tag without a renderer or a component. This section gives examples of these situations and summarizes what is required for a custom component, renderer, and tag.

You would use a custom renderer without a custom component if you wanted to add some client-side validation on a standard component. You would implement the validation code with a client-side scripting language, such as JavaScript, and then render the JavaScript with the custom renderer. In this situation, you need a custom tag to go with the renderer so that its tag handler can register the renderer on the standard component.

Custom components as well as custom renderers need custom tags associated with them. However, you can have a custom tag without a custom renderer or custom component. For example, suppose that you need to create a custom validator that requires extra attributes on the validator tag. In this case, the custom tag corresponds to a custom validator and not to a custom component or custom renderer. In any case, you still need to associate the custom tag with a server-side object.

Table 15-1 summarizes what you must or can associate with a custom component, custom renderer, or custom tag.

Table 15-1 Requirements for Custom Components, Custom Renderers, and Custom Tags

Custom Item | Must Have | Can Have

Custom component

|

Custom tag

|

Custom renderer or standard renderer

Custom renderer

|

Custom tag

|

Custom component or standard component

Custom JavaServer Faces tag

|

Some server-side object, like a component, a custom renderer, or custom validator

|

Custom component or standard component associated with a custom renderer

15.2 Understanding the Image Map Example

Duke's Bookstore includes a custom image map component on the index.xhtml page. This image map displays a selection of six book titles. When the user clicks one of the book titles in the image map, the application goes to a page that displays the title of the selected book as well as information about a featured book. The page allows the user to add either book (or none) to the shopping cart.

15.2.1 Why Use JavaServer Faces Technology to Implement an Image Map?

JavaServer Faces technology is an ideal framework to use for implementing this kind of image map because it can perform the work that must be done on the server without requiring you to create a server-side image map.

In general, client-side image maps are preferred over server-side image maps for several reasons. One reason is that the client-side image map allows the browser to provide immediate feedback when a user positions the mouse over a hotspot. Another reason is that client-side image maps perform better because they don't require round-trips to the server. However, in some situations, your image map might need to access the server to retrieve data or to change the appearance of nonform controls, tasks that a client-side image map cannot do.

Because the image map custom component uses JavaServer Faces technology, it has the best of both styles of image maps: It can handle the parts of the application that need to be performed on the server while allowing the other parts of the application to be performed on the client side.

15.2.2 Understanding the Rendered HTML

Here is an abbreviated version of the form part of the HTML page that the application needs to render:

<form id="j_idt13" name="j_idt13" method="post"
        action="/dukesbookstore/index.xhtml" ...>
    ...
    <img id="j_idt13:mapImage"
         src="/dukesbookstore/javax.faces.resource/book_all.jpg?ln=images"
         alt="Choose a Book from our Catalog"
         usemap="#bookMap" />
    ...
    <map name="bookMap">
       <area alt="Duke"                        
          coords="67,23,212,268"
          shape="rect"
          onmouseout="document.forms[0]['j_idt13:mapImage'].src='resources/images/book_all.jpg'"
          onmouseover="document.forms[0]['j_idt13:mapImage'].src='resources/images/book_201.jpg'"
          onclick="document.forms[0]['bookMap_current'].value='Duke'; document.forms[0].submit()"
       />
    ...
       <input type="hidden" name="bookMap_current">
    </map>
    ...
</form>

The img tag associates an image (book_all.jpg) with the image map referenced in the usemap attribute value.

The map tag specifies the image map and contains a set of area tags.

Each area tag specifies a region of the image map. The onmouseover, onmouseout, and onclick attributes define which JavaScript code is executed when these events occur. When the user moves the mouse over a region, the onmouseover function associated with the region displays the map with that region highlighted. When the user moves the mouse out of a region, the onmouseout function redisplays the original image. If the user clicks on a region, the onclick function sets the value of the input tag to the ID of the selected area and submits the page.

The input tag represents a hidden control that stores the value of the currently selected area between client-server exchanges so that the server-side component classes can retrieve the value.

The server-side objects retrieve the value of bookMap_current and set the locale in the javax.faces.context.FacesContext instance according to the region that was selected.

15.2.3 Understanding the Facelets Page

Here is an abbreviated form of the Facelets page that the image map component uses to generate the HTML page shown in the preceding section. It uses custom bookstore:map and bookstore:area tags to represent the custom components:

<h:form>
    ...
        <h:graphicImage id="mapImage" 
                        name="book_all.jpg"
                        library="images"
                        alt="#{bundle.ChooseBook}"
                        usemap="#bookMap" />
        <bookstore:map id="bookMap" 
                       current="map1"
                       immediate="true"
                       action="bookstore">
            <f:actionListener
                type="dukesbookstore.listeners.MapBookChangeListener" />
            <bookstore:area id="map1" value="#{Book201}"
                            onmouseover="resources/images/book_201.jpg"
                            onmouseout="resources/images/book_all.jpg"
                            targetImage="mapImage" />
            <bookstore:area id="map2" value="#{Book202}" 
                            onmouseover="resources/images/book_202.jpg"
                            onmouseout="resources/images/book_all.jpg" 
                            targetImage="mapImage"/>
            ...
        </bookstore:map>
    ...
</h:form>

The alt attribute of the h:graphicImage tag maps to the localized string "Choose a Book from our Catalog".

The f:actionListener tag within the bookstore:map tag points to a listener class for an action event. The processAction method of the listener places the book ID for the selected map area into the session map. The way this event is handled is explained more in Handling Events for Custom Components.

The action attribute of the bookstore:map tag specifies a logical outcome String, "bookstore", which by implicit navigation rules sends the application to the page bookstore.xhtml. For more information on navigation, see Configuring Navigation Rules.

The immediate attribute of the bookstore:map tag is set to true, which indicates that the default javax.faces.event.ActionListener implementation should execute during the Apply Request Values phase of the request-processing lifecycle, instead of waiting for the Invoke Application phase. Because the request resulting from clicking the map does not require any validation, data conversion, or server-side object updates, it makes sense to skip directly to the Invoke Application phase.

The current attribute of the bookstore:map tag is set to the default area, which is map1 (the book My Early Years: Growing Up on Star7, by Duke).

Notice that the bookstore:area tags do not contain any of the JavaScript, coordinate, or shape data that is displayed on the HTML page. The JavaScript is generated by the dukesbookstore.renderers.AreaRenderer class. The onmouseover and onmouseout attribute values indicate the image to be loaded when these events occur. How the JavaScript is generated is explained more in Performing Encoding.

The coordinate, shape, and alternate text data are obtained through the value attribute, whose value refers to an attribute in application scope. The value of this attribute is a bean, which stores the coords, shape, and alt data. How these beans are stored in the application scope is explained more in the next section.

15.2.4 Configuring Model Data

In a JavaServer Faces application, data such as the coordinates of a hotspot of an image map is retrieved from the value attribute through a bean. However, the shape and coordinates of a hotspot should be defined together because the coordinates are interpreted differently depending on what shape the hotspot is. Because a component's value can be bound only to one property, the value attribute cannot refer to both the shape and the coordinates.

To solve this problem, the application encapsulates all of this information in a set of ImageArea objects. These objects are initialized into application scope by the managed bean creation facility (see Section 16.4.1, "Using the managed-bean Element"). Here is part of the managed bean declaration for the ImageArea bean corresponding to the South America hotspot:

<managed-bean eager="true">
    ...
    <managed-bean-name>Book201</managed-bean-name>
    <managed-bean-class>
        javaeetutorial.dukesbookstore.model.ImageArea
    </managed-bean-class>
    <managed-bean-scope>application</managed-bean-scope>
    <managed-property>
        ...
        <property-name>shape</property-name>
        <value>rect</value>
    </managed-property>
    <managed-property>
        ...
        <property-name>alt</property-name>
        <value>Duke</value>
    </managed-property>
    <managed-property>
        ...
        <property-name>coords</property-name>
        <value>67,23,212,268</value>
    </managed-property>
</managed-bean>

For more information on initializing managed beans with the managed bean creation facility, see the section Application Configuration Resource File.

The value attributes of the bookstore:area tags refer to the beans in the application scope, as shown in this bookstore:area tag from index.xhtml:

<bookstore:area id="map1" value="#{Book201}"
                onmouseover="resources/images/book_201.jpg"
                onmouseout="resources/images/book_all.jpg"
                targetImage="mapImage" />

To reference the ImageArea model object bean values from the component class, you implement a getValue method in the component class. This method calls super.getValue. The superclass of tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/src/java/dukesbookstore/components/AreaComponent.java, UIOutput, has a getValue method that does the work of finding the ImageArea object associated with AreaComponent. The AreaRenderer class, which needs to render the alt, shape, and coords values from the ImageArea object, calls the getValue method of AreaComponent to retrieve the ImageArea object.

ImageArea iarea = (ImageArea) area.getValue();

ImageArea is a simple bean, so you can access the shape, coordinates, and alternative text values by calling the appropriate accessor methods of ImageArea. Creating the Renderer Class explains how to do this in the AreaRenderer class.

15.2.5 Summary of the Image Map Application Classes

Table 15-2 summarizes all the classes needed to implement the image map component.

Table 15-2 Image Map Classes

Class | Function

AreaSelectedEvent

|

The javax.faces.event.ActionEvent indicating that an AreaComponent from the MapComponent has been selected.

AreaComponent

|

The class that defines AreaComponent, which corresponds to the bookstore:area custom tag.

MapComponent

|

The class that defines MapComponent, which corresponds to the bookstore:map custom tag.

AreaRenderer

|

This javax.faces.render.Renderer performs the delegated rendering for AreaComponent.

ImageArea

|

The bean that stores the shape and coordinates of the hotspots.

MapBookChangeListener

|

The action listener for the MapComponent.

The Duke's Bookstore source directory, called bookstore-dir, is tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/src/java/dukesbookstore/. The event and listener classes are located in bookstore-dir/listeners/. The component classes are located in bookstore-dir/components/. The renderer classes are located in bookstore-dir/renderers/. ImageArea is located in bookstore-dir/model/.

15.3 Steps for Creating a Custom Component

You can apply the following steps while developing your own custom component.

Create a custom component class that does the following:

Overrides the getFamily method to return the component family, which is used to look up renderers that can render the component

Includes the rendering code or delegates it to a renderer (explained in Step 2)

Enables component attributes to accept expressions

Queues an event on the component if the component generates events

Saves and restores the component state

Delegate rendering to a renderer if your component does not handle the rendering. To do this:

Create a custom renderer class by extending javax.faces.render.Renderer.

Register the renderer to a render kit.

Register the component.

Create an event handler if your component generates events.

Create a tag library descriptor (TLD) that defines the custom tag.

See Registering a Custom Component and Registering a Custom Renderer with a Render Kit for information on registering the custom component and the renderer. The section Using a Custom Component discusses how to use the custom component in a JavaServer Faces page.

15.4 Creating Custom Component Classes

As explained in When to Use a Custom Component, a component class defines the state and behavior of a UI component. The state information includes the component's type, identifier, and local value. The behavior defined by the component class includes the following:

Decoding (converting the request parameter to the component's local value)

Encoding (converting the local value into the corresponding markup)

Saving the state of the component

Updating the bean value with the local value

Processing validation on the local value

Queueing events

The javax.faces.component.UIComponentBase class defines the default behavior of a component class. All the classes representing the standard components extend from UIComponentBase. These classes add their own behavior definitions, as your custom component class will do.

Your custom component class must either extend UIComponentBase directly or extend a class representing one of the standard components. These classes are located in the javax.faces.component package, and their names begin with UI.

If your custom component serves the same purpose as a standard component, you should extend that standard component rather than directly extend UIComponentBase. For example, suppose you want to create an editable menu component. It makes sense to have this component extend UISelectOne rather than UIComponentBase because you can reuse the behavior already defined in UISelectOne. The only new functionality you need to define is to make the menu editable.

Whether you decide to have your component extend UIComponentBase or a standard component, you might also want your component to implement one or more of these behavioral interfaces defined in the javax.faces.component package:

ActionSource: Indicates that the component can fire a javax.faces.event.ActionEvent

ActionSource2: Extends ActionSource and allows component properties referencing methods that handle action events to use method expressions as defined by the EL

EditableValueHolder: Extends ValueHolder and specifies additional features for editable components, such as validation and emitting value-change events

NamingContainer: Mandates that each component rooted at this component has a unique ID

StateHolder: Denotes that a component has state that must be saved between requests

ValueHolder: Indicates that the component maintains a local value as well as the option of accessing data in the model tier

If your component extends UIComponentBase, it automatically implements only StateHolder. Because all components directly or indirectly extend UIComponentBase, they all implement StateHolder. Any component that implements StateHolder also implements the StateHelper interface, which extends StateHolder and defines a Map-like contract that makes it easy for components to save and restore a partial view state.

If your component extends one of the other standard components, it might also implement other behavioral interfaces in addition to StateHolder. If your component extends UICommand, it automatically implements ActionSource2. If your component extends UIOutput or one of the component classes that extend UIOutput, it automatically implements ValueHolder. If your component extends UIInput, it automatically implements EditableValueHolder and ValueHolder. See the JavaServer Faces API documentation to find out what the other component classes implement.

You can also make your component explicitly implement a behavioral interface that it doesn't already by virtue of extending a particular standard component. For example, if you have a component that extends UIInput and you want it to fire action events, you must make it explicitly implement ActionSource2 because a UIInput component doesn't automatically implement this interface.

The Duke's Bookstore image map example has two component classes: AreaComponent and MapComponent. The MapComponent class extends UICommand and therefore implements ActionSource2, which means it can fire action events when a user clicks on the map. The AreaComponent class extends the standard component UIOutput. The @FacesComponent annotation registers the components with the JavaServer Faces implementation:

@FacesComponent("DemoMap")
public class MapComponent extends UICommand {...}

@FacesComponent("DemoArea")
public class AreaComponent extends UIOutput {...}

The MapComponent class represents the component corresponding to the bookstore:map tag:

<bookstore:map id="bookMap" 
               current="map1" 
               immediate="true"
               action="bookstore">
    ...
</bookstore:map>

The AreaComponent class represents the component corresponding to the bookstore:area tag:

<bookstore:area id="map1" value="#{Book201}" 
                onmouseover="resources/images/book_201.jpg" 
                onmouseout="resources/images/book_all.jpg" 
                targetImage="mapImage"/>

MapComponent has one or more AreaComponent instances as children. Its behavior consists of the following actions:

Retrieving the value of the currently selected area

Defining the properties corresponding to the component's values

Generating an event when the user clicks on the image map

Queuing the event

Saving its state

Rendering the HTML map tag and the HTML input tag

MapComponent delegates the rendering of the HTML map and input tags to the MapRenderer class.

AreaComponent is bound to a bean that stores the shape and coordinates of the region of the image map. You will see how all this data is accessed through the value expression in Creating the Renderer Class. The behavior of AreaComponent consists of the following:

Retrieving the shape and coordinate data from the bean

Setting the value of the hidden tag to the id of this component

Rendering the area tag, including the JavaScript for the onmouseover, onmouseout, and onclick functions

Although these tasks are actually performed by AreaRenderer, AreaComponent must delegate the tasks to AreaRenderer. See Delegating Rendering to a Renderer for more information.

The rest of this section describes the tasks that MapComponent performs as well as the encoding and decoding that it delegates to MapRenderer. Handling Events for Custom Components details how MapComponent handles events.

15.4.1 Specifying the Component Family

If your custom component class delegates rendering, it needs to override the getFamily method of UIComponent to return the identifier of a component family, which is used to refer to a component or set of components that can be rendered by a renderer or set of renderers. The component family is used along with the renderer type to look up renderers that can render the component:

public String getFamily() {
    return ("Map");
}

The component family identifier, Map, must match that defined by the component-family elements included in the component and renderer configurations in the application configuration resource file. Registering a Custom Renderer with a Render Kit explains how to define the component family in the renderer configuration. Registering a Custom Component explains how to define the component family in the component configuration.

15.4.2 Performing Encoding

During the Render Response phase, the JavaServer Faces implementation processes the encoding methods of all components and their associated renderers in the view. The encoding methods convert the current local value of the component into the corresponding markup that represents it in the response.

The UIComponentBase class defines a set of methods for rendering markup: encodeBegin, encodeChildren, and encodeEnd. If the component has child components, you might need to use more than one of these methods to render the component; otherwise, all rendering should be done in encodeEnd. Alternatively, you can use the encodeALL method, which encompasses all the methods.

Because MapComponent is a parent component of AreaComponent, the area tags must be rendered after the beginning map tag and before the ending map tag. To accomplish this, the MapRenderer class renders the beginning map tag in encodeBegin and the rest of the map tag in encodeEnd.

The JavaServer Faces implementation automatically invokes the encodeEnd method of AreaComponent's renderer after it invokes MapRenderer's encodeBegin method and before it invokes MapRenderer's encodeEnd method. If a component needs to perform the rendering for its children, it does this in the encodeChildren method.

Here are the encodeBegin and encodeEnd methods of MapRenderer:

@Override
public void encodeBegin(FacesContext context, UIComponent component) 
        throws IOException {
    if ((context == null)|| (component == null)) {
        throw new NullPointerException();
    }
    MapComponent map = (MapComponent) component;
    ResponseWriter writer = context.getResponseWriter();
    writer.startElement("map", map);
    writer.writeAttribute("name", map.getId(), "id");
}

@Override
public void encodeEnd(FacesContext context, UIComponent component) 
        throws IOException {
    if ((context == null) || (component == null)){
        throw new NullPointerException();
    }
    MapComponent map = (MapComponent) component;
    ResponseWriter writer = context.getResponseWriter();
    writer.startElement("input", map);
    writer.writeAttribute("type", "hidden", null);
    writer.writeAttribute("name", getName(context,map), "clientId");
    writer.endElement("input");
    writer.endElement("map");
}

Notice that encodeBegin renders only the beginning map tag. The encodeEnd method renders the input tag and the ending map tag.

The encoding methods accept a UIComponent argument and a javax.faces.context.FacesContext argument. The FacesContext instance contains all the information associated with the current request. The UIComponent argument is the component that needs to be rendered.

The rest of the method renders the markup to the javax.faces.context.ResponseWriter instance, which writes out the markup to the current response. This basically involves passing the HTML tag names and attribute names to the ResponseWriter instance as strings, retrieving the values of the component attributes, and passing these values to the ResponseWriter instance.

The startElement method takes a String (the name of the tag) and the component to which the tag corresponds (in this case, map). (Passing this information to the ResponseWriter instance helps design-time tools know which portions of the generated markup are related to which components.)

After calling startElement, you can call writeAttribute to render the tag's attributes. The writeAttribute method takes the name of the attribute, its value, and the name of a property or attribute of the containing component corresponding to the attribute. The last parameter can be null, and it won't be rendered.

The name attribute value of the map tag is retrieved using the getId method of UIComponent, which returns the component's unique identifier. The name attribute value of the input tag is retrieved using the getName(FacesContext, UIComponent) method of MapRenderer.

If you want your component to perform its own rendering but delegate to a renderer if there is one, include the following lines in the encoding method to check whether there is a renderer associated with this component:

if (getRendererType() != null) {
    super.encodeEnd(context);
    return;
}

If there is a renderer available, this method invokes the superclass's encodeEnd method, which does the work of finding the renderer. The MapComponent class delegates all rendering to MapRenderer, so it does not need to check for available renderers.

In some custom component classes that extend standard components, you might need to implement other methods in addition to encodeEnd. For example, if you need to retrieve the component's value from the request parameters, you must also implement the decode method.

15.4.3 Performing Decoding

During the Apply Request Values phase, the JavaServer Faces implementation processes the decode methods of all components in the tree. The decode method extracts a component's local value from incoming request parameters and uses a javax.faces.convert.Converter implementation to convert the value to a type that is acceptable to the component class.

A custom component class or its renderer must implement the decode method only if it must retrieve the local value or if it needs to queue events. The component queues the event by calling queueEvent.

Here is the decode method of MapRenderer:

@Override
public void decode(FacesContext context, UIComponent component) {
    if ((context == null) || (component == null)) {
        throw new NullPointerException();
    }
    MapComponent map = (MapComponent) component;
    String key = getName(context, map);
    String value = (String) context.getExternalContext().
            getRequestParameterMap().get(key);
    if (value != null)
        map.setCurrent(value);
    }
}

The decode method first gets the name of the hidden input field by calling getName(FacesContext, UIComponent). It then uses that name as the key to the request parameter map to retrieve the current value of the input field. This value represents the currently selected area. Finally, it sets the value of the MapComponent class's current attribute to the value of the input field.

15.4.4 Enabling Component Properties to Accept Expressions

Nearly all the attributes of the standard JavaServer Faces tags can accept expressions, whether they are value expressions or method expressions. It is recommended that you also enable your component attributes to accept expressions because it gives you much more flexibility when you write Facelets pages.

To enable the attributes to accept expressions, the component class must implement getter and setter methods for the component properties. These methods can use the facilities offered by the StateHelper interface to store and retrieve not only the values for these properties but also the state of the components across multiple requests.

Because MapComponent extends UICommand, the UICommand class already does the work of getting the ValueExpression and MethodExpression instances associated with each of the attributes that it supports. Similarly, the UIOutput class that AreaComponent extends already obtains the ValueExpression instances for its supported attributes. For both components, the simple getter and setter methods store and retrieve the key values and state for the attributes, as shown in this code fragment from AreaComponent:

enum PropertyKeys {
    alt, coords, shape, targetImage;
}
public String getAlt() {
    return (String) getStateHelper().eval(PropertyKeys.alt, null);
}
public void setAlt(String alt) {
    getStateHelper().put(PropertyKeys.alt, alt);
}
...

However, if you have a custom component class that extends UIComponentBase, you will need to implement the methods that get the ValueExpression and MethodExpression instances associated with those attributes that are enabled to accept expressions. For example, you could include a method that gets the ValueExpression instance for the immediate attribute:

public boolean isImmediate() {
    if (this.immediateSet) {
        return (this.immediate);
    }
    ValueExpression ve = getValueExpression("immediate");
    if (ve != null) {
        Boolean value = (Boolean) ve.getValue(
            getFacesContext().getELContext());
        return (value.booleanValue());
    } else {
        return (this.immediate);
    }
}

The properties corresponding to the component attributes that accept method expressions must accept and return a MethodExpression object. For example, if MapComponent extended UIComponentBase instead of UICommand, it would need to provide an action property that returns and accepts a MethodExpression object:

public MethodExpression getAction() {
    return (this.action);
}
public void setAction(MethodExpression action) {
    this.action = action;
}

15.4.5 Saving and Restoring State

As described in Enabling Component Properties to Accept Expressions, use of the StateHelper interface facilities allows you to save the component's state at the same time you set and retrieve property values. The StateHelper implementation allows partial state saving; it saves only the changes in the state since the initial request, not the entire state, because the full state can be restored during the Restore View phase.

Component classes that implement StateHolder may prefer to implement the saveState(FacesContext) and restoreState(FacesContext, Object) methods to help the JavaServer Faces implementation save and restore the state of components across multiple requests.

To save a set of values, you can implement the saveState(FacesContext) method. This method is called during the Render Response phase, during which the state of the response is saved for processing on subsequent requests. Here is a hypothetical method from MapComponent, which has only one attribute, current:

@Override
public Object saveState(FacesContext context) {
    Object values[] = new Object[2];
    values[0] = super.saveState(context);
    values[1] = current;
    return (values);
}

This method initializes an array, which will hold the saved state. It next saves all of the state associated with the component.

A component that implements StateHolder may also provide an implementation for restoreState(FacesContext, Object), which restores the state of the component to that saved with the saveState(FacesContext) method. The restoreState(FacesContext, Object) method is called during the Restore View phase, during which the JavaServer Faces implementation checks whether there is any state that was saved during the last Render Response phase and needs to be restored in preparation for the next postback.

Here is a hypothetical restoreState(FacesContext, Object) method from MapComponent:

public void restoreState(FacesContext context, Object state) {
    Object values[] = (Object[]) state;
    super.restoreState(context, values[0]);
    current = (String) values[1];
}

This method takes a FacesContext and an Object instance, representing the array that is holding the state for the component. This method sets the component's properties to the values saved in the Object array.

Whether or not you implement these methods in your component class, you can use the javax.faces.STATE_SAVING_METHOD context parameter to specify in the deployment descriptor where you want the state to be saved: either client or server. If state is saved on the client, the state of the entire view is rendered to a hidden field on the page. By default, the state is saved on the server.

The web applications in the Duke's Forest case study save their view state on the client.

Saving state on the client uses more bandwidth as well as more client resources, whereas saving it on the server uses more server resources. You may also want to save state on the client if you expect your users to disable cookies.

15.5 Delegating Rendering to a Renderer

Both MapComponent and AreaComponent delegate all of their rendering to a separate renderer. The section Performing Encoding explains how MapRenderer performs the encoding for MapComponent. This section explains in detail the process of delegating rendering to a renderer using AreaRenderer, which performs the rendering for AreaComponent.

To delegate rendering, you perform these tasks.

Create the Renderer class.

Register the renderer with a render kit by using the @FacesRenderer annotation (or by using the application configuration resource file, as explained in Registering a Custom Renderer with a Render Kit).

Identify the renderer type in the FacesRenderer annotation.

15.5.1 Creating the Renderer Class

When delegating rendering to a renderer, you can delegate all encoding and decoding to the renderer, or you can choose to do part of it in the component class. The AreaComponent class delegates encoding to the AreaRenderer class.

The renderer class begins with a @FacesRenderer annotation:

@FacesRenderer(componentFamily = "Area", rendererType = "DemoArea")
public class AreaRenderer extends Renderer {

The @FacesRenderer annotation registers the renderer class with the JavaServer Faces implementation as a renderer class. The annotation identifies the component family as well as the renderer type.

To perform the rendering for AreaComponent, AreaRenderer must implement an encodeEnd method. The encodeEnd method of AreaRenderer retrieves the shape, coordinates, and alternative text values stored in the ImageArea bean that is bound to AreaComponent. Suppose that the area tag currently being rendered has a value attribute value of "book203". The following line from encodeEnd gets the value of the attribute "book203" from the FacesContext instance:

ImageArea ia = (ImageArea)area.getValue();

The attribute value is the ImageArea bean instance, which contains the shape, coords, and alt values associated with the book203 AreaComponent instance. Configuring Model Data describes how the application stores these values.

After retrieving the ImageArea object, the method renders the values for shape, coords, and alt by simply calling the associated accessor methods and passing the returned values to the ResponseWriter instance, as shown by these lines of code, which write out the shape and coordinates:

writer.startElement("area", area);
writer.writeAttribute("alt", iarea.getAlt(), "alt");
writer.writeAttribute("coords", iarea.getCoords(), "coords");
writer.writeAttribute("shape", iarea.getShape(), "shape");

The encodeEnd method also renders the JavaScript for the onmouseout, onmouseover, and onclick attributes. The Facelets page needs to provide only the path to the images that are to be loaded during an onmouseover or onmouseout action:

<bookstore:area id="map3" value="#{Book203}" 
                onmouseover="resources/images/book_203.jpg" 
                onmouseout="resources/images/book_all.jpg" 
                targetImage="mapImage"/>

The AreaRenderer class takes care of generating the JavaScript for these actions, as shown in the following code from encodeEnd. The JavaScript that AreaRenderer generates for the onclick action sets the value of the hidden field to the value of the current area's component ID and submits the page.

sb = new StringBuffer("document.forms[0]['").append(targetImageId).
        append("'].src='");
sb.append(
        getURI(context,
        (String) area.getAttributes().get("onmouseout")));
sb.append("'");
writer.writeAttribute("onmouseout", sb.toString(), "onmouseout");
sb = new StringBuffer("document.forms[0]['").append(targetImageId).
        append("'].src='");
sb.append(
        getURI(context,
        (String) area.getAttributes().get("onmouseover")));
sb.append("'");
writer.writeAttribute("onmouseover", sb.toString(), "onmouseover");
sb = new StringBuffer("document.forms[0]['");
sb.append(getName(context, area));
sb.append("'].value='");
sb.append(iarea.getAlt());
sb.append("'; document.forms[0].submit()");
writer.writeAttribute("onclick", sb.toString(), "value");
writer.endElement("area");

By submitting the page, this code causes the JavaServer Faces lifecycle to return back to the Restore View phase. This phase saves any state information, including the value of the hidden field, so that a new request component tree is constructed. This value is retrieved by the decode method of the MapComponent class. This decode method is called by the JavaServer Faces implementation during the Apply Request Values phase, which follows the Restore View phase.

In addition to the encodeEnd method, AreaRenderer contains an empty constructor. This is used to create an instance of AreaRenderer so that it can be added to the render kit.

The @FacesRenderer annotation registers the renderer class with the JavaServer Faces implementation as a renderer class. The annotation identifies the component family as well as the renderer type.

15.5.2 Identifying the Renderer Type

During the Render Response phase, the JavaServer Faces implementation calls the getRendererType method of the component's tag handler to determine which renderer to invoke, if there is one.

You identify the type associated with the renderer in the rendererType element of the @FacesRenderer annotation for AreaRenderer as well as in the renderer-type element of the tag library descriptor.

15.6 Implementing an Event Listener

The JavaServer Faces technology supports action events and value-change events for components.

Action events occur when the user activates a component that implements javax.faces.component.ActionSource. These events are represented by the class javax.faces.event.ActionEvent.

Value-change events occur when the user changes the value of a component that implements javax.faces.component.EditableValueHolder. These events are represented by the class javax.faces.event.ValueChangeEvent.

One way to handle events is to implement the appropriate listener classes. Listener classes that handle the action events in an application must implement the interface javax.faces.event.ActionListener. Similarly, listeners that handle the value-change events must implement the interface javax.faces.event.ValueChangeListener.

This section explains how to implement the two listener classes.

To handle events generated by custom components, you must implement an event listener and an event handler and manually queue the event on the component. See Handling Events for Custom Components for more information.

Note:

You do not need to create an ActionListener implementation to handle an event that results solely in navigating to a page and does not perform any other application-specific processing. See Writing a Method to Handle Navigation for information on how to manage page navigation.

15.6.1 Implementing Value-Change Listeners

A javax.faces.event.ValueChangeListener implementation must include a processValueChange(ValueChangeEvent) method. This method processes the specified value-change event and is invoked by the JavaServer Faces implementation when the value-change event occurs. The ValueChangeEvent instance stores the old and the new values of the component that fired the event.

In the Duke's Bookstore case study, the NameChanged listener implementation is registered on the name UIInput component on the bookcashier.xhtml page. This listener stores into session scope the name the user entered in the field corresponding to the name component.

The bookreceipt.xhtml subsequently retrieves the name from the session scope:

<h:outputFormat title="thanks"
                value="#{bundle.ThankYouParam}">
    <f:param value="#{sessionScope.name}"/>
</h:outputFormat>

When the bookreceipt.xhtml page is loaded, it displays the name inside the message:

"Thank you, {0}, for purchasing your books from us."

Here is part of the NameChanged listener implementation:

public class NameChanged extends Object implements ValueChangeListener {

    @Override
    public void processValueChange(ValueChangeEvent event)
            throws AbortProcessingException {
    
        if (null != event.getNewValue()) {
            FacesContext.getCurrentInstance().getExternalContext().
                getSessionMap().put("name", event.getNewValue());
        }
    }
}

When the user enters the name in the field, a value-change event is generated, and the processValueChange(ValueChangeEvent) method of the NameChanged listener implementation is invoked. This method first gets the ID of the component that fired the event from the ValueChangeEvent object, and it puts the value, along with an attribute name, into the session map of the FacesContext instance.

Registering a Value-Change Listener on a Component explains how to register this listener onto a component.

15.6.2 Implementing Action Listeners

A javax.faces.event.ActionListener implementation must include a processAction(ActionEvent) method. The processAction(ActionEvent) method processes the specified action event. The JavaServer Faces implementation invokes the processAction(ActionEvent) method when the ActionEvent occurs.

The Duke's Bookstore case study uses two ActionListener implementations, LinkBookChangeListener and MapBookChangeListener. See Handling Events for Custom Components for details on MapBookChangeListener.

Registering an Action Listener on a Component explains how to register this listener onto a component.

15.7 Handling Events for Custom Components

As explained in Implementing an Event Listener, events are automatically queued on standard components that fire events. A custom component, on the other hand, must manually queue events from its decode method if it fires events.

Performing Decoding explains how to queue an event on MapComponent using its decode method. This section explains how to write the class that represents the event of clicking on the map and how to write the method that processes this event.

As explained in Understanding the Facelets Page, the actionListener attribute of the bookstore:map tag points to the MapBookChangeListener class. The listener class's processAction method processes the event of clicking the image map. Here is the processAction method:

@Override
public void processAction(ActionEvent actionEvent)
        throws AbortProcessingException {

    AreaSelectedEvent event = (AreaSelectedEvent) actionEvent;
    String current = event.getMapComponent().getCurrent();
    FacesContext context = FacesContext.getCurrentInstance();
    String bookId = books.get(current);
    context.getExternalContext().getSessionMap().put("bookId", bookId);
}

When the JavaServer Faces implementation calls this method, it passes in an ActionEvent object that represents the event generated by clicking on the image map. Next, it casts it to an AreaSelectedEvent object (see tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/src/java/dukesbookstore/listeners/AreaSelectedEvent.java). Then this method gets the MapComponent associated with the event. Next, it gets the value of the MapComponent object's current attribute, which indicates the currently selected area. The method then uses the value of the current attribute to get the book's ID value from a HashMap object, which is constructed elsewhere in the MapBookChangeListener class. Finally, the method places the ID obtained from the HashMap object into the session map for the application.

In addition to the method that processes the event, you need the event class itself. This class is very simple to write; you have it extend ActionEvent and provide a constructor that takes the component on which the event is queued and a method that returns the component. Here is the AreaSelectedEvent class used with the image map:

public class AreaSelectedEvent extends ActionEvent {
    public AreaSelectedEvent(MapComponent map) {
        super(map);
    }
    public MapComponent getMapComponent() {
        return ((MapComponent) getComponent());
    }
}

As explained in the section Creating Custom Component Classes, in order for MapComponent to fire events in the first place, it must implement ActionSource. Because MapComponent extends UICommand, it also implements ActionSource.

15.8 Defining the Custom Component Tag in a Tag Library Descriptor

To use a custom tag, you declare it in a Tag Library Descriptor (TLD). The TLD file defines how the custom tag is used in a JavaServer Faces page. The web container uses the TLD to validate the tag. The set of tags that are part of the HTML render kit are defined in the HTML_BASIC TLD, available at http://docs.oracle.com/javaee/7/javaserverfaces/2.2/renderkitdocs/.

The TLD file name must end with taglib.xml. In the Duke's Bookstore case study, the custom tags area and map are defined in the file web/WEB-INF/bookstore.taglib.xml.

All tag definitions must be nested inside the facelet-taglib element in the TLD. Each tag is defined by a tag element. Here are the tag definitions for the area and map components:

<facelet-taglib xmlns="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee"
...>
    <namespace>http://dukesbookstore</namespace>
    <tag>
        <tag-name>area</tag-name>
        <component>
            <component-type>DemoArea</component-type>
            <renderer-type>DemoArea</renderer-type>
        </component>
    </tag>
    <tag>
        <tag-name>map</tag-name>
        <component>
            <component-type>DemoMap</component-type>
            <renderer-type>DemoMap</renderer-type>
        </component>
    </tag>
</facelet-taglib>

The component-type element specifies the name defined in the @FacesComponent annotation, and the renderer-type element specifies the rendererType defined in the @FacesRenderer annotation.

The facelet-taglib element must also include a namespace element, which defines the namespace to be specified in pages that use the custom component. See Using a Custom Component for information on specifying the namespace in pages.

The TLD file is located in the WEB-INF directory. In addition, an entry is included in the web deployment descriptor (web.xml) to identify the custom tag library descriptor file, as follows:

    <context-param>
        <param-name>javax.faces.FACELETS_LIBRARIES</param-name>
        <param-value>/WEB-INF/bookstore.taglib.xml</param-value>
    </context-param>

15.9 Using a Custom Component

To use a custom component in a page, you add the custom tag associated with the component to the page.

As explained in Defining the Custom Component Tag in a Tag Library Descriptor, you must ensure that the TLD that defines any custom tags is packaged in the application if you intend to use the tags in your pages. TLD files are stored in the WEB-INF/ directory or subdirectory of the WAR file or in the META-INF/ directory or subdirectory of a tag library packaged in a JAR file.

You also need to include a namespace declaration in the page so that the page has access to the tags. The custom tags for the Duke's Bookstore case study are defined in bookstore.taglib.xml. The ui:composition tag on the index.xhtml page declares the namespace defined in the tag library:

<ui:composition xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
                xmlns:ui="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/facelets"
                xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html"
                xmlns:f="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/core"
                xmlns:bookstore="http://dukesbookstore"
                template="./bookstoreTemplate.xhtml">

Finally, to use a custom component in a page, you add the component's tag to the page.

The Duke's Bookstore case study includes a custom image map component on the index.xhtml page. This component allows you to select a book by clicking on a region of the image map:

...
<h:graphicImage id="mapImage"
                name="book_all.jpg"
                library="images
                alt="#{bundle.chooseLocale}"
                usemap="#bookMap" />
<bookstore:map id="bookMap"
               current="map1"
               immediate="true"
               action="bookstore">
    <f:actionListener
        type="javaeetutorial.dukesbookstore.listeners.MapBookChangeListener" />
    <bookstore:area id="map1" value="#{Book201}" 
                    onmouseover="resources/images/book_201.jpg" 
                    onmouseout="resources/images/book_all.jpg" 
                    targetImage="mapImage" />
    ...
    <bookstore:area id="map6" value="#{Book207}" 
                    onmouseover="resources/images/book_207.jpg" 
                    onmouseout="resources/images//book_all.jpg" 
                    targetImage="mapImage" />
</bookstore:map>

The standard h:graphicImage tag associates an image (book_all.jpg) with an image map that is referenced in the usemap attribute value.

The custom bookstore:map tag that represents the custom component, MapComponent, specifies the image map and contains a set of bookstore:area tags. Each custom bookstore:area tag represents a custom AreaComponent and specifies a region of the image map.

On the page, the onmouseover and onmouseout attributes specify the image that is displayed when the user performs the actions described by the attributes. The custom renderer also renders an onclick attribute.

In the rendered HTML page, the onmouseover, onmouseout, and onclick attributes define which JavaScript code is executed when these events occur. When the user moves the mouse over a region, the onmouseover function associated with the region displays the map with that region highlighted. When the user moves the mouse out of a region, the onmouseout function redisplays the original image. When the user clicks a region, the onclick function sets the value of a hidden input tag to the ID of the selected area and submits the page.

When the custom renderer renders these attributes in HTML, it also renders the JavaScript code. The custom renderer also renders the entire onclick attribute rather than letting the page author set it.

The custom renderer that renders the HTML map tag also renders a hidden input component that holds the current area. The server-side objects retrieve the value of the hidden input field and set the locale in the FacesContext instance according to which region was selected.

15.10 Creating and Using a Custom Converter

A JavaServer Faces converter class converts strings to objects and objects to strings as required. Several standard converters are provided by JavaServer Faces for this purpose. See Using the Standard Converters for more information on these included converters.

As explained in Conversion Model, if the standard converters included with JavaServer Faces cannot perform the data conversion that you need, you can create a custom converter to perform this specialized conversion. This implementation, at a minimum, must define how to convert data both ways between the two views of the data described in Conversion Model.

All custom converters must implement the javax.faces.convert.Converter interface. This section explains how to implement this interface to perform a custom data conversion.

The Duke's Bookstore case study uses a custom Converter implementation, located in tut-install/examples/case-studies/dukes-bookstore/src/java/dukesbookstore/converters/CreditCardConverter.java, to convert the data entered in the Credit Card Number field on the bookcashier.xhtml page. It strips blanks and hyphens from the text string and formats it so that a blank space separates every four characters.

Another common use case for a custom converter is in a list for a nonstandard object type. In the Duke's Tutoring case study, the Student and Guardian entities require a custom converter so that they can be converted to and from a UISelectItems input component.

15.10.1 Creating a Custom Converter

The CreditCardConverter custom converter class is created as follows:

@FacesConverter("ccno")
public class CreditCardConverter implements Converter {
    ...
}

The @FacesConverter annotation registers the custom converter class as a converter with the name of ccno with the JavaServer Faces implementation. Alternatively, you can register the converter with entries in the application configuration resource file, as shown in Registering a Custom Converter.

To define how the data is converted from the presentation view to the model view, the Converter implementation must implement the getAsObject(FacesContext, UIComponent, String) method from the Converter interface. Here is the implementation of this method from CreditCardConverter:

@Override
public Object getAsObject(FacesContext context,
        UIComponent component, String newValue)
        throws ConverterException {

    if (newValue.isEmpty()) {
        return null;
    }
    // Since this is only a String to String conversion,
    // this conversion does not throw ConverterException.
    
    String convertedValue = newValue.trim();
    if ( (convertedValue.contains("-")) || (convertedValue.contains(" "))) {
        char[] input = convertedValue.toCharArray();
        StringBuilder builder = new StringBuilder(input.length);
        for (int i = 0; i < input.length; ++i) {
            if ((input[i] == '-') || (input[i] == ' ')) {
            } else {
                builder.append(input[i]);
            }
        }
        convertedValue = builder.toString();
    }
    return convertedValue;
}

During the Apply Request Values phase, when the components' decode methods are processed, the JavaServer Faces implementation looks up the component's local value in the request and calls the getAsObject method. When calling this method, the JavaServer Faces implementation passes in the current FacesContext instance, the component whose data needs conversion, and the local value as a String. The method then writes the local value to a character array, trims the hyphens and blanks, adds the rest of the characters to a String, and returns the String.

To define how the data is converted from the model view to the presentation view, the Converter implementation must implement the getAsString(FacesContext, UIComponent, Object) method from the Converter interface. Here is an implementation of this method:

@Override
public String getAsString(FacesContext context,
        UIComponent component, Object value)
        throws ConverterException {
    
    String inputVal = null;
    if ( value == null ) {
        return "";
    }
    // value must be of a type that can be cast to a String.
    try {
        inputVal = (String)value;
    } catch (ClassCastException ce) {
        FacesMessage errMsg = new FacesMessage(CONVERSION_ERROR_MESSAGE_ID);
        FacesContext.getCurrentInstance().addMessage(null, errMsg);
        throw new ConverterException(errMsg.getSummary());
    }
    // insert spaces after every four characters for better
    // readability if they are not already present.
    char[] input = inputVal.toCharArray();
    StringBuilder builder = new StringBuilder(input.length + 3);
    for (int i = 0; i < input.length; ++i) {
        if ((i % 4) == 0 && (i != 0)) {
            if ({input[i] != ' ') || (input[i] != '-')){
                builder.append(" ");
                // if there are any "-"'s convert them to blanks.
            } else if (input[i] == '-') {
                builder.append(" ");
            }
         }
         builder.append(input[i]);
    }
    String convertedValue = builder.toString();
    return convertedValue;
}

During the Render Response phase, in which the components' encode methods are called, the JavaServer Faces implementation calls the getAsString method in order to generate the appropriate output. When the JavaServer Faces implementation calls this method, it passes in the current FacesContext, the UIComponent whose value needs to be converted, and the bean value to be converted. Because this converter does a String-to-String conversion, this method can cast the bean value to a String.

If the value cannot be converted to a String, the method throws an exception, passing an error message from the resource bundle that is registered with the application. Registering Application Messages explains how to register custom error messages with the application.

If the value can be converted to a String, the method reads the String to a character array and loops through the array, adding a space after every four characters.

You can also create a custom converter with a @FacesConverter annotation that specifies the forClass attribute, as shown in the following example from the Duke's Tutoring case study:

@FacesConverter(forClass=Guardian.class, value="guardian")
public class GuardianConverter extends EntityConverter implements Converter { ...

The forClass attribute registers the converter as the default converter for the Guardian class. Therefore, whenever that class is specified by a value attribute of an input component, the converter is invoked automatically.

A converter class can be a separate Java POJO class, as in the Duke's Bookstore case study. If it needs to access objects defined in a managed bean class, however, it can be a subclass of a JavaServer Faces managed bean, as in the address-book persistence example, in which the converters use an enterprise bean that is injected into the managed bean class.

15.10.2 Using a Custom Converter

To apply the data conversion performed by a custom converter to a particular component's value, you must do one of the following.

Reference the converter from the component tag's converter attribute.

Nest an f:converter tag inside the component's tag and reference the custom converter from one of the f:converter tag's attributes.

If you are using the component tag's converter attribute, this attribute must reference the Converter implementation's identifier or the fully-qualified class name of the converter. Creating and Using a Custom Converter explains how to implement a custom converter.

The identifier for the credit card converter class is ccno, the value specified in the @FacesConverter annotation:

@FacesConverter("ccno")
public class CreditCardConverter implements Converter {
    ...

Therefore, the CreditCardConverter instance can be registered on the ccno component as shown in the following example:

<h:inputText id="ccno"
             size="19"
             converter="ccno"
             value="#{cashierBean.creditCardNumber}"
             required="true"
             requiredMessage="#{bundle.ReqCreditCard}">
    ...
</h:inputText>

By setting the converter attribute of a component's tag to the converter's identifier or its class name, you cause that component's local value to be automatically converted according to the rules specified in the Converter implementation.

Instead of referencing the converter from the component tag's converter attribute, you can reference the converter from an f:converter tag nested inside the component's tag. To reference the custom converter using the f:converter tag, you do one of the following.

Set the f:converter tag's converterId attribute to the Converter implementation's identifier defined in the @FacesConverter annotation or in the application configuration resource file. This method is shown in bookcashier.xhtml:

<h:inputText id="ccno" 
             size="19"
             value="#{cashierBean.creditCardNumber}"
             required="true"
             requiredMessage="#{bundle.ReqCreditCard}">
    <f:converter converterId="ccno"/>
    <f:validateRegex 
       pattern="\d{16}|\d{4} \d{4} \d{4} \d{4}|\d{4}-\d{4}-\d{4}-\d{4}"/>
</h:inputText>

Bind the Converter implementation to a managed bean property using the f:converter tag's binding attribute, as described in Binding Converters, Listeners, and Validators to Managed Bean Properties.

The JavaServer Faces implementation calls the converter's getAsObject method to strip spaces and hyphens from the input value. The getAsString method is called when the bookcashier.xhtml page is redisplayed; this happens if the user orders more than $100 worth of books.

In the Duke's Tutoring case study, each converter is registered as the converter for a particular class. The converter is automatically invoked whenever that class is specified by a value attribute of an input component. In the following example, the itemValue attribute (highlighted in bold) calls the converter for the Guardian class:

<h:selectManyListbox id="selectGuardiansMenu"
                     title="#{bundle['action.add.guardian']}"
                     value="#{guardianManager.selectedGuardians}"
                     size="5"
                     converter="guardian">
    <f:selectItems value="#{guardianManager.allGuardians}"
                   var="selectedGuardian"
                   itemLabel="#{selectedGuardian.name}"
                   itemValue="#{selectedGuardian}" />
</h:selectManyListbox>

15.11 Creating and Using a Custom Validator

If the standard validators or Bean Validation don't perform the validation checking you need, you can create a custom validator to validate user input. As explained in Validation Model, there are two ways to implement validation code.

Implement a managed bean method that performs the validation.

Provide an implementation of the javax.faces.validator.Validator interface to perform the validation.

Writing a Method to Perform Validation explains how to implement a managed bean method to perform validation. The rest of this section explains how to implement the Validator interface.

If you choose to implement the Validator interface and you want to allow the page author to configure the validator's attributes from the page, you also must specify a custom tag for registering the validator on a component.

If you prefer to configure the attributes in the Validator implementation, you can forgo specifying a custom tag and instead let the page author register the validator on a component using the f:validator tag, as described in Using a Custom Validator.

You can also create a managed bean property that accepts and returns the Validator implementation you create, as described in Writing Properties Bound to Converters, Listeners, or Validators. You can use the f:validator tag's binding attribute to bind the Validator implementation to the managed bean property.

Usually, you will want to display an error message when data fails validation. You need to store these error messages in a resource bundle.

After creating the resource bundle, you have two ways to make the messages available to the application. You can queue the error messages onto the FacesContext programmatically, or you can register the error messages in the application configuration resource file, as explained in Registering Application Messages.

For example, an e-commerce application might use a general-purpose custom validator called FormatValidator.java to validate input data against a format pattern that is specified in the custom validator tag. This validator would be used with a Credit Card Number field on a Facelets page. Here is the custom validator tag:

<mystore:formatValidator
 formatPatterns="9999999999999999|9999 9999 9999 9999|9999-9999-9999-9999"/>

According to this validator, the data entered in the field must be one of the following:

A 16-digit number with no spaces

A 16-digit number with a space between every four digits

A 16-digit number with hyphens between every four digits

The f:validateRegex tag makes a custom validator unnecessary in this situation. However, the rest of this section describes how this validator would be implemented and how to specify a custom tag so that the page author could register the validator on a component.

15.11.1 Implementing the Validator Interface

A Validator implementation must contain a constructor, a set of accessor methods for any attributes on the tag, and a validate method, which overrides the validate method of the Validator interface.

The hypothetical FormatValidator class also defines accessor methods for setting the formatPatterns attribute, which specifies the acceptable format patterns for input into the fields. The setter method calls the parseFormatPatterns method, which separates the components of the pattern string into a string array, formatPatternsList.

public String getFormatPatterns() {
    return (this.formatPatterns);
}
public void setFormatPatterns(String formatPatterns) {
    this.formatPatterns = formatPatterns;
    parseFormatPatterns();
}

In addition to defining accessor methods for the attributes, the class overrides the validate method of the Validator interface. This method validates the input and also accesses the custom error messages to be displayed when the String is invalid.

The validate method performs the actual validation of the data. It takes the FacesContext instance, the component whose data needs to be validated, and the value that needs to be validated. A validator can validate only data of a component that implements javax.faces.component.EditableValueHolder.

Here is an implementation of the validate method:

@FacesValidator
public class FormatValidator implements Validator, StateHolder {
    ...
    public void validate(FacesContext context, UIComponent component, 
                         Object toValidate) {

        boolean valid = false;
        String value = null;
        if ((context == null) || (component == null)) {
            throw new NullPointerException();
        }
        if (!(component instanceof UIInput)) {
            return;
        }
        if ( null == formatPatternsList || null == toValidate) {
            return;
        }
        value = toValidate.toString();
        // validate the value against the list of valid patterns.
        Iterator patternIt = formatPatternsList.iterator();
        while (patternIt.hasNext()) {
            valid = isFormatValid(
                ((String)patternIt.next()), value);
            if (valid) {
                break;
            }
        }
        if ( !valid ) {
            FacesMessage errMsg =
                new FacesMessage(FORMAT_INVALID_MESSAGE_ID);
            FacesContext.getCurrentInstance().addMessage(null, errMsg);
            throw new ValidatorException(errMsg);
        }
    }
}

The @FacesValidator annotation registers the FormatValidator class as a validator with the JavaServer Faces implementation. The validate method gets the local value of the component and converts it to a String. It then iterates over the formatPatternsList list, which is the list of acceptable patterns that was parsed from the formatPatterns attribute of the custom validator tag.

While iterating over the list, this method checks the pattern of the component's local value against the patterns in the list. If the pattern of the local value does not match any pattern in the list, this method generates an error message. It then creates a javax.faces.application.FacesMessage and queues it on the FacesContext for display, using a String that represents the key in the Properties file:

public static final String FORMAT_INVALID_MESSAGE_ID =
     "FormatInvalid";
}

Finally, the method passes the message to the constructor of javax.faces.validator.ValidatorException.

When the error message is displayed, the format pattern will be substituted for the {0} in the error message, which, in English, is as follows:

Input must match one of the following patterns: {0}

You may wish to save and restore state for your validator, although state saving is not usually necessary. To do so, you will need to implement the StateHolder interface as well as the Validator interface. To implement StateHolder, you would need to implement its four methods: saveState(FacesContext), restoreState(FacesContext, Object), isTransient, and setTransient(boolean). See Saving and Restoring State for more information.

15.11.2 Specifying a Custom Tag

If you implemented a Validator interface rather than implementing a managed bean method that performs the validation, you need to do one of the following.

Allow the page author to specify the Validator implementation to use with the f:validator tag. In this case, the Validator implementation must define its own properties. Using a Custom Validator explains how to use the f:validator tag.

Specify a custom tag that provides attributes for configuring the properties of the validator from the page.

To create a custom tag, you need to add the tag to the tag library descriptor for the application, bookstore.taglib.xml:

<tag>
    <tag-name>validator</tag-name>
    <validator>
        <validator-id>formatValidator</validator-id>
        <validator-class>
            dukesbookstore.validators.FormatValidator
        </validator-class>
    </validator>
</tag>

The tag-name element defines the name of the tag as it must be used in a Facelets page. The validator-id element identifies the custom validator. The validator-class element wires the custom tag to its implementation class.

Using a Custom Validator explains how to use the custom validator tag on the page.

15.11.3 Using a Custom Validator

To register a custom validator on a component, you must do one of the following.

Nest the validator's custom tag inside the tag of the component whose value you want to be validated.

Nest the standard f:validator tag within the tag of the component and reference the custom Validator implementation from the f:validator tag.

Here is a hypothetical custom formatValidator tag for the Credit Card Number field, nested within the h:inputText tag:

<h:inputText id="ccno" size="19"
  ...
  required="true">
  <mystore:formatValidator
  formatPatterns="9999999999999999|9999 9999 9999 9999|9999-9999-9999-9999"/>
</h:inputText>
<h:message styleClass="validationMessage" for="ccno"/>

This tag validates the input of the ccno field against the patterns defined by the page author in the formatPatterns attribute.

You can use the same custom validator for any similar component by simply nesting the custom validator tag within the component tag.

If the application developer who created the custom validator prefers to configure the attributes in the Validator implementation rather than allow the page author to configure the attributes from the page, the developer will not create a custom tag for use with the validator.

In this case, the page author must nest the f:validator tag inside the tag of the component whose data needs to be validated. Then the page author needs to do one of the following.

Set the f:validator tag's validatorId attribute to the ID of the validator that is defined in the application configuration resource file.

Bind the custom Validator implementation to a managed bean property using the f:validator tag's binding attribute, as described in Binding Converters, Listeners, and Validators to Managed Bean Properties.

The following tag registers a hypothetical validator on a component using an f:validator tag and references the ID of the validator:

<h:inputText id="name" value="#{CustomerBean.name}"
            size="10" ...>
    <f:validator validatorId="customValidator" />
    ...
</h:inputText>

15.12 Binding Component Values and Instances to Managed Bean Properties

A component tag can wire its data to a managed bean by one of the following methods:

Binding its component's value to a bean property

Binding its component's instance to a bean property

To bind a component's value to a managed bean property, a component tag's value attribute uses an EL value expression. To bind a component instance to a bean property, a component tag's binding attribute uses a value expression.

When a component instance is bound to a managed bean property, the property holds the component's local value. Conversely, when a component's value is bound to a managed bean property, the property holds the value stored in the managed bean. This value is updated with the local value during the Update Model Values phase of the lifecycle. There are advantages to both of these methods.

Binding a component instance to a bean property has the following advantages.

The managed bean can programmatically modify component attributes.

The managed bean can instantiate components rather than let the page author do so.

Binding a component's value to a bean property has the following advantages.

The page author has more control over the component attributes.

The managed bean has no dependencies on the JavaServer Faces API (such as the component classes), allowing for greater separation of the presentation layer from the model layer.

The JavaServer Faces implementation can perform conversions on the data based on the type of the bean property without the developer needing to apply a converter.

In most situations, you will bind a component's value rather than its instance to a bean property. You'll need to use a component binding only when you need to change one of the component's attributes dynamically. For example, if an application renders a component only under certain conditions, it can set the component's rendered property accordingly by accessing the property to which the component is bound.

When referencing the property using the component tag's value attribute, you need to use the proper syntax. For example, suppose a managed bean called MyBean has this int property:

protected int currentOption = null;
public int getCurrentOption(){...}
public void setCurrentOption(int option){...}

The value attribute that references this property must have this value-binding expression:

#{myBean.currentOption}

In addition to binding a component's value to a bean property, the value attribute can specify a literal value or can map the component's data to any primitive (such as int), structure (such as an array), or collection (such as a list), independent of a JavaBeans component. Table 15-3 lists some example value-binding expressions that you can use with the value attribute.

Table 15-3 Examples of Value-Binding Expressions

Value | Expression

A Boolean

|

cart.numberOfItems> 0

A property initialized from a context initialization parameter

|

initParam.quantity

A bean property

|

cashierBean.name

A value in an array

|

books[3]

A value in a collection

|

books["fiction"]

A property of an object in an array of objects

|

books[3].price

The next two sections explain how to use the value attribute to bind a component's value to a bean property or other data objects and how to use the binding attribute to bind a component instance to a bean property.

15.12.1 Binding a Component Value to a Property

To bind a component's value to a managed bean property, you specify the name of the bean and the property using the value attribute.

This means that the first part of the EL value expression must match the name of the managed bean up to the first period (.) and the part of the value expression after the period must match the property of the managed bean.

For example, in the Duke's Bookstore case study, the h:dataTable tag in bookcatalog.xhtml sets the value of the component to the value of the books property of the BookstoreBean backing bean, whose name is store:

<h:dataTable id="books"
             value="#{store.books}"
             var="book"
             headerClass="list-header"
             styleClass="list-background"
             rowClasses="list-row-even, list-row-odd"
             border="1" 
             summary="#{bundle.BookCatalog}">

The value is obtained by calling the backing bean's getBooks method, which in turn calls the BookRequestBean session bean's getBooks method.

If you use the application configuration resource file to configure managed beans instead of defining them in managed bean classes, the name of the bean in the value expression must match the managed-bean-name element of the managed bean declaration up to the first period (.) in the expression. Similarly, the part of the value expression after the period must match the name specified in the corresponding property-name element in the application configuration resource file.

For example, consider this managed bean configuration, which configures the ImageArea bean corresponding to the top-left book in the image map on the index.html page of the Duke's Bookstore case study:

<managed-bean eager="true">
    ...
    <managed-bean-name>Book201</managed-bean-name>
    <managed-bean-class>dukesbookstore.model.ImageArea</managed-bean-class>
    <managed-bean-scope>application</managed-bean-scope>
    <managed-property>
        ...
        <property-name>shape</property-name>
        <value>rect</value>
    </managed-property>
    <managed-property>
        ...
        <property-name>alt</property-name>
        <value>Duke</value>
    </managed-property>
    ...

This example configures a bean called Book201, which has several properties, one of which is called shape.

Although the bookstore:area tags on the index.xhtml page do not bind to an ImageArea property (they bind to the bean itself), you could refer to the property using a value expression from the value attribute of the component's tag:

<h:outputText value="#{Book201.shape}" />

See Configuring Managed Beans for information on how to configure beans in the application configuration resource file.

15.12.2 Binding a Component Value to an Implicit Object

One external data source that a value attribute can refer to is an implicit object.

The bookreceipt.xhtml page of the Duke's Bookstore case study has a reference to an implicit object:

<h:outputFormat title="thanks" 
                value="#{bundle.ThankYouParam}">
    <f:param value="#{sessionScope.name}"/>
</h:outputFormat>

This tag gets the name of the customer from the session scope and inserts it into the parameterized message at the key ThankYouParam from the resource bundle. For example, if the name of the customer is Gwen Canigetit, this tag will render:

Thank you, Gwen Canigetit, for purchasing your books from us.

Retrieving values from other implicit objects is done in a similar way to the example shown in this section. Table 15-4 lists the implicit objects to which a value attribute can refer. All of the implicit objects, except for the scope objects, are read-only and therefore should not be used as values for a UIInput component.

Table 15-4 Implicit Objects

Implicit Object | What It Is

applicationScope

|

A Map of the application scope attribute values, keyed by attribute name

cookie

|

A Map of the cookie values for the current request, keyed by cookie name

facesContext

|

The FacesContext instance for the current request

header

|

A Map of HTTP header values for the current request, keyed by header name

headerValues

|

A Map of String arrays containing all the header values for HTTP headers in the current request, keyed by header name

initParam

|

A Map of the context initialization parameters for this web application

param

|

A Map of the request parameters for this request, keyed by parameter name

paramValues

|

A Map of String arrays containing all the parameter values for request parameters in the current request, keyed by parameter name

requestScope

|

A Map of the request attributes for this request, keyed by attribute name

sessionScope

|

A Map of the session attributes for this request, keyed by attribute name

view

|

The root UIComponent in the current component tree stored in the FacesRequest for this request

15.12.3 Binding a Component Instance to a Bean Property

A component instance can be bound to a bean property using a value expression with the binding attribute of the component's tag. You usually bind a component instance rather than its value to a bean property if the bean must dynamically change the component's attributes.

Here are two tags from the bookcashier.xhtml page that bind components to bean properties:

<h:selectBooleanCheckbox id="fanClub" 
                         rendered="false"
                         binding="#{cashierBean.specialOffer}" />
<h:outputLabel for="fanClub"
               rendered="false"
               binding="#{cashierBean.specialOfferText}"
               value="#{bundle.DukeFanClub}"/>
</h:outputLabel>

The h:selectBooleanCheckbox tag renders a check box and binds the fanClub UISelectBoolean component to the specialOffer property of the cashier bean. The h:outputLabel tag binds the component representing the check box's label to the specialOfferText property of the cashier bean. If the application's locale is English, the h:outputLabel tag renders

I'd like to join the Duke Fan Club, free with my purchase of over $100

The rendered attributes of both tags are set to false to prevent the check box and its label from being rendered. If the customer makes a large order and clicks the Submit button, the submit method of CashierBean sets both components' rendered properties to true, causing the check box and its label to be rendered.

These tags use component bindings rather than value bindings because the managed bean must dynamically set the values of the components' rendered properties.

If the tags were to use value bindings instead of component bindings, the managed bean would not have direct access to the components and would therefore require additional code to access the components from the FacesContext instance to change the components' rendered properties.

Writing Properties Bound to Component Instances explains how to write the bean properties bound to the example components.

15.13 Binding Converters, Listeners, and Validators to Managed Bean Properties

As described in Adding Components to a Page Using HTML Tag Library Tags, a page author can bind converter, listener, and validator implementations to managed bean properties using the binding attributes of the tags that are used to register the implementations on components.

This technique has similar advantages to binding component instances to managed bean properties, as described in Binding Component Values and Instances to Managed Bean Properties. In particular, binding a converter, listener, or validator implementation to a managed bean property yields the following benefits.

The managed bean can instantiate the implementation instead of allowing the page author to do so.

The managed bean can programmatically modify the attributes of the implementation. In the case of a custom implementation, the only other way to modify the attributes outside of the implementation class would be to create a custom tag for it and require the page author to set the attribute values from the page.

Whether you are binding a converter, listener, or validator to a managed bean property, the process is the same for any of the implementations.

Nest the converter, listener, or validator tag within an appropriate component tag.

Make sure that the managed bean has a property that accepts and returns the converter, listener, or validator implementation class that you want to bind to the property.

Reference the managed bean property using a value expression from the binding attribute of the converter, listener, or validator tag.

For example, say that you want to bind the standard DateTime converter to a managed bean property because you want to set the formatting pattern of the user's input in the managed bean rather than on the Facelets page. First, the page registers the converter onto the component by nesting the f:convertDateTime tag within the component tag. Then, the page references the property with the binding attribute of the f:convertDateTime tag:

<h:inputText value="#{loginBean.birthDate}">
    <f:convertDateTime binding="#{loginBean.convertDate}" />
</h:inputText>

The convertDate property would look something like this:

private DateTimeConverter convertDate;
public DateTimeConverter getConvertDate() {
    ...
    return convertDate;
}
public void setConvertDate(DateTimeConverter convertDate) {
    convertDate.setPattern("EEEEEEEE, MMM dd, yyyy");
    this.convertDate = convertDate;
}

See Writing Properties Bound to Converters, Listeners, or Validators for more information on writing managed bean properties for converter, listener, and validator implementations.

9 Expression Language

This chapter introduces the Expression Language (also referred to as the EL), which provides an important mechanism for enabling the presentation layer (web pages) to communicate with the application logic (managed beans). The EL is used by several JavaEE technologies, such as JavaServer Faces technology, JavaServer Pages (JSP) technology, and Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE (CDI). The EL can also be used in stand-alone environments. This chapter only covers the use of the EL in Java EE containers.

The following topics are addressed here:

Overview of the EL

Immediate and Deferred Evaluation Syntax

Value and Method Expressions

Operations on Collection Objects

Operators

Reserved Words

Examples of EL Expressions

Further Information about the Expression Language

9.1 Overview of the EL

The EL allows page authors to use simple expressions to dynamically access data from JavaBeans components. For example, the test attribute of the following conditional tag is supplied with an EL expression that compares 0 with the number of items in the session-scoped bean named cart.

<c:if test="${sessionScope.cart.numberOfItems > 0}">
  ...
</c:if>

See Using the EL to Reference Managed Beans for more information on how to use the EL in JavaServer Faces applications.

To summarize, the EL provides a way to use simple expressions to perform the following tasks:

Dynamically read application data stored in JavaBeans components, various data structures, and implicit objects

Dynamically write data, such as user input into forms, to JavaBeans components

Invoke arbitrary static and public methods

Dynamically perform arithmetic, boolean, and string operations

Dynamically construct collection objects and perform operations on collections

In a JavaServer Faces page, an EL expression can be used either in static text or in the attribute of a custom tag or standard action.

Finally, the EL provides a pluggable API for resolving expressions so that custom resolvers that can handle expressions not already supported by the EL can be implemented.

9.2 Immediate and Deferred Evaluation Syntax

The EL supports both immediate and deferred evaluation of expressions. Immediate evaluation means that the expression is evaluated and the result returned as soon as the page is first rendered. Deferred evaluation means that the technology using the expression language can use its own machinery to evaluate the expression sometime later during the page's lifecycle, whenever it is appropriate to do so.

Those expressions that are evaluated immediately use the ${} syntax. Expressions whose evaluation is deferred use the #{} syntax.

Because of its multiphase lifecycle, JavaServer Faces technology uses mostly deferred evaluation expressions. During the lifecycle, component events are handled, data is validated, and other tasks are performed in a particular order. Therefore, a JavaServer Faces implementation must defer evaluation of expressions until the appropriate point in the lifecycle.

Other technologies using the EL might have different reasons for using deferred expressions.

9.2.1 Immediate Evaluation

All expressions using the ${} syntax are evaluated immediately. These expressions can appear as part of a template (static) text or as the value of a tag attribute that can accept runtime expressions.

The following example shows a tag whose value attribute references an immediate evaluation expression that updates the quantity of books retrieved from the backing bean named catalog:

<h:outputText value="${catalog.bookQuantity}" />

The JavaServer Faces implementation evaluates the expression ${catalog.bookQuantity}, converts it, and passes the returned value to the tag handler. The value is updated on the page.

9.2.2 Deferred Evaluation

Deferred evaluation expressions take the form #{expr} and can be evaluated at other phases of a page lifecycle as defined by whatever technology is using the expression. In the case of JavaServer Faces technology, its controller can evaluate the expression at different phases of the lifecycle, depending on how the expression is being used in the page.

The following example shows a JavaServer Faces h:inputText tag, which represents a field component into which a user enters a value. The h:inputText tag's value attribute references a deferred evaluation expression that points to the name property of the customer bean:

<h:inputText id="name" value="#{customer.name}" />

For an initial request of the page containing this tag, the JavaServer Faces implementation evaluates the #{customer.name} expression during the render-response phase of the lifecycle. During this phase, the expression merely accesses the value of name from the customer bean, as is done in immediate evaluation.

For a postback request, the JavaServer Faces implementation evaluates the expression at different phases of the lifecycle, during which the value is retrieved from the request, validated, and propagated to the customer bean.

As shown in this example, deferred evaluation expressions can be

Value expressions that can be used to both read and write data

Method expressions

Value expressions (both immediate and deferred) and method expressions are explained in the next section.

9.3 Value and Method Expressions

The EL defines two kinds of expressions: value expressions and method expressions. Value expressions can be evaluated to yield a value, and method expressions are used to reference a method.

9.3.1 Value Expressions

Value expressions can be further categorized into rvalue and lvalue expressions. An lvalue expression can specify a target, such as an object, a bean property, or elements of a collection, that can be assigned a value. An rvalue expression cannot specify such a target.

All expressions that are evaluated immediately use the ${} delimiters, and although the expression can be an lvalue expression, no assignments will ever happen. Expressions whose evaluation can be deferred use the #{} delimiters and can act as both rvalue and lvalue expressions; if the expression is an lvalue expression, it can be assigned a new value. Consider the following two value expressions:

${customer.name}

#{customer.name}

The former uses immediate evaluation syntax, whereas the latter uses deferred evaluation syntax. The first expression accesses the name property, gets its value, and passes the value to the tag handler. With the second expression, the tag handler can defer the expression evaluation to a later time in the page lifecycle if the technology using this tag allows.

In the case of JavaServer Faces technology, the latter tag's expression is evaluated immediately during an initial request for the page. During a postback request, this expression can be used to set the value of the name property with user input.

9.3.1.1 Referencing Objects

A top-level identifier (such as customer in the expression customer.name) can refer to the following objects:

Lambda parameters

EL variables

Managed beans

Implicit objects

Classes of static fields and methods

To refer to these objects, you write an expression using a variable that is the name of the object. The following expression references a managed bean called customer:

${customer}

You can use a custom EL resolver to alter the way variables are resolved. For instance, you can provide an EL resolver that intercepts objects with the name customer, so that ${customer} returns a value in the EL resolver instead. (JavaServer Faces technology uses an EL resolver to handle managed beans.)

An enum constant is a special case of a static field, and you can reference such a constant directly. For example, consider this enum class:

public enum Suit {hearts, spades, diamonds, clubs}

In the following expression, in which mySuit is an instance of Suit, you can compare suit.hearts to the instance:

${mySuit == suit.hearts}

9.3.1.2 Referencing Object Properties or Collection Elements

To refer to properties of a bean, static fields or methods of a class, or items of a collection, you use the . or [] notation. The same syntax can be used for attributes of an implicit object, because attributes are placed in a map.

To reference the name property of the customer bean, use either the expression ${customer.name} or the expression ${customer["name"]}. Here, the part inside the brackets is a String literal that is the name of the property to reference. The [] syntax is more general than the . syntax, because the part inside the brackets can be any String expression, not just literals.

You can use double or single quotes for the String literal. You can also combine the [] and . notations, as shown here:

${customer.address["street"]}

You can reference a static field or method using the syntax classname.field, as in the following example:

Boolean.FALSE

The classname is the name of the class without the package name. By default, all the java.lang packages are imported. You can import other packages, classes, and static fields as needed.

If you are accessing an item in an array or list, you must use the [] notation and specify an index in the array or list. The index is an expression that can be converted to int. The following example references the first of the customer orders, assuming that customer.orders is a List:

${customer.orders[1]}

If you are accessing an item in a Map, you must specify the key for the Map. If the key is a String literal, the dot (.) notation can be used. Assuming that customer.orders is a Map with a String key, the following examples reference the item with the key "socks":

${customer.orders["socks"]}

${customer.orders.socks}

9.3.1.3 Referencing Literals

The EL defines the following literals:

Boolean: true and false

Integer: As in Java

Floating-point: As in Java

String: With single and double quotes; " is escaped as \", ' is escaped as \', and \ is escaped as \\

Null: null

Here are some examples:

${"literal"}

${true}

${57}

9.3.1.4 Parameterized Method Calls

The EL offers support for parameterized method calls.

Both the . and [] operators can be used for invoking method calls with parameters, as shown in the following expression syntax:

expr-a[expr-b](parameters)

expr-a.identifier-b(parameters)

In the first expression syntax, expr-a is evaluated to represent a bean object. The expression expr-b is evaluated and cast to a string that represents a method in the bean represented by expr-a. In the second expression syntax, expr-a is evaluated to represent a bean object, and identifier-b is a string that represents a method in the bean object. The parameters in parentheses are the arguments for the method invocation. Parameters can be zero or more values of expressions, separated by commas.

Parameters are supported for both value expressions and method expressions. In the following example, which is a modified tag from the guessnumber application, a random number is provided as an argument rather than from user input to the method call:

<h:inputText value="#{userNumberBean.userNumber('5')}">

The preceding example uses a value expression.

Consider the following example of a JavaServer Faces component tag that uses a method expression:

<h:commandButton action="#{trader.buy}" value="buy"/>

The EL expression trader.buy calls the trader bean's buy method. You can modify the tag to pass on a parameter. Here is the revised tag in which a parameter is passed:

<h:commandButton action="#{trader.buy('SOMESTOCK')}" value="buy"/>

In the preceding example, you are passing the string 'SOMESTOCK' (a stock symbol) as a parameter to the buy method.

9.3.1.5 Where Value Expressions Can Be Used

Value expressions using the ${} delimiters can be used

In static text

In any standard or custom tag attribute that can accept an expression

The value of an expression in static text is computed and inserted into the current output. Here is an example of an expression embedded in static text:

<some:tag>
    some text ${expr} some text
</some:tag>

A tag attribute can be set in the following ways.

With a single expression construct:

<some:tag value="${expr}"/>

<another:tag value="#{expr}"/>

These expressions are evaluated, and the result is converted to the attribute's expected type.

With one or more expressions separated or surrounded by text:

<some:tag value="some${expr}${expr}text${expr}"/>

<another:tag value="some#{expr}#{expr}text#{expr}"/>

These kinds of expression, called composite expressions, are evaluated from left to right. Each expression embedded in the composite expression is converted to a String and then concatenated with any intervening text. The resulting String is then converted to the attribute's expected type.

With text only:

<some:tag value="sometext"/>

The attribute's String value is converted to the attribute's expected type.

You can use the string concatenation operator += to create a single expression from what would otherwise be a composite expression. For example, you could change the composite expression

<some:tag value="sometext ${expr} moretext"/>

to

<some:tag value="${sometext += expr += moretext}"/>

All expressions used to set attribute values are evaluated in the context of an expected type. If the result of the expression evaluation does not match the expected type exactly, a type conversion will be performed. For example, the expression ${1.2E4} provided as the value of an attribute of type float will result in the following conversion:

Float.valueOf("1.2E4").floatValue()

9.3.2 Method Expressions

Another feature of the EL is its support of deferred method expressions. A method expression is used to refer to a public method of a bean and has the same syntax as an lvalue expression.

In JavaServer Faces technology, a component tag represents a component on a page. The component tag uses method expressions to specify methods that can be invoked to perform some processing for the component. These methods are necessary for handling events that the components generate and for validating component data, as shown in this example:

<h:form>
    <h:inputText id="name"
                 value="#{customer.name}"
                 validator="#{customer.validateName}"/>
    <h:commandButton id="submit"
                     action="#{customer.submit}" />
</h:form>

The h:inputText tag displays as a field. The validator attribute of this h:inputText tag references a method, called validateName, in the bean, called customer.

Because a method can be invoked during different phases of the lifecycle, method expressions must always use the deferred evaluation syntax.

Like lvalue expressions, method expressions can use the . and the [] operators. For example, #{object.method} is equivalent to #{object["method"]}. The literal inside the [] is converted to String and is used to find the name of the method that matches it.

Method expressions can be used only in tag attributes and only in the following ways:

With a single expression construct, where bean refers to a JavaBeans component and method refers to a method of the JavaBeans component:

<some:tag value="#{bean.method}"/>

The expression is evaluated to a method expression, which is passed to the tag handler. The method represented by the method expression can then be invoked later.

With text only:

<some:tag value="sometext"/>

Method expressions support literals primarily to support action attributes in JavaServer Faces technology. When the method referenced by this method expression is invoked, the method returns the String literal, which is then converted to the expected return type, as defined in the tag's tag library descriptor.

9.3.3 Lambda Expressions

A lambda expression is a value expression with parameters. The syntax is similar to that of the lambda expression in the Java programming language, except that in the EL, the body of the lambda expression is an EL expression.

For basic information on lambda expressions, see http://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/java/javaOO/lambdaexpressions.html.

Note:

Lambda expressions are part of Java SE 8, but you can use them in EL expressions with Java SE 7, the Java version associated with the Java EE 7 platform.

A lambda expression uses the arrow token (->) operator. The identifiers to the left of the operator are called lambda parameters. The body, to the right of the operator, must be an EL expression. The lambda parameters are enclosed in parentheses; the parentheses can be omitted if there is only one parameter. Here are some examples:

x -> x+1
(x, y) -> x + y
() -> 64

A lambda expression behaves like a function. It can be invoked immediately. For example, the following invocation evaluates to 7:

((x, y) -> x + y)(3, 4)

You can use a lambda expression in conjunction with the assignment and semicolon operators. For example, the following code assigns the previous lambda expression to a variable and then invokes it. The result is again 7:

v = (x, y) -> x + y; v(3, 4)

A lambda expression can also be passed as an argument to a method and be invoked in the method. It can also be nested in another lambda expression.

9.4 Operations on Collection Objects

The EL supports operations on collection objects: sets, lists, and maps. It allows the dynamic creation of collection objects, which can then be operated on using streams and pipelines.

Note:

Like lambda expressions, operations on collection objects are part of Java SE 8, but you can use them in EL expressions with Java SE 7, the Java version associated with the Java EE 7 platform.

For example, you can construct a set as follows:

{1,2,3}

You can construct a list as follows; a list can contain various types of items:

[1,2,3]
[1, "two", [three,four]]

You can construct a map by using a colon to define the entries, as follows:

{"one":1, "two":2, "three":3}

You operate on collection objects using method calls to the stream of elements derived from the collection. Some operations return another stream, which allows additional operations. Therefore, you can chain these operations together in a pipeline.

A stream pipeline consists of the following:

A source (the Stream object)

Any number of intermediate operations that return a stream (for example, filter and map)

A terminal operation that does not return a stream (for example, toList())

The stream method obtains a Stream from a java.util.Collection or a Java array. The stream operations do not modify the original collection object.

For example, you might generate a list of titles of history books as follows:

books.stream().filter(b->b.category == 'history')
              .map(b->b.title)
              .toList()

The following simpler example returns a sorted version of the original list:

[1,3,5,2].stream().sorted().toList()

Streams and stream operations are documented in the Java SE 8 API documentation, available at http://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/. The following subset of operations is supported by the EL:

allMatch
anyMatch
average
count
distinct
filter
findFirst
flatMap
forEach
iterator
limit
map
max
min
noneMatch
peek
reduce
sorted
substream
sum
toArray
toList

See the EL specification at http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=341 for details on these operations.

9.5 Operators

In addition to the . and [] operators discussed in Value and Method Expressions, the EL provides the following operators, which can be used in rvalue expressions only.

Arithmetic: +, - (binary), *, / and div, % and mod, - (unary).

String concatenation: +=.

Logical: and, &&, or, ||, not, !.

Relational: ==, eq, !=, ne, <, lt, >, gt, <=, ge, >=, le. Comparisons can be made against other values or against Boolean, string, integer, or floating-point literals.

Empty: The empty operator is a prefix operation that can be used to determine whether a value is null or empty.

Conditional: A ? B : C. Evaluate B or C, depending on the result of the evaluation of A.

Lambda expression: ->, the arrow token.

Assignment: =.

Semicolon: ;.

The precedence of operators, highest to lowest, left to right, is as follows:

[] .

() (used to change the precedence of operators)

- (unary) not ! empty

* / div % mod

+ - (binary)

+=

<> <= >= lt gt le ge

== != eq ne

&& and

|| or

? :

->

=

;

9.6 Reserved Words

The following words are reserved for the EL and should not be used as identifiers:

and
or
not
eq
ne
lt
gt
le
ge
true
false
null
instanceof
empty
div
mod

9.7 Examples of EL Expressions

Table 9-1 contains example EL expressions and the result of evaluating them.

Table 9-1 Example Expressions

EL Expression | Result

${1> (4/2)}

|

false

${4.0>= 3}

|

true

${100.0 == 100}

|

true

${(10*10) ne 100}

|

false

${'a' > 'b'}

|

false

${'hip' lt 'hit'}

|

true

${4> 3}

|

true

${1.2E4 + 1.4}

|

12001.4

${3 div 4}

|

0.75

${10 mod 4}

|

2

${((x, y) -> x + y)(3, 5.5)}

|

8.5

[1,2,3,4].stream().sum()

|

10

[1,3,5,2].stream().sorted().toList()

|

[1, 2, 3, 5]

${!empty param.Add}

|

False if the request parameter named Add is null or an empty string

${pageContext.request.contextPath}

|

The context path

${sessionScope.cart.numberOfItems}

|

The value of the numberOfItems property of the session-scoped attribute named cart

${param['mycom.productId']}

|

The value of the request parameter named mycom.productId

${header["host"]}

|

The host

${departments[deptName]}

|

The value of the entry named deptName in the departments map

${requestScope['javax.servlet.forward.servlet_path']}

|

The value of the request-scoped attribute named javax.servlet.forward.servlet_path

#{customer.lName}

|

Gets the value of the property lName from the customer bean during an initial request; sets the value of lName during a postback

#{customer.calcTotal}

|

The return value of the method calcTotal of the customer bean

9.8 Further Information about the Expression Language

For more information about the EL, see

The Expression Language 3.0 specification:

http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=341

The EL specification website:

https://java.net/projects/el-spec/

8 Introduction to Facelets

The term Facelets refers to the view declaration language for JavaServer Faces technology. Facelets is a part of the JavaServer Faces specification and also the preferred presentation technology for building JavaServer Faces technology–based applications. JavaServer Pages (JSP) technology, previously used as the presentation technology for JavaServer Faces, does not support all the new features available in JavaServer Faces in the Java EE 7 platform. JSP technology is considered to be a deprecated presentation technology for JavaServer Faces.

The following topics are addressed here:

What Is Facelets?

The Lifecycle of a Facelets Application

Developing a Simple Facelets Application: The guessnumber-jsf Example Application

Using Facelets Templates

Composite Components

Web Resources

Relocatable Resources

Resource Library Contracts

HTML5-Friendly Markup

8.1 What Is Facelets?

Facelets is a powerful but lightweight page declaration language that is used to build JavaServer Faces views using HTML style templates and to build component trees. Facelets features include the following:

Use of XHTML for creating web pages

Support for Facelets tag libraries in addition to JavaServer Faces and JSTL tag libraries

Support for the Expression Language (EL)

Templating for components and pages

The advantages of Facelets for large-scale development projects include the following:

Support for code reuse through templating and composite components

Functional extensibility of components and other server-side objects through customization

Faster compilation time

Compile-time EL validation

High-performance rendering

In short, the use of Facelets reduces the time and effort that needs to be spent on development and deployment.

Facelets views are usually created as XHTML pages. JavaServer Faces implementations support XHTML pages created in conformance with the XHTML Transitional Document Type Definition (DTD), as listed at http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/#a_dtd_XHTML-1.0-Transitional. By convention, web pages built with XHTML have an .xhtml extension.

JavaServer Faces technology supports various tag libraries to add components to a web page. To support the JavaServer Faces tag library mechanism, Facelets uses XML namespace declarations. Table 8-1 lists the tag libraries supported by Facelets.

Table 8-1 Tag Libraries Supported by Facelets

Tag Library | URI | Prefix | Example | Contents

JavaServer Faces Facelets Tag Library

|

http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/facelets

|

ui:

|

ui:component

ui:insert

|

Tags for templating

JavaServer Faces HTML Tag Library

|

http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html

|

h:

|

h:head

h:body

h:outputText

h:inputText

|

JavaServer Faces component tags for all UIComponent objects

JavaServer Faces Core Tag Library

|

http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/core

|

f:

|

f:actionListener

f:attribute

|

Tags for JavaServer Faces custom actions that are independent of any particular render kit

Pass-through Elements Tag Library

|

http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf

|

jsf:

|

jsf:id

|

Tags to support HTML5-friendly markup

Pass-through Attributes Tag Library

|

http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/passthrough

|

p:

|

p:type

|

Tags to support HTML5-friendly markup

Composite Component Tag Library

|

http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/composite

|

cc:

|

cc:interface

|

Tags to support composite components

JSTL Core Tag Library

|

http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsp/jstl/core

|

c:

|

c:forEach

c:catch

|

JSTL 1.2 Core Tags

JSTL Functions Tag Library

|

http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsp/jstl/functions

|

fn:

|

fn:toUpperCase

fn:toLowerCase

|

JSTL 1.2 Functions Tags

Facelets provides two namespaces to support HTML5-friendly markup. For details, see HTML5-Friendly Markup.

Facelets supports tags for composite components, for which you can declare custom prefixes. For more information on composite components, see Composite Components.

The namespace prefixes shown in the table are conventional, not mandatory. As is always the case when you declare an XML namespace, you can specify any prefix in your Facelets page. For example, you can declare the prefix for the composite component tag library as

xmlns:composite="http://java.sun.com/jsf/composite"

instead of as

xmlns:cc="http://java.sun.com/jsf/composite"

Based on the JavaServer Faces support for Expression Language (EL) syntax, Facelets uses EL expressions to reference properties and methods of managed beans. EL expressions can be used to bind component objects or values to methods or properties of managed beans that are used as backing beans. For more information on using EL expressions, see Using the EL to Reference Managed Beans.

8.2 The Lifecycle of a Facelets Application

The JavaServer Faces specification defines the lifecycle of a JavaServer Faces application. For more information on this lifecycle, see The Lifecycle of a JavaServer Faces Application. The following steps describe that process as applied to a Facelets-based application.

When a client, such as a browser, makes a new request to a page that is created using Facelets, a new component tree or javax.faces.component.UIViewRoot is created and placed in the FacesContext.

The UIViewRoot is applied to the Facelets, and the view is populated with components for rendering.

The newly built view is rendered back as a response to the client.

On rendering, the state of this view is stored for the next request. The state of input components and form data is stored.

The client may interact with the view and request another view or change from the JavaServer Faces application. At this time, the saved view is restored from the stored state.

The restored view is once again passed through the JavaServer Faces lifecycle, which eventually will either generate a new view or re-render the current view if there were no validation problems and no action was triggered.

If the same view is requested, the stored view is rendered once again.

If a new view is requested, then the process described in Step 2 is continued.

The new view is then rendered back as a response to the client.

8.3 Developing a Simple Facelets Application: The guessnumber-jsf Example Application

This section describes the general steps involved in developing a JavaServer Faces application. The following tasks are usually required:

Developing the managed beans

Creating the pages using the component tags

Defining page navigation

Mapping the FacesServlet instance

Adding managed bean declarations

8.3.1 Creating a Facelets Application

The example used in this tutorial is the guessnumber-jsf application. The application presents you with a page that asks you to guess a number from 0 to 10, validates your input against a random number, and responds with another page that informs you whether you guessed the number correctly or incorrectly.

The source code for this application is in the tut-install/examples/web/jsf/guessnumber-jsf/ directory.

8.3.1.1 Developing a Managed Bean

In a typical JavaServer Faces application, each page of the application connects to a managed bean that serves as a backing bean. The backing bean defines the methods and properties that are associated with the components. In this example, both pages use the same backing bean.

The following managed bean class, UserNumberBean.java, generates a random number from 0 to 10 inclusive:

package javaeetutorial.guessnumber;

import java.io.Serializable;
import java.util.Random;
import javax.enterprise.context.SessionScoped;
import javax.inject.Named; 

@Named
@SessionScoped
public class UserNumberBean implements Serializable {

    private static final long serialVersionUID = 5443351151396868724L;
    Integer randomInt = null;
    Integer userNumber = null;
    String response = null;
    private int maximum = 10;
    private int minimum = 0;

    public UserNumberBean() {
        Random randomGR = new Random();
        randomInt = new Integer(randomGR.nextInt(maximum + 1));
        // Print number to server log
        System.out.println("Duke's number: " + randomInt);
    }

    public void setUserNumber(Integer user_number) {
        userNumber = user_number;
    }

    public Integer getUserNumber() {
        return userNumber;
    }

    public String getResponse() {
        if ((userNumber == null) || (userNumber.compareTo(randomInt) != 0)) {
            return "Sorry, " + userNumber + " is incorrect.";
        } else {
            return "Yay! You got it!";
        }
    }

    public int getMaximum() {
        return (this.maximum);
    }

    public void setMaximum(int maximum) {
        this.maximum = maximum;
    }

    public int getMinimum() {
        return (this.minimum);
    }

    public void setMinimum(int minimum) {
        this.minimum = minimum;
    }
}

Note the use of the @Named annotation, which makes the managed bean accessible through the EL. The @SessionScoped annotation registers the bean scope as session to enable you to make multiple guesses as you run the application.

8.3.1.2 Creating Facelets Views

To create a page or view, you add components to the pages, wire the components to backing bean values and properties, and register converters, validators, or listeners on the components.

For the example application, XHTML web pages serve as the front end. The first page of the example application is a page called greeting.xhtml. A closer look at various sections of this web page provides more information.

The first section of the web page declares the content type for the page, which is XHTML:

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" 
  "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">

The next section specifies the language of the XHTML page and then declares the XML namespace for the tag libraries that are used in the web page:

<html lang="en"
      xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html"
      xmlns:f="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/core">

The next section uses various tags to insert components into the web page:

    <h:head>
        <h:outputStylesheet library="css" name="default.css"/>
        <title>Guess Number Facelets Application</title>
    </h:head>
    <h:body>
        <h:form>
            <h:graphicImage value="#{resource['images:wave.med.gif']}"
                            alt="Duke waving his hand"/>
            <h2>
                Hi, my name is Duke. I am thinking of a number from
                #{userNumberBean.minimum} to #{userNumberBean.maximum}.
                Can you guess it?
            </h2>
            <p><h:inputText id="userNo"
                            title="Enter a number from 0 to 10:"
                            value="#{userNumberBean.userNumber}">
                   <f:validateLongRange minimum="#{userNumberBean.minimum}"
                                        maximum="#{userNumberBean.maximum}"/>
                </h:inputText>
                <h:commandButton id="submit" value="Submit"
                                 action="response"/>
            </p>
            <h:message showSummary="true" showDetail="false"
                       style="color: #d20005;
                       font-family: 'New Century Schoolbook', serif;
                       font-style: oblique;
                       text-decoration: overline"
                       id="errors1"
                       for="userNo"/>
        </h:form>
    </h:body>

Note the use of the following tags:

Facelets HTML tags (those beginning with h:) to add components

The Facelets core tag f:validateLongRange to validate the user input

An h:inputText tag accepts user input and sets the value of the managed bean property userNumber through the EL expression #{userNumberBean.userNumber}. The input value is validated for value range by the JavaServer Faces standard validator tag f:validateLongRange.

The image file, wave.med.gif, is added to the page as a resource, as is the style sheet. For more details about the resources facility, see Web Resources.

An h:commandButton tag with the ID submit starts validation of the input data when a user clicks the button. Using implicit navigation, the tag redirects the client to another page, response.xhtml, which shows the response to your input. The page specifies only response, which by default causes the server to look for response.xhtml.

You can now create the second page, response.xhtml, with the following content:

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
    "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">

<html lang="en"
      xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html">

    <h:head>
        <h:outputStylesheet library="css" name="default.css"/>
        <title>Guess Number Facelets Application</title>
    </h:head>
    <h:body>
        <h:form>
            <h:graphicImage value="#{resource['images:wave.med.gif']}"
                            alt="Duke waving his hand"/>
            <h2>
                <h:outputText id="result" value="#{userNumberBean.response}"/>
            </h2>
            <h:commandButton id="back" value="Back" action="greeting"/>
        </h:form>
    </h:body>
</html>

This page also uses implicit navigation, setting the action attribute for the Back button to send the user to the greeting.xhtml page.

8.3.2 Configuring the Application

Configuring a JavaServer Faces application involves mapping the Faces Servlet in the web deployment descriptor file, such as a web.xml file, and possibly adding managed bean declarations, navigation rules, and resource bundle declarations to the application configuration resource file, faces-config.xml.

If you are using NetBeans IDE, a web deployment descriptor file is automatically created for you. In such an IDE-created web.xml file, change the default greeting page, which is index.xhtml, to greeting.xhtml. Here is an example web.xml file, showing this change in bold.

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<web-app version="3.1" xmlns="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee" 
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee 
  http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee/web-app_3_1.xsd">
    <context-param>
        <param-name>javax.faces.PROJECT_STAGE</param-name>
        <param-value>Development</param-value>
    </context-param>
    <servlet>
        <servlet-name>Faces Servlet</servlet-name>
        <servlet-class>javax.faces.webapp.FacesServlet</servlet-class>
        <load-on-startup>1</load-on-startup>
    </servlet>
    <servlet-mapping>
        <servlet-name>Faces Servlet</servlet-name>
        <url-pattern>*.xhtml</url-pattern>
    </servlet-mapping>
    <session-config>
        <session-timeout>
            30
        </session-timeout>
    </session-config>
    <welcome-file-list>
        <welcome-file>greeting.xhtml</welcome-file> 
    </welcome-file-list>
</web-app>

Note the use of the context parameter PROJECT_STAGE. This parameter identifies the status of a JavaServer Faces application in the software lifecycle.

The stage of an application can affect the behavior of the application. For example, if the project stage is defined as Development, debugging information is automatically generated for the user. If not defined by the user, the default project stage is Production.

8.3.3 Running the guessnumber-jsf Facelets Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the guessnumber-jsf example.

8.3.3.1 To Build, Package, and Deploy the guessnumber-jsf Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf

Select the guessnumber-jsf folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the guessnumber-jsf project and select Build.

This option builds the example application and deploys it to your GlassFish Server instance.

8.3.3.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the guessnumber-jsf Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf/guessnumber-jsf/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, guessnumber-jsf.war, that is located in the target directory. It then deploys it to the server.

8.3.3.3 To Run the guessnumber-jsf Example

Open a web browser.

Enter the following URL in your web browser:

http://localhost:8080/guessnumber-jsf

In the field, enter a number from 0 to 10 and click Submit.

Another page appears, reporting whether your guess is correct or incorrect.

If you guessed incorrectly, click Back to return to the main page.

You can continue to guess until you get the correct answer, or you can look in the server log, where the UserNumberBean constructor displays the correct answer.

8.4 Using Facelets Templates

JavaServer Faces technology provides the tools to implement user interfaces that are easy to extend and reuse. Templating is a useful Facelets feature that allows you to create a page that will act as the base, or template, for the other pages in an application. By using templates, you can reuse code and avoid recreating similarly constructed pages. Templating also helps in maintaining a standard look and feel in an application with a large number of pages.

Table 8-2 lists Facelets tags that are used for templating and their respective functionality.

Table 8-2 Facelets Templating Tags

Tag | Function

ui:component

|

Defines a component that is created and added to the component tree.

ui:composition

|

Defines a page composition that optionally uses a template. Content outside of this tag is ignored.

ui:debug

|

Defines a debug component that is created and added to the component tree.

ui:decorate

|

Similar to the composition tag but does not disregard content outside this tag.

ui:define

|

Defines content that is inserted into a page by a template.

ui:fragment

|

Similar to the component tag but does not disregard content outside this tag.

ui:include

|

Encapsulates and reuses content for multiple pages.

ui:insert

|

Inserts content into a template.

ui:param

|

Used to pass parameters to an included file.

ui:repeat

|

Used as an alternative for loop tags, such as c:forEach or h:dataTable.

ui:remove

|

Removes content from a page.

For more information on Facelets templating tags, see the documentation at http://docs.oracle.com/javaee/7/javaserverfaces/2.2/vdldocs/facelets/.

The Facelets tag library includes the main templating tag ui:insert. A template page that is created with this tag allows you to define a default structure for a page. A template page is used as a template for other pages, usually referred to as client pages.

Here is an example of a template saved as template.xhtml:

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" 
      "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:ui="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/facelets"
      xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html">
    
    <h:head>
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" 
              content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <h:outputStylesheet library="css" name="default.css"/>
        <h:outputStylesheet library="css" name="cssLayout.css"/>
        <title>Facelets Template</title>
    </h:head>
    
    <h:body>
        <div id="top" class="top">
            <ui:insert name="top">Top Section</ui:insert>
        </div>
        <div>
        <div id="left">
             <ui:insert name="left">Left Section</ui:insert>
        </div>
        <div id="content" class="left_content">
             <ui:insert name="content">Main Content</ui:insert>
        </div>
        </div>
    </h:body>
</html>

The example page defines an XHTML page that is divided into three sections: a top section, a left section, and a main section. The sections have style sheets associated with them. The same structure can be reused for the other pages of the application.

The client page invokes the template by using the ui:composition tag. In the following example, a client page named templateclient.xhtml invokes the template page named template.xhtml from the preceding example. A client page allows content to be inserted with the help of the ui:define tag.

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" 
  "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:ui="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/facelets"
      xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html">
    
    <h:body>
        <ui:composition template="./template.xhtml">
            <ui:define name="top">
                Welcome to Template Client Page
            </ui:define>

            <ui:define name="left">
                <h:outputLabel value="You are in the Left Section"/>
            </ui:define>

            <ui:define name="content">
                <h:graphicImage value="#{resource['images:wave.med.gif']}"/>
                <h:outputText value="You are in the Main Content Section"/>
            </ui:define>
        </ui:composition>
    </h:body>
</html>

You can use NetBeans IDE to create Facelets template and client pages. For more information on creating these pages, see https://netbeans.org/kb/docs/web/jsf20-intro.html.

8.5 Composite Components

JavaServer Faces technology offers the concept of composite components with Facelets. A composite component is a special type of template that acts as a component.

Any component is essentially a piece of reusable code that behaves in a particular way. For example, an input component accepts user input. A component can also have validators, converters, and listeners attached to it to perform certain defined actions.

A composite component consists of a collection of markup tags and other existing components. This reusable, user-created component has a customized, defined functionality and can have validators, converters, and listeners attached to it like any other component.

With Facelets, any XHTML page that contains markup tags and other components can be converted into a composite component. Using the resources facility, the composite component can be stored in a library that is available to the application from the defined resources location.

Table 8-3 lists the most commonly used composite tags and their functions.

Table 8-3 Composite Component Tags

Tag | Function

composite:interface

|

Declares the usage contract for a composite component. The composite component can be used as a single component whose feature set is the union of the features declared in the usage contract.

composite:implementation

|

Defines the implementation of the composite component. If a composite:interface element appears, there must be a corresponding composite:implementation.

composite:attribute

|

Declares an attribute that may be given to an instance of the composite component in which this tag is declared.

composite:insertChildren

|

Any child components or template text within the composite component tag in the using page will be reparented into the composite component at the point indicated by this tag's placement within the composite:implementation section.

composite:valueHolder

|

Declares that the composite component whose contract is declared by the composite:interface in which this element is nested exposes an implementation of ValueHolder suitable for use as the target of attached objects in the using page.

composite:editableValueHolder

|

Declares that the composite component whose contract is declared by the composite:interface in which this element is nested exposes an implementation of EditableValueHolder suitable for use as the target of attached objects in the using page.

composite:actionSource

|

Declares that the composite component whose contract is declared by the composite:interface in which this element is nested exposes an implementation of ActionSource2 suitable for use as the target of attached objects in the using page.

For more information and a complete list of Facelets composite tags, see the documentation at http://docs.oracle.com/javaee/7/javaserverfaces/2.2/vdldocs/facelets/.

The following example shows a composite component that accepts an email address as input:

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
  "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:composite="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/composite"
  xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html">

    <h:head>
        <title>This content will not be displayed</title>
    </h:head>
    <h:body>
        <composite:interface>
            <composite:attribute name="value" required="false"/>
        </composite:interface>

        <composite:implementation>
            <h:outputLabel value="Email id: "></h:outputLabel>
            <h:inputText value="#{cc.attrs.value}"></h:inputText>
        </composite:implementation>
    </h:body>
</html>

Note the use of cc.attrs.value when defining the value of the inputText component. The word cc in JavaServer Faces is a reserved word for composite components. The #{cc.attrs.attribute-name} expression is used to access the attributes defined for the composite component's interface, which in this case happens to be value.

The preceding example content is stored as a file named email.xhtml in a folder named resources/emcomp, under the application web root directory. This directory is considered a library by JavaServer Faces, and a component can be accessed from such a library. For more information on resources, see Web Resources.

The web page that uses this composite component is generally called a using page. The using page includes a reference to the composite component, in the xml namespace declarations:

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
  "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html"
  xmlns:em="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/composite/emcomp">

    <h:head>
        <title>Using a sample composite component</title>
    </h:head>

    <body>
        <h:form>
            <em:email value="Enter your email id" />
        </h:form>
    </body>
</html>

The local composite component library is defined in the xmlns namespace with the declaration xmlns:em="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/composite/emcomp". The component itself is accessed through the em:email tag. The preceding example content can be stored as a web page named emuserpage.xhtml under the web root directory. When compiled and deployed on a server, it can be accessed with the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/application-name/emuserpage.xhtml

See Chapter 14, "Composite Components: Advanced Topics and an Example," for more information and an example.

8.6 Web Resources

Web resources are any software artifacts that the web application requires for proper rendering, including images, script files, and any user-created component libraries. Resources must be collected in a standard location, which can be one of the following.

A resource packaged in the web application root must be in a subdirectory of a resources directory at the web application root: resources/resource-identifier.

A resource packaged in the web application's classpath must be in a subdirectory of the META-INF/resources directory within a web application: META-INF/resources/resource-identifier. You can use this file structure to package resources in a JAR file bundled in the web application.

The JavaServer Faces runtime will look for the resources in the preceding listed locations, in that order.

Resource identifiers are unique strings that conform to the following format (all on one line):

[locale-prefix/][library-name/][library-version/]resource-name[/resource-version]

Elements of the resource identifier in brackets ([]) are optional, indicating that only a resource-name, which is usually a file name, is a required element. For example, the most common way to specify a style sheet, image, or script is to use the library and name attributes, as in the following tag from the guessnumber-jsf example:

<h:outputStylesheet library="css" name="default.css"/>

This tag specifies that the default.css style sheet is in the directory web/resources/css.

You can also specify the location of an image using the following syntax, also from the guessnumber-jsf example:

<h:graphicImage value="#{resource['images:wave.med.gif']}"/>

This tag specifies that the image named wave.med.gif is in the directory web/resources/images.

Resources can be considered as a library location. Any artifact, such as a composite component or a template that is stored in the resources directory, becomes accessible to the other application components, which can use it to create a resource instance.

8.7 Relocatable Resources

You can place a resource tag in one part of a page and specify that it be rendered in another part of the page. To do this, you use the target attribute of a tag that specifies a resource. Acceptable values for this attribute are as follows.

"head" renders the resource in the head element.

"body" renders the resource in the body element.

"form" renders the resource in the form element.

For example, the following h:outputScript tag is placed within an h:form element, but it renders the JavaScript in the head element:

<h:form>
    <h:outputScript name="myscript.js" library="mylibrary" target="head"/>
</h:form>

The h:outputStylesheet tag also supports resource relocation, in a similar way.

Relocatable resources are essential for composite components that use stylesheets and can also be useful for composite components that use JavaScript. See The compositecomponentexample Example Application for an example.

8.8 Resource Library Contracts

Resource library contracts allow you to define a different look and feel for different parts of one or more applications, instead of either having to use the same look and feel for all or having to specify a different look on a page-by-page basis.

To do this, you create a contracts section of your web application. Within the contracts section, you can specify any number of named areas, each of which is called a contract. Within each contract you can specify resources such as template files, stylesheets, JavaScript files, and images.

For example, you could specify two contracts named c1 and c2, each of which uses a template and other files:

src/main/webapp
    WEB-INF/
    contracts
        c1
            template.xhtml
            style.css
            myImg.gif
            myJS.js
        c2
            template.xhtml
            style2.css
            img2.gif
            JS2.js
    index.xhtml
    ...

One part of the application can use c1, while another can use c2.

Another way to use contracts is to specify a single contract that contains multiple templates:

src/main/webapp
    contracts
        myContract
            template1.xhtml
            template2.xhtml
            style.css
            img.png
            img2.png

You can package a resource library contract in a JAR file for reuse in different applications. If you do so, the contracts must be located under META-INF/contracts. You can then place the JAR file in the WEB-INF/lib directory of an application. This means that the application would be organized as follows:

src/main/webapp/
    WEB-INF/lib/myContract.jar
    ...

You can specify the contract usage within an application's faces-config.xml file, under the resource-library-contracts element. You need to use this element only if your application uses more than one contract, however.

8.8.1 The hello1-rlc Example Application

The hello1-rlc example modifies the simple hello1 example from A Web Module That Uses JavaServer Faces Technology: The hello1 Example to use two resource library contracts. Each of the two pages in the application uses a different contract.

The managed bean for hello1-rlc, Hello.java, is identical to the one for hello1 (except that it replaces the @Named and @RequestScoped annotations with @Model).

The source code for this application is in the tut-install/examples/web/jsf/hello1-rlc/ directory.

8.8.1.1 Configuring the hello1-rlc Example

The faces-config.xml file for the hello1-rlc example contains the following elements:

<resource-library-contracts>
    <contract-mapping>
        <url-pattern>/reply/*</url-pattern>
        <contracts>reply</contracts>
    </contract-mapping>
    <contract-mapping>
        <url-pattern>*</url-pattern>
        <contracts>hello</contracts>
    </contract-mapping>
</resource-library-contracts>

The contract-mapping elements within the resource-library-contracts element map each contract to a different set of pages within the application. One contract, named reply, is used for all pages under the reply area of the application (/reply/*). The other contract, hello, is used for all other pages in the application (*).

The application is organized as follows:

hello1-rlc
    pom.xml
    src/main/java/javaeetutorial/hello1rlc/Hello.java
    src/main/webapp
        WEB-INF
            faces-config.xml
            web.xml
        contracts
            hello
                default.css
                duke.handsOnHips.gif
                template.xhtml
            reply
                default.css
                duke.thumbsup.gif
                template.xhtml
        reply
            response.xhtml
        greeting.xhtml

The web.xml file specifies the welcome-file as greeting.xhtml. Because it is not located under src/main/webapp/reply, this Facelets page uses the hello contract, whereas src/main/webapp/reply/response.xhtml uses the reply contract.

8.8.1.2 The Facelets Pages for the hello1-rlc Example

The greeting.xhtml and response.xhtml pages have identical code calling in their templates:

<ui:composition template="/template.xhtml">

The template.xhtml files in the hello and reply contracts differ only in two respects: the placeholder text for the title element ("Hello Template" and "Reply Template") and the graphic that each specifies.

The default.css stylesheets in the two contracts differ in only one respect: the background color specified for the body element.

8.8.1.3 To Build, Package, and Deploy the hello1-rlc Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf

Select the hello1-rlc folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the hello1-rlc project and select Build.

This option builds the example application and deploys it to your GlassFish Server instance.

8.8.1.4 To Build, Package, and Deploy the hello1-rlc Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf/hello1-rlc/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, hello1-rlc.war, that is located in the target directory. It then deploys it to your GlassFish Server instance.

8.8.1.5 To Run the hello1-rlc Example

Enter the following URL in your web browser:

http://localhost:8080/hello1-rlc

The greeting.xhtml page looks just like the one from hello1 except for its background color and graphic.

In the text field, enter your name and click Submit.

The response page also looks just like the one from hello1 except for its background color and graphic.

The page displays the name you submitted. Click Back to return to the greeting.xhtml page.

8.9 HTML5-Friendly Markup

When you want to produce user interface features for which HTML does not have its own elements, you can create a custom JavaServer Faces component and insert it in your Facelets page. This mechanism can cause a simple element to create complex web code. However, creating such a component is a significant task (see Chapter 15, "Creating Custom UI Components and Other Custom Objects").

HTML5 offers new elements and attributes that can make it unnecessary to write your own components. It also provides many new capabilities for existing components. JavaServer Faces technology supports HTML5 not by introducing new UI components that imitate HTML5 ones but by allowing you to use HTML5 markup directly. It also allows you to use JavaServer Faces attributes within HTML5 elements. JavaServer Faces technology support for HTML5 falls into two categories:

Pass-through elements

Pass-through attributes

The effect of the HTML5-friendly markup feature is to offer the Facelets page author almost complete control over the rendered page output, rather than having to pass this control off to component authors. You can mix and match JavaServer Faces and HTML5 components and elements as you see fit.

8.9.1 Using Pass-Through Elements

Pass-through elements allow you to use HTML5 tags and attributes but to treat them as equivalent to JavaServer Faces components associated with a server-side UIComponent instance.

To make an element that is not a JavaServer Faces element a pass-through element, specify at least one of its attributes using the http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf namespace. For example, the following code declares the namespace with the short name jsf:

<html ... xmlns:jsf="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf"
...
    <input type="email" jsf:id="email" name="email"
           value="#{reservationBean.email}" required="required"/>

Here, the jsf prefix is placed on the id attribute so that the HTML5 input tag's attributes are treated as part of the Facelets page. This means that, for example, you can use EL expressions to retrieve managed bean properties.

Table 8-4 shows how pass-through elements are rendered as Facelets tags. The JSF implementation uses the element name and the identifying attribute to determine the corresponding Facelets tag that will be used in the server-side processing. The browser, however, interprets the markup that the page author has written.

Table 8-4 How Facelets Renders HTML5 Elements

HTML5 Element Name | Identifying Attribute | Facelets Tag

a

|

jsf:action

|

h:commandLink

a

|

jsf:actionListener

|

h:commandLink

a

|

jsf:value

|

h:outputLink

a

|

jsf:outcome

|

h:link

body

|
|

h:body

button

|
|

h:commandButton

button

|

jsf:outcome

|

h:button

form

|
|

h:form

head

|
|

h:head

img

|
|

h:graphicImage

input

|

type="button"

|

h:commandButton

input

|

type="checkbox"

|

h:selectBooleanCheckbox

input

|

type="color"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="date"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="datetime"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="datetime-local"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="email"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="month"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="number"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="range"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="search"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="time"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="url"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="week"

|

h:inputText

input

|

type="file"

|

h:inputFile

input

|

type="hidden"

|

h:inputHidden

input

|

type="password"

|

h:inputSecret

input

|

type="reset"

|

h:commandButton

input

|

type="submit"

|

h:commandButton

input

|

type="*"

|

h:inputText

label

|
|

h:outputLabel

link

|
|

h:outputStylesheet

script

|
|

h:outputScript

select

|

multiple="*"

|

h:selectManyListbox

select

|
|

h:selectOneListbox

textarea

|
|

h:inputTextArea

8.9.2 Using Pass-Through Attributes

Pass-through attributes are the converse of pass-through elements. They allow you to pass attributes that are not JavaServer Faces attributes through to the browser without interpretation. If you specify a pass-through attribute in a JavaServer Faces UIComponent, the attribute name and value are passed straight through to the browser without being interpreted by JavaServer Faces components or renderers. There are several ways to specify pass-through attributes.

Use the JavaServer Faces namespace for pass-through attributes to prefix the attribute names within a JavaServer Faces component. For example, the following code declares the namespace with the short name p, then passes the type, min, max, required, and title attributes through to the HTML5 input component:

<html ... xmlns:p="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/passthrough"
...
    
<h:form prependId="false">
<h:inputText id="nights" p:type="number" value="#{bean.nights}" 
             p:min="1" p:max="30" p:required="required" 
             p:title="Enter a number between 1 and 30 inclusive.">
        ...

This will cause the following markup to be rendered (assuming that bean.nights has a default value set to 1):

<input id="nights" type="number" value="1" min="1" max="30"
       required="required" 
       title="Enter a number between 1 and 30 inclusive.">

To pass a single attribute, nest the f:passThroughAttribute tag within a component tag. For example:

<h:inputText value="#{user.email}">
    <f:passThroughAttribute name="type" value="email" />
</h:inputText>

This code would be rendered similarly to the following:

<input value="me@me.com" type="email" />

To pass a group of attributes, nest the f:passThroughAttributes tag within a component tag, specifying an EL value that must evaluate to a Map<String, Object>. For example:

<h:inputText value="#{bean.nights">
    <f:passThroughAttributes value="#{bean.nameValuePairs}" />
</h:inputText>

If the bean used the following Map declaration and initialized the map in the constructor as follows, the markup would be similar to the output of the code that uses the pass-through attribute namespace:

private Map<String, Object> nameValuePairs;
...
public Bean() {
    this.nameValuePairs = new HashMap<>();
    this.nameValuePairs.put("type", "number");
    this.nameValuePairs.put("min", "1");
    this.nameValuePairs.put("max", "30");
    this.nameValuePairs.put("required", "required");
    this.nameValuePairs.put("title", 
            "Enter a number between 1 and 4 inclusive.");
}

8.9.3 The reservation Example Application

The reservation example application provides a set of HTML5 input elements of various types to simulate purchasing tickets for a theatrical event. It consists of two Facelets pages, reservation.xhtml and confirmation.xhtml, and a backing bean, ReservationBean.java. The pages use both pass-through attributes and pass-through elements.

The source code for this application is in the tut-install/examples/web/jsf/reservation/ directory.

8.9.3.1 The Facelets Pages for the reservation Application

The first important feature of the Facelets pages for the reservation application is the DOCTYPE header. Most Facelets pages in JavaServer Faces applications refer to the XHTML DTD. The facelets pages for this application begin simply with the following DOCTYPE header, which indicates an HTML5 page:

<!DOCTYPE html>

The namespace declarations in the html element of the reservation.xhtml page specify both the jsf and the passthrough namespaces:

<html lang="en"
      xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:f="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/core"
      xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html"
      xmlns:p="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/passthrough"
      xmlns:jsf="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf">

Next, an empty h:head tag followed by an h:outputStylesheet tag within the h:body tag illustrates the use of a relocatable resource (as described in Relocatable Resources):

<h:head>
</h:head>
<h:body>
    <h:outputStylesheet name="css/stylesheet.css" target="head"/>

The reservation.xhtml page uses pass-through elements for most of the form fields on the page. This allows it to use some HTML5-specific input element types, such as date and email. For example, the following element renders both a date format and a calendar from which you can choose a date. The jsf prefix on the id attribute makes the element a pass-through one:

    <input type="date" jsf:id="date" name="date" 
           value="#{reservationBean.date}" required="required"
           title="Enter or choose a date."/>

The field for the number of tickets, however, uses the h:passThroughAttributes tag to pass a Map defined in the managed bean. It also recalculates the total in response to a change in the field:

    <h:inputText id="tickets" value="#{reservationBean.tickets}">
        <f:passThroughAttributes value="#{reservationBean.ticketAttrs}"/>
        <f:ajax event="change" render="total" 
                listener="#{reservationBean.calculateTotal}"/>
    </h:inputText>

The field for the price specifies the number type as a pass-through attribute of the h:inputText element, offering a range of four ticket prices. Here, the p prefix on the HTML5 attributes passes them through to the browser uninterpreted by the JavaServer Faces input component:

    <h:inputText id="price" p:type="number" 
                 value="#{reservationBean.price}" 
                 p:min="80" p:max="120"
                 p:step="20" p:required="required" 
                 p:title="Enter a price: 80, 100, 120, or 140.">
        <f:ajax event="change" render="total" 
                listener="#{reservationBean.calculateTotal}"/>
    </h:inputText>

The output of the calculateTotal method that is specified as the listener for the Ajax event is rendered in the output element whose id and name value is total. See Chapter 13, "Using Ajax with JavaServer Faces Technology", for more information.

The second Facelets page, confirmation.xhtml, uses a pass-through output element to display the values entered by the user and provides a Facelets h:commandButton tag to allow the user to return to the reservation.xhtml page.

8.9.3.2 The Managed Bean for the reservation Application

The session-scoped managed bean for the reservation application, ReservationBean.java, contains properties for all the elements on the Facelets pages. It also contains two methods, calculateTotal and clear, that act as listeners for Ajax events on the reservation.xhtml page.

8.9.3.3 To Build, Package, and Deploy the reservation Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf

Select the reservation folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the reservation project and select Build.

This option builds the example application and deploys it to your GlassFish Server instance.

8.9.3.4 To Build, Package, and Deploy the reservation Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/web/jsf/reservation/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, reservation.war, that is located in the target directory. It then deploys the WAR file to your GlassFish Server instance.

8.9.3.5 To Run the reservation Example

At the time of the publication of this tutorial, the browser that most fully implements HTML5 is Google Chrome, and it is recommended that you use it to run this example. Other browsers are catching up, however, and may work equally well by the time you read this.

Enter the following URL in your web browser:

http://localhost:8080/reservation

Enter information in the fields of the reservation.xhtml page.

The Performance Date field has a date field with up and down arrows that allow you to increment and decrement the month, day, and year as well as a larger down arrow that brings up a date editor in calendar form.

The Number of Tickets and Ticket Price fields also have up and down arrows that allow you to increment and decrement the values within the allowed range and steps. The Estimated Total changes when you change either of these two fields.

Email addresses and dates are checked for format, but not for validity (you can make a reservation for a past date, for instance).

Click Make Reservation to complete the reservation or Clear to restore the fields to their default values.

If you click Make Reservation, the confirmation.xhtml page appears, displaying the submitted values.

Click Back to return to the reservation.xhtml page.

11 Using Converters, Listeners, and Validators

The previous chapter described components and explained how to add them to a web page. This chapter provides information on adding more functionality to the components through converters, listeners, and validators.

Converters are used to convert data that is received from the input components. Converters allow an application to bring the strongly typed features of the Java programming language into the String-based world of HTTP servlet programming.

Listeners are used to listen to the events happening in the page and perform actions as defined.

Validators are used to validate the data that is received from the input components. Validators allow an application to express constraints on form input data to ensure that the necessary requirements are met before the input data is processed.

The following topics are addressed here:

Using the Standard Converters

Registering Listeners on Components

Using the Standard Validators

Referencing a Managed Bean Method

11.1 Using the Standard Converters

The JavaServer Faces implementation provides a set of Converter implementations that you can use to convert component data. The purpose of conversion is to take the String-based data coming in from the Servlet API and convert it to strongly typed Java objects suitable for the business domain. For more information on the conceptual details of the conversion model, see Conversion Model.

The standard Converter implementations are located in the javax.faces.convert package. Normally, converters are implicitly assigned based on the type of the EL expression pointed to by the value of the component. However, these converters can also be accessed by a converter ID. Table 11-1 shows the converter classes and their associated converter IDs.

Table 11-1 Converter Classes and Converter IDs

Class in the javax.faces.convert Package | Converter ID

BigDecimalConverter

|

javax.faces.BigDecimal

BigIntegerConverter

|

javax.faces.BigInteger

BooleanConverter

|

javax.faces.Boolean

ByteConverter

|

javax.faces.Byte

CharacterConverter

|

javax.faces.Character

DateTimeConverter

|

javax.faces.DateTime

DoubleConverter

|

javax.faces.Double

EnumConverter

|

javax.faces.Enum

FloatConverter

|

javax.faces.Float

IntegerConverter

|

javax.faces.Integer

LongConverter

|

javax.faces.Long

NumberConverter

|

javax.faces.Number

ShortConverter

|

javax.faces.Short

A standard error message is associated with each of these converters. If you have registered one of these converters onto a component on your page and the converter is not able to convert the component's value, the converter's error message will display on the page. For example, the following error message appears if BigIntegerConverter fails to convert a value:

{0} must be a number consisting of one or more digits

In this case, the {0} substitution parameter will be replaced with the name of the input component on which the converter is registered.

Two of the standard converters (DateTimeConverter and NumberConverter) have their own tags, which allow you to configure the format of the component data using the tag attributes. For more information about using DateTimeConverter, see Using DateTimeConverter. For more information about using NumberConverter, see Using NumberConverter. The following section explains how to convert a component's value, including how to register other standard converters with a component.

11.1.1 Converting a Component's Value

To use a particular converter to convert a component's value, you need to register the converter onto the component. You can register any of the standard converters in one of the following ways.

Nest one of the standard converter tags inside the component's tag. These tags are f:convertDateTime and f:convertNumber, which are described in Using DateTimeConverter and Using NumberConverter, respectively.

Bind the value of the component to a managed bean property of the same type as the converter. This is the most common technique.

Refer to the converter from the component tag's converter attribute, specifying the ID of the converter class.

Nest an f:converter tag inside of the component tag, and use either the f:converter tag's converterId attribute or its binding attribute to refer to the converter.

As an example of the second technique, if you want a component's data to be converted to an Integer, you can simply bind the component's value to a managed bean property. Here is an example:

Integer age = 0;
public Integer getAge(){ return age;}
public void setAge(Integer age) {this.age = age;}

The data from the h:inputText tag in the this example will be converted to a java.lang.Integer value. The Integer type is a supported type of NumberConverter. If you don't need to specify any formatting instructions using the f:convertNumber tag attributes, and if one of the standard converters will suffice, you can simply reference that converter by using the component tag's converter attribute.

You can also nest an f:converter tag within the component tag and use either the converter tag's converterId attribute or its binding attribute to reference the converter.

The converterId attribute must reference the converter's ID. Here is an example that uses one of the converter IDs listed in Table 11-1:

<h:inputText value="#{loginBean.age}">
    <f:converter converterId="javax.faces.Integer" />
</h:inputText>

Instead of using the converterId attribute, the f:converter tag can use the binding attribute. The binding attribute must resolve to a bean property that accepts and returns an appropriate Converter instance.

You can also create custom converters and register them on components using the f:converter tag. For details, see Creating and Using a Custom Converter.

11.1.2 Using DateTimeConverter

You can convert a component's data to a java.util.Date by nesting the convertDateTime tag inside the component tag. The convertDateTime tag has several attributes that allow you to specify the format and type of the data. Table 11-2 lists the attributes.

Here is a simple example of a convertDateTime tag:

<h:outputText value="#{cashierBean.shipDate}">
    <f:convertDateTime type="date" dateStyle="full" />
</h:outputText>

When binding the DateTimeConverter to a component, ensure that the managed bean property to which the component is bound is of type java.util.Date. In the preceding example, cashierBean.shipDate must be of type java.util.Date.

The example tag can display the following output:

Saturday, September 21, 2013

You can also display the same date and time by using the following tag in which the date format is specified:

<h:outputText value="#{cashierBean.shipDate}">
    <f:convertDateTime pattern="EEEEEEEE, MMM dd, yyyy" />
</h:outputText>

If you want to display the example date in Spanish, you can use the locale attribute:

<h:outputText value="#{cashierBean.shipDate}">
    <f:convertDateTime dateStyle="full"
                       locale="es"
                       timeStyle="long" type="both" />
</h:outputText>

This tag would display the following output:

jueves 24 de octubre de 2013 15:07:04 GMT

Refer to the "Customizing Formats" lesson of the Java Tutorial at http://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/i18n/format/simpleDateFormat.html for more information on how to format the output using the pattern attribute of the convertDateTime tag.

Table 11-2 Attributes for the f:convertDateTime Tag

Attribute | Type | Description

binding

|

DateTimeConverter

|

Used to bind a converter to a managed bean property.

dateStyle

|

String

|

Defines the format, as specified by java.text.DateFormat, of a date or the date part of a date string. Applied only if type is date or both and if pattern is not defined. Valid values: default, short, medium, long, and full. If no value is specified, default is used.

for

|

String

|

Used with composite components. Refers to one of the objects within the composite component inside which this tag is nested.

locale

|

String or Locale

|

Locale whose predefined styles for dates and times are used during formatting or parsing. If not specified, the Locale returned by FacesContext.getLocale will be used.

pattern

|

String

|

Custom formatting pattern that determines how the date/time string should be formatted and parsed. If this attribute is specified, dateStyle, timeStyle, and type attributes are ignored.

timeStyle

|

String

|

Defines the format, as specified by java.text.DateFormat, of a time or the time part of a date string. Applied only if type is time and pattern is not defined. Valid values: default, short, medium, long, and full. If no value is specified, default is used.

timeZone

|

String or TimeZone

|

Time zone in which to interpret any time information in the date string.

type

|

String

|

Specifies whether the string value will contain a date, a time, or both. Valid values are date, time, or both. If no value is specified, date is used.

11.1.3 Using NumberConverter

You can convert a component's data to a java.lang.Number by nesting the convertNumber tag inside the component tag. The convertNumber tag has several attributes that allow you to specify the format and type of the data. Table 11-3 lists the attributes.

The following example uses a convertNumber tag to display the total prices of the contents of a shopping cart:

<h:outputText value="#{cart.total}">
    <f:convertNumber currencySymbol="$" type="currency"/>
</h:outputText>

When binding the NumberConverter to a component, ensure that the managed bean property to which the component is bound is of a primitive type or has a type of java.lang.Number. In the preceding example, cart.total is of type double.

Here is an example of a number that this tag can display:

$934

This result can also be displayed by using the following tag in which the currency pattern is specified:

<h:outputText id="cartTotal" value="#{cart.total}">
    <f:convertNumber pattern="$####" />
</h:outputText>

See the "Customizing Formats" lesson of the Java Tutorial at http://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/i18n/format/decimalFormat.html for more information on how to format the output by using the pattern attribute of the convertNumber tag.

Table 11-3 Attributes for the f:convertNumber Tag

Attribute | Type | Description

binding

|

NumberConverter

|

Used to bind a converter to a managed bean property.

currencyCode

|

String

|

ISO 4217 currency code, used only when formatting currencies.

currencySymbol

|

String

|

Currency symbol, applied only when formatting currencies.

for

|

String

|

Used with composite components. Refers to one of the objects within the composite component inside which this tag is nested.

groupingUsed

|

Boolean

|

Specifies whether formatted output contains grouping separators.

integerOnly

|

Boolean

|

Specifies whether only the integer part of the value will be parsed.

locale

|

String or Locale

|

Locale whose number styles are used to format or parse data.

maxFractionDigits

|

int

|

Maximum number of digits formatted in the fractional part of the output.

maxIntegerDigits

|

int

|

Maximum number of digits formatted in the integer part of the output.

minFractionDigits

|

int

|

Minimum number of digits formatted in the fractional part of the output.

minIntegerDigits

|

int

|

Minimum number of digits formatted in the integer part of the output.

pattern

|

String

|

Custom formatting pattern that determines how the number string is formatted and parsed.

type

|

String

|

Specifies whether the string value is parsed and formatted as a number, currency, or percentage. If not specified, number is used.

11.2 Registering Listeners on Components

An application developer can implement listeners as classes or as managed bean methods. If a listener is a managed bean method, the page author references the method from either the component's valueChangeListener attribute or its actionListener attribute. If the listener is a class, the page author can reference the listener from either an f:valueChangeListener tag or an f:actionListener tag and nest the tag inside the component tag to register the listener on the component.

Referencing a Method That Handles an Action Event and Referencing a Method That Handles a Value-Change Event explain how a page author uses the valueChangeListener and actionListener attributes to reference managed bean methods that handle events.

This section explains how to register a NameChanged value-change listener and a BookChange action listener implementation on components. The Duke's Bookstore case study includes both of these listeners.

11.2.1 Registering a Value-Change Listener on a Component

A page author can register a ValueChangeListener implementation on a component that implements EditableValueHolder by nesting an f:valueChangeListener tag within the component's tag on the page. The f:valueChangeListener tag supports the attributes shown in Table 11-4, one of which must be used.

Table 11-4 Attributes for the f:valueChangeListener Tag

Attribute | Description

type

|

References the fully qualified class name of a ValueChangeListener implementation. Can accept a literal or a value expression.

binding

|

References an object that implements ValueChangeListener. Can accept only a value expression, which must point to a managed bean property that accepts and returns a ValueChangeListener implementation.

The following example shows a value-change listener registered on a component:

<h:inputText id="name"
             size="30"
             value="#{cashierBean.name}"
             required="true"
             requiredMessage="#{bundle.ReqCustomerName}">
    <f:valueChangeListener
        type="javaeetutorial.dukesbookstore.listeners.NameChanged" />
</h:inputText>

In the example, the core tag type attribute specifies the custom NameChanged listener as the ValueChangeListener implementation registered on the name component.

After this component tag is processed and local values have been validated, its corresponding component instance will queue the ValueChangeEvent associated with the specified ValueChangeListener to the component.

The binding attribute is used to bind a ValueChangeListener implementation to a managed bean property. This attribute works in a similar way to the binding attribute supported by the standard converter tags. See Binding Component Values and Instances to Managed Bean Properties for more information.

11.2.2 Registering an Action Listener on a Component

A page author can register an ActionListener implementation on a command component by nesting an f:actionListener tag within the component's tag on the page. Similarly to the f:valueChangeListener tag, the f:actionListener tag supports both the type and binding attributes. One of these attributes must be used to reference the action listener.

Here is an example of an h:commandLink tag that references an ActionListener implementation:

<h:commandLink id="Duke" action="bookstore">
    <f:actionListener 
        type="javaeetutorial.dukesbookstore.listeners.LinkBookChangeListener" />
    <h:outputText value="#{bundle.Book201}"/>
</h:commandLink>

The type attribute of the f:actionListener tag specifies the fully qualified class name of the ActionListener implementation. Similarly to the f:valueChangeListener tag, the f:actionListener tag also supports the binding attribute. See Binding Converters, Listeners, and Validators to Managed Bean Properties for more information about binding listeners to managed bean properties.

In addition to the actionListener tag that allows you register a custom listener onto a component, the core tag library includes the f:setPropertyActionListener tag. You use this tag to register a special action listener onto the ActionSource instance associated with a component. When the component is activated, the listener will store the object referenced by the tag's value attribute into the object referenced by the tag's target attribute.

The bookcatalog.xhtml page of the Duke's Bookstore application uses f:setPropertyActionListener with two components: the h:commandLink component used to link to the bookdetails.xhtml page and the h:commandButton component used to add a book to the cart:

<h:dataTable id="books"
    value="#{store.books}"
    var="book"
    headerClass="list-header"
    styleClass="list-background"
    rowClasses="list-row-even, list-row-odd"
    border="1"
    summary="#{bundle.BookCatalog}" >
    ...
    <h:column>
        <f:facet name="header">
            <h:outputText value="#{bundle.ItemTitle}"/>
        </f:facet>
        <h:commandLink action="#{catalog.details}"
                       value="#{book.title}">
            <f:setPropertyActionListener target="#{requestScope.book}"
                                         value="#{book}"/>
        </h:commandLink>
    </h:column>
    ...
    <h:column>
        <f:facet name="header">
            <h:outputText value="#{bundle.CartAdd}"/>
        </f:facet>
        <h:commandButton id="add"
                         action="#{catalog.add}"
                         value="#{bundle.CartAdd}">
            <f:setPropertyActionListener target="#{requestScope.book}"
                                         value="#{book}"/>
        </h:commandButton>
    </h:column>

The h:commandLink and h:commandButton tags are within an h:dataTable tag, which iterates over the list of books. The var attribute refers to a single book in the list of books.

The object referenced by the var attribute of an h:dataTable tag is in page scope. However, in this case you need to put this object into request scope so that when the user activates the commandLink component to go to bookdetails.xhtml or activates the commandButton component to go to bookcatalog.xhtml, the book data is available to those pages. Therefore, the f:setPropertyActionListener tag is used to set the current book object into request scope when the commandLink or commandButton component is activated.

In the preceding example, the f:setPropertyActionListener tag's value attribute references the book object. The f:setPropertyActionListener tag's target attribute references the value expression requestScope.book, which is where the book object referenced by the value attribute is stored when the commandLink or the commandButton component is activated.

11.3 Using the Standard Validators

JavaServer Faces technology provides a set of standard classes and associated tags that page authors and application developers can use to validate a component's data. Table 11-5 lists all the standard validator classes and the tags that allow you to use the validators from the page.

Table 11-5 The Validator Classes

Validator Class | Tag | Function

BeanValidator

|

validateBean

|

Registers a bean validator for the component.

DoubleRangeValidator

|

validateDoubleRange

|

Checks whether the local value of a component is within a certain range. The value must be floating-point or convertible to floating-point.

LengthValidator

|

validateLength

|

Checks whether the length of a component's local value is within a certain range. The value must be a java.lang.String.

LongRangeValidator

|

validateLongRange

|

Checks whether the local value of a component is within a certain range. The value must be any numeric type or String that can be converted to a long.

RegexValidator

|

validateRegex

|

Checks whether the local value of a component is a match against a regular expression from the java.util.regex package.

RequiredValidator

|

validateRequired

|

Ensures that the local value is not empty on an EditableValueHolder component.

All of these validator classes implement the Validator interface. Component writers and application developers can also implement this interface to define their own set of constraints for a component's value.

Similar to the standard converters, each of these validators has one or more standard error messages associated with it. If you have registered one of these validators onto a component on your page and the validator is unable to validate the component's value, the validator's error message will display on the page. For example, the error message that displays when the component's value exceeds the maximum value allowed by LongRangeValidator is as follows:

{1}: Validation Error: Value is greater than allowable maximum of "{0}"

In this case, the {1} substitution parameter is replaced by the component's label or id, and the {0} substitution parameter is replaced with the maximum value allowed by the validator.

See Displaying Error Messages with the h:message and h:messages Tags for information on how to display validation error messages on the page when validation fails.

Instead of using the standard validators, you can use Bean Validation to validate data. If you specify bean validation constraints on your managed bean properties, the constraints are automatically placed on the corresponding fields on your applications web pages. See Chapter 21, "Introduction to Bean Validation" for more information. You do not need to specify the validateBean tag to use Bean Validation, but the tag allows you to use more advanced Bean Validation features. For example, you can use the validationGroups attribute of the tag to specify constraint groups.

You can also create and register custom validators, although Bean Validation has made this feature less useful. For details, see Creating and Using a Custom Validator.

11.3.1 Validating a Component's Value

To validate a component's value using a particular validator, you need to register that validator on the component. You can do this in one of the following ways.

Nest the validator's corresponding tag (shown in Table 11-5) inside the component's tag. Using Validator Tags explains how to use the validateLongRange tag. You can use the other standard tags in the same way.

Refer to a method that performs the validation from the component tag's validator attribute.

Nest a validator tag inside the component tag, and use either the validator tag's validatorId attribute or its binding attribute to refer to the validator.

See Referencing a Method That Performs Validation for more information on using the validator attribute.

The validatorId attribute works similarly to the converterId attribute of the converter tag, as described in Converting a Component's Value.

Keep in mind that validation can be performed only on components that implement EditableValueHolder, because these components accept values that can be validated.

11.3.2 Using Validator Tags

The following example shows how to use the f:validateLongRange validator tag on an input component named quantity:

<h:inputText id="quantity" size="4" value="#{item.quantity}">
    <f:validateLongRange minimum="1"/>
</h:inputText>
<h:message for="quantity"/>

This tag requires the user to enter a number that is at least 1. The validateLongRange tag also has a maximum attribute, which sets a maximum value for the input.

The attributes of all the standard validator tags accept EL value expressions. This means that the attributes can reference managed bean properties rather than specify literal values. For example, the f:validateLongRange tag in the preceding example can reference managed bean properties called minimum and maximum to get the minimum and maximum values acceptable to the validator implementation, as shown in this snippet from the guessnumber-jsf example:

<h:inputText id="userNo"
             title="Type a number from 0 to 10:"
             value="#{userNumberBean.userNumber}">
    <f:validateLongRange minimum="#{userNumberBean.minimum}"
                         maximum="#{userNumberBean.maximum}"/>
</h:inputText>

The following f:validateRegex tag shows how you might ensure that a password is from 4 to 10 characters long and contains at least one digit, at least one lowercase letter, and at least one uppercase letter:

<f:validateRegex pattern="((?=.*\d)(?=.*[a-z])(?=.*[A-Z]).{4,10})"
                 for="passwordVal"/>

11.4 Referencing a Managed Bean Method

A component tag has a set of attributes for referencing managed bean methods that can perform certain functions for the component associated with the tag. These attributes are summarized in Table 11-6.

Table 11-6 Component Tag Attributes That Reference Managed Bean Methods

Attribute | Function

action

|

Refers to a managed bean method that performs navigation processing for the component and returns a logical outcome String

actionListener

|

Refers to a managed bean method that handles action events

validator

|

Refers to a managed bean method that performs validation on the component's value

valueChangeListener

|

Refers to a managed bean method that handles value-change events

Only components that implement ActionSource can use the action and actionListener attributes. Only components that implement EditableValueHolder can use the validator or valueChangeListener attributes.

The component tag refers to a managed bean method using a method expression as a value of one of the attributes. The method referenced by an attribute must follow a particular signature, which is defined by the tag attribute's definition in the documentation at http://docs.oracle.com/javaee/7/javaserverfaces/2.2/vdldocs/facelets/. For example, the definition of the validator attribute of the inputText tag is the following:

void validate(javax.faces.context.FacesContext,
              javax.faces.component.UIComponent, java.lang.Object)

The following sections give examples of how to use the attributes.

11.4.1 Referencing a Method That Performs Navigation

If your page includes a component, such as a button or a link, that causes the application to navigate to another page when the component is activated, the tag corresponding to this component must include an action attribute. This attribute does one of the following:

Specifies a logical outcome String that tells the application which page to access next

References a managed bean method that performs some processing and returns a logical outcome String

The following example shows how to reference a navigation method:

<h:commandButton value="#{bundle.Submit}"
                 action="#{cashierBean.submit}" />

See Writing a Method to Handle Navigation for information on how to write such a method.

11.4.2 Referencing a Method That Handles an Action Event

If a component on your page generates an action event, and if that event is handled by a managed bean method, you refer to the method by using the component's actionListener attribute.

The following example shows how such a method could be referenced:

<h:commandLink id="Duke" action="bookstore"
               actionListener="#{actionBean.chooseBookFromLink}">

The actionListener attribute of this component tag references the chooseBookFromLink method using a method expression. The chooseBookFromLink method handles the event when the user clicks the link rendered by this component. See Writing a Method to Handle an Action Event for information on how to write such a method.

11.4.3 Referencing a Method That Performs Validation

If the input of one of the components on your page is validated by a managed bean method, refer to the method from the component's tag by using the validator attribute.

The following simplified example from The guessnumber-cdi CDI Example shows how to reference a method that performs validation on inputGuess, an input component:

<h:inputText id="inputGuess" 
    value="#{userNumberBean.userNumber}" 
    required="true" size="3" 
    disabled="#{userNumberBean.number eq userNumberBean.userNumber ...}"
    validator="#{userNumberBean.validateNumberRange}">
</h:inputText>

The managed bean method validateNumberRange verifies that the input value is within the valid range, which changes each time another guess is made. See Writing a Method to Perform Validation for information on how to write such a method.

11.4.4 Referencing a Method That Handles a Value-Change Event

If you want a component on your page to generate a value-change event and you want that event to be handled by a managed bean method instead of a ValueChangeListener implementation, you refer to the method by using the component's valueChangeListener attribute:

<h:inputText id="name"
             size="30"
             value="#{cashierBean.name}"
             required="true"
             valueChangeListener="#{cashierBean.processValueChange}" />
</h:inputText>

The valueChangeListener attribute of this component tag references the processValueChange method of CashierBean by using a method expression. The processValueChange method handles the event of a user entering a name in the input field rendered by this component.

Writing a Method to Handle a Value-Change Event describes how to implement a method that handles a ValueChangeEvent.

5 Packaging

This chapter describes packaging. A Java EE application is packaged into one or more standard units for deployment to any Java EE platform–compliant system. Each unit contains a functional component or components, such as an enterprise bean, web page, servlet, or applet, and an optional deployment descriptor that describes its content.

The following topics are addressed here:

Packaging Applications

Packaging Enterprise Beans

Packaging Web Archives

Packaging Resource Adapter Archives

5.1 Packaging Applications

A Java EE application is delivered in a Java Archive (JAR) file, a Web Archive (WAR) file, or an Enterprise Archive (EAR) file. A WAR or EAR file is a standard JAR (.jar) file with a .war or .ear extension. Using JAR, WAR, and EAR files and modules makes it possible to assemble a number of different Java EE applications using some of the same components. No extra coding is needed; it is only a matter of assembling (or packaging) various Java EE modules into Java EE JAR, WAR, or EAR files.

An EAR file (see Figure 5-1) contains Java EE modules and, optionally, deployment descriptors. A deployment descriptor, an XML document with an .xml extension, describes the deployment settings of an application, a module, or a component. Because deployment descriptor information is declarative, it can be changed without the need to modify the source code. At runtime, the Java EE server reads the deployment descriptor and acts upon the application, module, or component accordingly.

Deployment information is most commonly specified in the source code by annotations. Deployment descriptors, if present, override what is specified in the source code.

Figure 5-1 EAR File Structure

Description of "Figure 5-1 EAR File Structure"

The two types of deployment descriptors are Java EE and runtime. A Java EE deployment descriptor is defined by a Java EE specification and can be used to configure deployment settings on any Java EE-compliant implementation. A runtime deployment descriptor is used to configure Java EE implementation-specific parameters. For example, the GlassFish Server runtime deployment descriptor contains such information as the context root of a web application as well as GlassFish Server implementation-specific parameters, such as caching directives. The GlassFish Server runtime deployment descriptors are named glassfish-moduleType.xml and are located in the same META-INF directory as the Java EE deployment descriptor.

A Java EE module consists of one or more Java EE components for the same container type and, optionally, one component deployment descriptor of that type. An enterprise bean module deployment descriptor, for example, declares transaction attributes and security authorizations for an enterprise bean. A Java EE module can be deployed as a stand-alone module.

Java EE modules are of the following types:

EJB modules, which contain class files for enterprise beans and, optionally, an EJB deployment descriptor. EJB modules are packaged as JAR files with a .jar extension.

Web modules, which contain servlet class files, web files, supporting class files, GIF and HTML files, and, optionally, a web application deployment descriptor. Web modules are packaged as JAR files with a .war (web archive) extension.

Application client modules, which contain class files and, optionally, an application client deployment descriptor. Application client modules are packaged as JAR files with a .jar extension.

Resource adapter modules, which contain all Java interfaces, classes, native libraries, and, optionally, a resource adapter deployment descriptor. Together, these implement the Connector architecture (see Java EE Connector Architecture) for a particular EIS. Resource adapter modules are packaged as JAR files with an .rar (resource adapter archive) extension.

5.2 Packaging Enterprise Beans

This section explains how enterprise beans can be packaged in EJB JAR or WAR modules.

5.2.1 Packaging Enterprise Beans in EJB JAR Modules

An EJB JAR file is portable and can be used for various applications.

To assemble a Java EE application, package one or more modules, such as EJB JAR files, into an EAR file, the archive file that holds the application. When deploying the EAR file that contains the enterprise bean's EJB JAR file, you also deploy the enterprise bean to GlassFish Server. You can also deploy an EJB JAR that is not contained in an EAR file. Figure 5-2 shows the contents of an EJB JAR file.

Figure 5-2 Structure of an Enterprise Bean JAR

Description of "Figure 5-2 Structure of an Enterprise Bean JAR"

5.2.2 Packaging Enterprise Beans in WAR Modules

Enterprise beans often provide the business logic of a web application. In these cases, packaging the enterprise bean within the web application's WAR module simplifies deployment and application organization. Enterprise beans may be packaged within a WAR module as Java programming language class files or within a JAR file that is bundled within the WAR module.

To include enterprise bean class files in a WAR module, the class files should be in the WEB-INF/classes directory.

To include a JAR file that contains enterprise beans in a WAR module, add the JAR to the WEB-INF/lib directory of the WAR module.

WAR modules that contain enterprise beans do not require an ejb-jar.xml deployment descriptor. If the application uses ejb-jar.xml, it must be located in the WAR module's WEB-INF directory.

JAR files that contain enterprise bean classes packaged within a WAR module are not considered EJB JAR files, even if the bundled JAR file conforms to the format of an EJB JAR file. The enterprise beans contained within the JAR file are semantically equivalent to enterprise beans located in the WAR module's WEB-INF/classes directory, and the environment namespace of all the enterprise beans are scoped to the WAR module.

For example, suppose that a web application consists of a shopping cart enterprise bean, a credit card–processing enterprise bean, and a Java servlet front end. The shopping cart bean exposes a local, no-interface view and is defined as follows:

package com.example.cart;

@Stateless
public class CartBean { ... }

The credit card–processing bean is packaged within its own JAR file, cc.jar, exposes a local, no-interface view, and is defined as follows:

package com.example.cc;

@Stateless
public class CreditCardBean { ... }

The servlet, com.example.web.StoreServlet, handles the web front end and uses both CartBean and CreditCardBean. The WAR module layout for this application is as follows:

WEB-INF/classes/com/example/cart/CartBean.class
WEB-INF/classes/com/example/web/StoreServlet
WEB-INF/lib/cc.jar
WEB-INF/ejb-jar.xml
WEB-INF/web.xml

5.3 Packaging Web Archives

In the Java EE architecture, a web module is the smallest deployable and usable unit of web resources. A web module contains web components and static web content files, such as images, which are called web resources. A Java EE web module corresponds to a web application as defined in the Java Servlet specification.

In addition to web components and web resources, a web module can contain other files:

Server-side utility classes, such as shopping carts

Client-side classes, such as utility classes

A web module has a specific structure. The top-level directory of a web module is the document root of the application. The document root is where XHTML pages, client-side classes and archives, and static web resources, such as images, are stored.

The document root contains a subdirectory named WEB-INF, which can contain the following files and directories:

classes, a directory that contains server-side classes: servlets, enterprise bean class files, utility classes, and JavaBeans components

lib, a directory that contains JAR files that contain enterprise beans, and JAR archives of libraries called by server-side classes

Deployment descriptors, such as web.xml (the web application deployment descriptor) and ejb-jar.xml (an EJB deployment descriptor)

A web module needs a web.xml file if it uses JavaServer Faces technology, if it must specify certain kinds of security information, or if you want to override information specified by web component annotations.

You can also create application-specific subdirectories (that is, package directories) in either the document root or the WEB-INF/classes/ directory.

A web module can be deployed as an unpacked file structure or can be packaged in a JAR file known as a Web Archive (WAR) file. Because the contents and use of WAR files differ from those of JAR files, WAR file names use a .war extension. The web module just described is portable; you can deploy it into any web container that conforms to the Java Servlet specification.

You can provide a runtime deployment descriptor (DD) when you deploy a WAR on GlassFish Server, but it is not required under most circumstances. The runtime DD is an XML file that may contain such information as the context root of the web application, the mapping of the portable names of an application's resources to GlassFish Server resources, and the mapping of an application's security roles to users, groups, and principals defined in GlassFish Server. The GlassFish Server web application runtime DD, if used, is named glassfish-web.xml and is located in the WEB-INF directory. The structure of a web module that can be deployed on GlassFish Server is shown in Figure 5-3.

Figure 5-3 Web Module Structure

Description of "Figure 5-3 Web Module Structure"

5.4 Packaging Resource Adapter Archives

A Resource Adapter Archive (RAR) file stores XML files, Java classes, and other objects for Java EE Connector Architecture (JCA) applications. A resource adapter can be deployed on any Java EE server, much like a Java EE application. A RAR file can be contained in an Enterprise Archive (EAR) file, or it can exist as a separate file.

The RAR file contains

A JAR file with the implementation classes of the resource adapter

An optional META-INF/ directory that can store an ra.xml file and/or an application server–specific deployment descriptor used for configuration purposes

A RAR file can be deployed on the application server as a standalone component or as part of a larger application. In both cases, the adapter is available to all applications using a lookup procedure.

38 Running the Persistence Examples

This chapter explains how to use the Java Persistence API. The material here focuses on the source code and settings of three examples. The first example, order, is an application that uses a stateful session bean to manage entities related to an ordering system. The second example, roster, is an application that manages a community sports system. The third example, address-book, is a web application that stores contact data. This chapter assumes that you are familiar with the concepts detailed in Chapter 37, "Introduction to the Java Persistence API".

The following topics are addressed here:

The order Application

The roster Application

The address-book Application

38.1 The order Application

The order application is a simple inventory and ordering application for maintaining a catalog of parts and placing an itemized order of those parts. The application has entities that represent parts, vendors, orders, and line items. These entities are accessed using a stateful session bean that holds the business logic of the application. A simple singleton session bean creates the initial entities on application deployment. A Facelets web application manipulates the data and displays data from the catalog.

The information contained in an order can be divided into elements. What is the order number? What parts are included in the order? What parts make up that part? Who makes the part? What are the specifications for the part? Are there any schematics for the part? The order application is a simplified version of an ordering system that has all these elements.

The order application consists of a single WAR module that includes the enterprise bean classes, the entities, the support classes, and the Facelets XHTML and class files.

The database schema in the Java DB database for order is shown in Figure 38-1.

Figure 38-1 Database Schema for the order Application

Description of "Figure 38-1 Database Schema for the order Application"

Note:

In this diagram, for simplicity, the PERSISTENCE_ORDER_ prefix is omitted from the table names.

38.1.1 Entity Relationships in the order Application

The order application demonstrates several types of entity relationships: self-referential, one-to-one, one-to-many, many-to-one, and unidirectional relationships.

38.1.1.1 Self-Referential Relationships

A self-referential relationship occurs between relationship fields in the same entity. Part has a field, bomPart, which has a one-to-many relationship with the field parts, which is also in Part. That is, a part can be made up of many parts, and each of those parts has exactly one bill-of-material part.

The primary key for Part is a compound primary key, a combination of the partNumber and revision fields. This key is mapped to the PARTNUMBER and REVISION columns in the PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART table:

...
@ManyToOne
@JoinColumns({
    @JoinColumn(name="BOMPARTNUMBER", referencedColumnName="PARTNUMBER"),
    @JoinColumn(name="BOMREVISION", referencedColumnName="REVISION")
})
public Part getBomPart() {
    return bomPart;
}
...
@OneToMany(mappedBy="bomPart")
public Collection<Part> getParts() {
    return parts;
}
...

38.1.1.2 One-to-One Relationships

Part has a field, vendorPart, that has a one-to-one relationship with VendorPart's part field. That is, each part has exactly one vendor part, and vice versa.

Here is the relationship mapping in Part:

@OneToOne(mappedBy="part")
public VendorPart getVendorPart() {
    return vendorPart;
}

Here is the relationship mapping in VendorPart:

@OneToOne
@JoinColumns({
    @JoinColumn(name="PARTNUMBER", referencedColumnName="PARTNUMBER"),
    @JoinColumn(name="PARTREVISION", referencedColumnName="REVISION")
})
public Part getPart() {
    return part;
}

Note that, because Part uses a compound primary key, the @JoinColumns annotation is used to map the columns in the PERSISTENCE_ORDER_VENDOR_PART table to the columns in PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART. The PERSISTENCE_ORDER_VENDOR_PART table's PARTREVISION column refers to PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART's REVISION column.

38.1.1.3 One-to-Many Relationship Mapped to Overlapping Primary and Foreign Keys

CustomerOrder has a field, lineItems, that has a one-to-many relationship with LineItem's field customerOrder. That is, each order has one or more line item.

LineItem uses a compound primary key that is made up of the orderId and itemId fields. This compound primary key maps to the ORDERID and ITEMID columns in the PERSISTENCE_ORDER_LINEITEM table. ORDERID is a foreign key to the ORDERID column in the PERSISTENCE_ORDER_CUSTOMERORDER table. This means that the ORDERID column is mapped twice: once as a primary key field, orderId; and again as a relationship field, order.

Here is the relationship mapping in CustomerOrder:

@OneToMany(cascade=ALL, mappedBy="customerOrder")
public Collection<LineItem> getLineItems() {
    return lineItems;
}

Here is the relationship mapping in LineItem:

@Id
@ManyToOne
@JoinColumn(name="ORDERID")
public CustomerOrder getCustomerOrder() {
    return customerOrder;
}

38.1.1.4 Unidirectional Relationships

LineItem has a field, vendorPart, that has a unidirectional many-to-one relationship with VendorPart. That is, there is no field in the target entity in this relationship:

@JoinColumn(name="VENDORPARTNUMBER")
@ManyToOne
public VendorPart getVendorPart() {
    return vendorPart;
}

38.1.2 Primary Keys in the order Application

The order application uses several types of primary keys: single-valued primary keys, generated primary keys, and compound primary keys.

38.1.2.1 Generated Primary Keys

VendorPart uses a generated primary key value. That is, the application does not assign primary key values for the entities but instead relies on the persistence provider to generate the primary key values. The @GeneratedValue annotation is used to specify that an entity will use a generated primary key.

In VendorPart, the following code specifies the settings for generating primary key values:

@TableGenerator(
    name="vendorPartGen",
    table="PERSISTENCE_ORDER_SEQUENCE_GENERATOR",
    pkColumnName="GEN_KEY",
    valueColumnName="GEN_VALUE",
    pkColumnValue="VENDOR_PART_ID",
    allocationSize=10)
@Id
@GeneratedValue(strategy=GenerationType.TABLE, generator="vendorPartGen")
public Long getVendorPartNumber() {
    return vendorPartNumber;
}

The @TableGenerator annotation is used in conjunction with @GeneratedValue's strategy=TABLE element. That is, the strategy used to generate the primary keys is to use a table in the database. The @TableGenerator annotation is used to configure the settings for the generator table. The name element sets the name of the generator, which is vendorPartGen in VendorPart.

The PERSISTENCE_ORDER_SEQUENCE_GENERATOR table, whose two columns are GEN_KEY and GEN_VALUE, will store the generated primary key values. This table could be used to generate other entities' primary keys, so the pkColumnValue element is set to VENDOR_PART_ID to distinguish this entity's generated primary keys from other entities' generated primary keys. The allocationSize element specifies the amount to increment when allocating primary key values. In this case, each VendorPart's primary key will increment by 10.

The primary key field vendorPartNumber is of type Long, as the generated primary key's field must be an integral type.

38.1.2.2 Compound Primary Keys

A compound primary key is made up of multiple fields and follows the requirements described in Primary Keys in Entities. To use a compound primary key, you must create a wrapper class.

In order, two entities use compound primary keys: Part and LineItem.

Part uses the PartKey wrapper class. Part's primary key is a combination of the part number and the revision number. PartKey encapsulates this primary key.

LineItem uses the LineItemKey class. LineItem's primary key is a combination of the order number and the item number. LineItemKey encapsulates this primary key.

This is the LineItemKey compound primary key wrapper class:

package javaeetutorial.order.entity;

import java.io.Serializable;

public final class LineItemKey implements Serializable {

    private Integer customerOrder;
    private int itemId;

    public LineItemKey() {}

    public LineItemKey(Integer order, int itemId) {
        this.setCustomerOrder(order);
        this.setItemId(itemId);
    } 

    @Override
    public int hashCode() {
        return ((this.getCustomerOrder() == null
                ? 0 : this.getCustomerOrder().hashCode())
                ^ ((int) this.getItemId()));
    }

    @Override
    public boolean equals(Object otherOb) {
        if (this == otherOb) {
            return true;
        }
        if (!(otherOb instanceof LineItemKey)) {
            return false;
        }
        LineItemKey other = (LineItemKey) otherOb;
        return ((this.getCustomerOrder() == null
                ? other.getCustomerOrder == null : this.getOrderId()
                .equals(other.getCustomerOrder())) 
                && (this.getItemId == oother.getItemId()));
    }

    @Override
    public String toString() {
        return "" + getCustomerOrder() + "-" + getItemId();
    }

    public Integer getCustomerOrder() {
        return customerOrder;
    }

    public void setCustomerOrder(Integer order) {
        this.customerOrder = order;
    }

    public int getItemId() {
        return itemId;
    }

    public void setItemId(int itemId) {
        this.itemId = itemId;
    }
}

The @IdClass annotation is used to specify the primary key class in the entity class. In LineItem, @IdClass is used as follows:

@IdClass(LineItemKey.class)
@Entity
...
public class LineItem implements Serializable {
    ...
}

The two fields in LineItem are tagged with the @Id annotation to mark those fields as part of the compound primary key:

@Id
public int getItemId() {
    return itemId;
}
...
@Id
@ManyToOne
@JoinColumn(name="ORDERID")
public CustomerOrder getCustomerOrder() {
    return customerOrder;
}

For customerOrder, you also use the @JoinColumn annotation to specify the column name in the table and that this column is an overlapping foreign key pointing at the PERSISTENCE_ORDER_CUSTOMERORDER table's ORDERID column (see One-to-Many Relationship Mapped to Overlapping Primary and Foreign Keys). That is, customerOrder will be set by the CustomerOrder entity.

In LineItem's constructor, the line item number (LineItem.itemId) is set using the CustomerOrder.getNextId method:

public LineItem(CustomerOrder order, int quantity, VendorPart vendorPart) {
    this.customerOrder = order;
    this.itemId = order.getNextId();
    this.quantity = quantity;
    this.vendorPart = vendorPart;
}

CustomerOrder.getNextId counts the number of current line items, adds 1, and returns that number:

@Transient
public int getNextId() {
    return this.lineItems.size() + 1;
}

Part requires the @Column annotation on the two fields that comprise Part's compound primary key, because Part's compound primary key is an overlapping primary key/foreign key:

@IdClass(PartKey.class)
@Entity
...
public class Part implements Serializable {
    ...
    @Id
    @Column(nullable=false)
    public String getPartNumber() {
        return partNumber;
    }
    ...
    @Id
    @Column(nullable=false)
    public int getRevision() {
        return revision;
    }
    ...
}

38.1.3 Entity Mapped to More Than One Database Table

Part's fields map to more than one database table: PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART and PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART_DETAIL. The PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART_DETAIL table holds the specification and schematics for the part. The @SecondaryTable annotation is used to specify the secondary table:

...
@Entity
@Table(name="PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART")
@SecondaryTable(name="PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART_DETAIL", pkJoinColumns={
    @PrimaryKeyJoinColumn(name="PARTNUMBER",
        referencedColumnName="PARTNUMBER"),
    @PrimaryKeyJoinColumn(name="REVISION",
        referencedColumnName="REVISION")
})
public class Part implements Serializable {
    ...
}

PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART_DETAIL and PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART share the same primary key values. The pkJoinColumns element of @SecondaryTable is used to specify that PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART_DETAIL's primary key columns are foreign keys to PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART. The @PrimaryKeyJoinColumn annotation sets the primary key column names and specifies which column in the primary table the column refers to. In this case, the primary key column names for both PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART_DETAIL and PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART are the same: PARTNUMBER and REVISION, respectively.

38.1.4 Cascade Operations in the order Application

Entities that have relationships to other entities often have dependencies on the existence of the other entity in the relationship. For example, a line item is part of an order; if the order is deleted, then the line item also should be deleted. This is called a cascade delete relationship.

In order, there are two cascade delete dependencies in the entity relationships. If the CustomerOrder to which a LineItem is related is deleted, the LineItem also should be deleted. If the Vendor to which a VendorPart is related is deleted, the VendorPart also should be deleted.

You specify the cascade operations for entity relationships by setting the cascade element in the inverse (nonowning) side of the relationship. The cascade element is set to ALL in the case of CustomerOrder.lineItems. This means that all persistence operations (deletes, updates, and so on) are cascaded from orders to line items.

Here is the relationship mapping in CustomerOrder:

@OneToMany(cascade=ALL, mappedBy="customerOrder")
public Collection<LineItem> getLineItems() {
    return lineItems;
}

Here is the relationship mapping in LineItem:

@Id
@ManyToOne
@JoinColumn(name="ORDERID")
public CustomerOrder getCustomerOrder() {
    return customerOrder;
}

38.1.5 BLOB and CLOB Database Types in the order Application

The PARTDETAIL table in the database has a column, DRAWING, of type BLOB. BLOB stands for binary large objects, which are used for storing binary data, such as an image. The DRAWING column is mapped to the field Part.drawing of type java.io.Serializable. The @Lob annotation is used to denote that the field is a large object:

@Column(table="PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART_DETAIL")
@Lob
public Serializable getDrawing() {
    return drawing;
}

PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART_DETAIL also has a column, SPECIFICATION, of type CLOB. CLOB stands for character large objects, which are used to store string data too large to be stored in a VARCHAR column. SPECIFICATION is mapped to the field Part.specification of type java.lang.String. The @Lob annotation is also used here to denote that the field is a large object:

@Column(table="PERSISTENCE_ORDER_PART_DETAIL")
@Lob
public String getSpecification() {
    return specification;
}

Both of these fields use the @Column annotation and set the table element to the secondary table.

38.1.6 Temporal Types in the order Application

The CustomerOrder.lastUpdate persistent property, which is of type java.util.Date, is mapped to the PERSISTENCE_ORDER_CUSTOMERORDER.LASTUPDATE database field, which is of the SQL type TIMESTAMP. To ensure the proper mapping between these types, you must use the @Temporal annotation with the proper temporal type specified in @Temporal's element. @Temporal's elements are of type javax.persistence.TemporalType. The possible values are

DATE, which maps to java.sql.Date

TIME, which maps to java.sql.Time

TIMESTAMP, which maps to java.sql.Timestamp

Here is the relevant section of CustomerOrder:

@Temporal(TIMESTAMP)
public Date getLastUpdate() {
    return lastUpdate;
}

38.1.7 Managing the order Application's Entities

The RequestBean stateful session bean contains the business logic and manages the entities of order. RequestBean uses the @PersistenceContext annotation to retrieve an entity manager instance, which is used to manage order's entities in RequestBean's business methods:

@PersistenceContext
private EntityManager em;

This EntityManager instance is a container-managed entity manager, so the container takes care of all the transactions involved in managing order's entities.

38.1.7.1 Creating Entities

The RequestBean.createPart business method creates a new Part entity. The EntityManager.persist method is used to persist the newly created entity to the database:

Part part = new Part(partNumber,
        revision,
        description,
        revisionDate,
        specification,
        drawing);
em.persist(part);

The ConfigBean singleton session bean is used to initialize the data in order. ConfigBean is annotated with @Startup, which indicates that the EJB container should create ConfigBean when order is deployed. The createData method is annotated with @PostConstruct and creates the initial entities used by order by calling RequestBean's business methods.

38.1.7.2 Finding Entities

The RequestBean.getOrderPrice business method returns the price of a given order based on the orderId. The EntityManager.find method is used to retrieve the entity from the database:

CustomerOrder order = em.find(CustomerOrder.class, orderId);

The first argument of EntityManager.find is the entity class, and the second is the primary key.

38.1.7.3 Setting Entity Relationships

The RequestBean.createVendorPart business method creates a VendorPart associated with a particular Vendor. The EntityManager.persist method is used to persist the newly created VendorPart entity to the database, and the VendorPart.setVendor and Vendor.setVendorPart methods are used to associate the VendorPart with the Vendor:

PartKey pkey = new PartKey();
pkey.setPartNumber(partNumber);
pkey.setRevision(revision);

Part part = em.find(Part.class, pkey);

VendorPart vendorPart = new VendorPart(description, price, part);
em.persist(vendorPart);

Vendor vendor = em.find(Vendor.class, vendorId);
vendor.addVendorPart(vendorPart);
vendorPart.setVendor(vendor);

38.1.7.4 Using Queries

The RequestBean.adjustOrderDiscount business method updates the discount applied to all orders. This method uses the findAllOrders named query, defined in CustomerOrder:

@NamedQuery(
    name="findAllOrders",
    query="SELECT co FROM CustomerOrder co " +
          "ORDER BY co.orderId"
)

The EntityManager.createNamedQuery method is used to run the query. Because the query returns a List of all the orders, the Query.getResultList method is used:

List orders = em.createNamedQuery(
        "findAllOrders")
        .getResultList();

The RequestBean.getTotalPricePerVendor business method returns the total price of all the parts for a particular vendor. This method uses a named parameter, id, defined in the named query findTotalVendorPartPricePerVendor defined in VendorPart:

@NamedQuery(
    name="findTotalVendorPartPricePerVendor",
    query="SELECT SUM(vp.price) " +
    "FROM VendorPart vp " +
    "WHERE vp.vendor.vendorId = :id"
)

When running the query, the Query.setParameter method is used to set the named parameter id to the value of vendorId, the parameter to RequestBean.getTotalPricePerVendor:

return (Double) em.createNamedQuery(
    "findTotalVendorPartPricePerVendor")
    .setParameter("id", vendorId)
    .getSingleResult();

The Query.getSingleResult method is used for this query because the query returns a single value.

38.1.7.5 Removing Entities

The RequestBean.removeOrder business method deletes a given order from the database. This method uses the EntityManager.remove method to delete the entity from the database:

CustomerOrder order = em.find(CustomerOrder.class, orderId);
em.remove(order);

38.1.8 Running the order Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the order application. First, you will create the database tables in the Java DB server.

38.1.8.1 To Run the order Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

If the database server is not already running, start it by following the instructions in Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server.

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/persistence

Select the order folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the order project and select Run.

NetBeans IDE opens a web browser to the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/order/

38.1.8.2 To Run the order Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

If the database server is not already running, start it by following the instructions in Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server.

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/persistence/order/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This compiles the source files and packages the application into a WAR file located at tut-install/examples/persistence/order/target/order.war. Then the WAR file is deployed to your GlassFish Server instance.

To create and update the order data, open a web browser to the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/order/

38.2 The roster Application

The roster application maintains the team rosters for players in recreational sports leagues. The application has four components: Java Persistence API entities (Player, Team, and League), a stateful session bean (RequestBean), an application client (RosterClient), and three helper classes (PlayerDetails, TeamDetails, and LeagueDetails).

Functionally, roster is similar to the order application, with three new features that order does not have: many-to-many relationships, entity inheritance, and automatic table creation at deployment time.

The database schema in the Java DB database for the roster application is shown in Figure 38-2.

Figure 38-2 Database Schema for the roster Application

Description of "Figure 38-2 Database Schema for the roster Application"

Note:

In this diagram, for simplicity, the PERSISTENCE_ROSTER_ prefix is omitted from the table names.

38.2.1 Relationships in the roster Application

A recreational sports system has the following relationships.

A player can be on many teams.

A team can have many players.

A team is in exactly one league.

A league has many teams.

In roster this system is reflected by the following relationships between the Player, Team, and League entities.

There is a many-to-many relationship between Player and Team.

There is a many-to-one relationship between Team and League.

38.2.1.1 The Many-To-Many Relationship in roster

The many-to-many relationship between Player and Team is specified by using the @ManyToMany annotation. In Team.java, the @ManyToMany annotation decorates the getPlayers method:

@ManyToMany
@JoinTable(
    name="PERSISTENCE_ROSTER_TEAM_PLAYER",
    joinColumns=
        @JoinColumn(name="TEAM_ID", referencedColumnName="ID"),
    inverseJoinColumns=
        @JoinColumn(name="PLAYER_ID", referencedColumnName="ID")
)
public Collection<Player> getPlayers() {
    return players;
}

The @JoinTable annotation is used to specify a database table that will associate player IDs with team IDs. The entity that specifies the @JoinTable is the owner of the relationship, so the Team entity is the owner of the relationship with the Player entity. Because roster uses automatic table creation at deployment time, the container will create a join table named PERSISTENCE_ROSTER_TEAM_PLAYER.

Player is the inverse, or nonowning, side of the relationship with Team. As one-to-one and many-to-one relationships, the nonowning side is marked by the mappedBy element in the relationship annotation. Because the relationship between Player and Team is bidirectional, the choice of which entity is the owner of the relationship is arbitrary.

In Player.java, the @ManyToMany annotation decorates the getTeams method:

@ManyToMany(mappedBy="players")
public Collection<Team> getTeams() {
    return teams;
}

38.2.2 Entity Inheritance in the roster Application

The roster application shows how to use entity inheritance, as described in Entity Inheritance.

The League entity in roster is an abstract entity with two concrete subclasses: SummerLeague and WinterLeague. Because League is an abstract class, it cannot be instantiated:

@Entity
@Table(name = "PERSISTENCE_ROSTER_LEAGUE")
public abstract class League implements Serializable { ... }

Instead, when creating a league, clients use SummerLeague or WinterLeague. SummerLeague and WinterLeague inherit the persistent properties defined in League and add only a constructor that verifies that the sport parameter matches the type of sport allowed in that seasonal league. For example, here is the SummerLeague entity:

...
@Entity
public class SummerLeague extends League implements Serializable {

    /** Creates a new instance of SummerLeague */
    public SummerLeague() {
    }

    public SummerLeague(String id, String name, String sport) 
            throws IncorrectSportException {
        this.id = id;
        this.name = name;
        if (sport.equalsIgnoreCase("swimming") ||
                sport.equalsIgnoreCase("soccer") ||
                sport.equalsIgnoreCase("basketball") ||
                sport.equalsIgnoreCase("baseball")) {
            this.sport = sport;
        } else {
            throw new IncorrectSportException("Sport is not a summer sport.");
        }
    }
}

The roster application uses the default mapping strategy of InheritanceType.SINGLE_TABLE, so the @Inheritance annotation is not required. If you want to use a different mapping strategy, decorate League with @Inheritance and specify the mapping strategy in the strategy element:

@Entity
@Inheritance(strategy=JOINED)
@Table(name="PERSISTENCE_ROSTER_LEAGUE")
public abstract class League implements Serializable { ... }

The roster application uses the default discriminator column name, so the @DiscriminatorColumn annotation is not required. Because you are using automatic table generation in roster, the Persistence provider will create a discriminator column called DTYPE in the PERSISTENCE_ROSTER_LEAGUE table, which will store the name of the inherited entity used to create the league. If you want to use a different name for the discriminator column, decorate League with @DiscriminatorColumn and set the name element:

@Entity
@DiscriminatorColumn(name="DISCRIMINATOR")
@Table(name="PERSISTENCE_ROSTER_LEAGUE")
public abstract class League implements Serializable { ... }

38.2.3 Criteria Queries in the roster Application

The roster application uses Criteria API queries, as opposed to the JPQL queries used in order. Criteria queries are Java programming language, typesafe queries defined in the business tier of roster, in the RequestBean stateful session bean.

38.2.3.1 Metamodel Classes in the roster Application

Metamodel classes model an entity's attributes and are used by Criteria queries to navigate to an entity's attributes. Each entity class in roster has a corresponding metamodel class, generated at compile time, with the same package name as the entity and appended with an underscore character (_). For example, the roster.entity.Player entity has a corresponding metamodel class, roster.entity.Player_.

Each persistent field or property in the entity class has a corresponding attribute in the entity's metamodel class. For the Player entity, the corresponding metamodel class is as follows:

@StaticMetamodel(Player.class)
public class Player_ {
    public static volatile SingularAttribute<Player, String> id;
    public static volatile SingularAttribute<Player, String> name;
    public static volatile SingularAttribute<Player, String> position;
    public static volatile SingularAttribute<Player, Double> salary;
    public static volatile CollectionAttribute<Player, Team> teams;
}

38.2.3.2 Obtaining a CriteriaBuilder Instance in RequestBean

The CriteriaBuilder interface defines methods to create criteria query objects and create expressions for modifying those query objects. RequestBean creates an instance of CriteriaBuilder by using a @PostConstruct method, init:

@PersistenceContext
private EntityManager em;
private CriteriaBuilder cb;

@PostConstruct
private void init() {
    cb = em.getCriteriaBuilder();
}

The EntityManager instance is injected at runtime, and then that EntityManager object is used to create the CriteriaBuilder instance by calling getCriteriaBuilder. The CriteriaBuilder instance is created in a @PostConstruct method to ensure that the EntityManager instance has been injected by the enterprise bean container.

38.2.3.3 Creating Criteria Queries in RequestBean's Business Methods

Many of the business methods in RequestBean define Criteria queries. One business method, getPlayersByPosition, returns a list of players who play a particular position on a team:

public List<PlayerDetails> getPlayersByPosition(String position) {
    logger.info("getPlayersByPosition");
    List<Player> players = null;
    
    try {
        CriteriaQuery<Player> cq = cb.createQuery(Player.class);
        if (cq != null) {
            Root<Player> player = cq.from(Player.class);

            // set the where clause
            cq.where(cb.equal(player.get(Player_.position), position));
            cq.select(player);
            TypedQuery<Player> q = em.createQuery(cq);
            players = q.getResultList();
        }
        return copyPlayersToDetails(players);
    } catch (Exception ex) {
        throw new EJBException(ex);
    }
}

A query object is created by calling the CriteriaBuilder object's createQuery method, with the type set to Player because the query will return a list of players.

The query root, the base entity from which the query will navigate to find the entity's attributes and related entities, is created by calling the from method of the query object. This sets the FROM clause of the query.

The WHERE clause, set by calling the where method on the query object, restricts the results of the query according to the conditions of an expression. The CriteriaBuilder.equal method compares the two expressions. In getPlayersByPosition, the position attribute of the Player_ metamodel class, accessed by calling the get method of the query root, is compared to the position parameter passed to getPlayersByPosition.

The SELECT clause of the query is set by calling the select method of the query object. The query will return Player entities, so the query root object is passed as a parameter to select.

The query object is prepared for execution by calling EntityManager.createQuery, which returns a TypedQuery<T> object with the type of the query, in this case Player. This typed query object is used to execute the query, which occurs when the getResultList method is called, and a List<Player> collection is returned.

38.2.4 Automatic Table Generation in the roster Application

At deployment time, GlassFish Server will automatically drop and create the database tables used by roster. This is done by setting the javax.persistence.schema-generation.database.action property to drop-and-create in persistence.xml:

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<persistence version="2.1" 
    xmlns="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/persistence"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/persistence
        http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/persistence/persistence_2_1.xsd">
  <persistence-unit name="em" transaction-type="JTA">
    <jta-data-source>java:comp/DefaultDataSource</jta-data-source>
    <properties>
      <property name="javax.persistence.schema-generation.database.action" 
                value="drop-and-create"/>
    </properties>
  </persistence-unit>
</persistence>

38.2.5 Running the roster Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the roster application.

38.2.5.1 To Run the roster Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

If the database server is not already running, start it by following the instructions in Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server.

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/persistence

Select the roster folder.

Select the Open Required Projects check box.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the roster project and select Build.

This will compile, package, and deploy the EAR to GlassFish Server.

You will see the following partial output from the application client in the Output tab:

List all players in team T2:
P6 Ian Carlyle goalkeeper 555.0
P7 Rebecca Struthers midfielder 777.0
P8 Anne Anderson forward 65.0
P9 Jan Wesley defender 100.0
P10 Terry Smithson midfielder 100.0

List all teams in league L1:
T1 Honey Bees Visalia
T2 Gophers Manteca
T5 Crows Orland

List all defenders:
P2 Alice Smith defender 505.0
P5 Barney Bold defender 100.0
P9 Jan Wesley defender 100.0
P22 Janice Walker defender 857.0
P25 Frank Fletcher defender 399.0

38.2.5.2 To Run the roster Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

If the database server is not already running, start it by following the instructions in Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server.

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/persistence/roster/roster-ear/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This compiles the source files and packages the application into an EAR file located at tut-install/examples/persistence/roster/target/roster.ear. The EAR file is then deployed to GlassFish Server. GlassFish Server will then drop and create the database tables during deployment, as specified in persistence.xml.

After successfully deploying the EAR, the client stubs are retrieved and the application client is run using the appclient application included with GlassFish Server.

You will see the output, which begins as follows:

[echo] running application client container.
[exec] List all players in team T2:
[exec] P6 Ian Carlyle goalkeeper 555.0
[exec] P7 Rebecca Struthers midfielder 777.0
[exec] P8 Anne Anderson forward 65.0
[exec] P9 Jan Wesley defender 100.0
[exec] P10 Terry Smithson midfielder 100.0

[exec] List all teams in league L1:
[exec] T1 Honey Bees Visalia
[exec] T2 Gophers Manteca
[exec] T5 Crows Orland

[exec] List all defenders:
[exec] P2 Alice Smith defender 505.0
[exec] P5 Barney Bold defender 100.0
[exec] P9 Jan Wesley defender 100.0
[exec] P22 Janice Walker defender 857.0
[exec] P25 Frank Fletcher defender 399.0

38.3 The address-book Application

The address-book example application is a simple web application that stores contact data. It uses a single entity class, Contact, that uses the Java API for JavaBeans Validation (Bean Validation) to validate the data stored in the persistent attributes of the entity, as described in Validating Persistent Fields and Properties.

38.3.1 Bean Validation Constraints in address-book

The Contact entity uses the @NotNull, @Pattern, and @Past constraints on the persistent attributes.

The @NotNull constraint marks the attribute as a required field. The attribute must be set to a non-null value before the entity can be persisted or modified. Bean Validation will throw a validation error if the attribute is null when the entity is persisted or modified.

The @Pattern constraint defines a regular expression that the value of the attribute must match before the entity can be persisted or modified. This constraint has two different uses in address-book.

The regular expression declared in the @Pattern annotation on the email field matches email addresses of the form name@domain name.top level domain, allowing only valid characters for email addresses. For example, username@example.com will pass validation, as will firstname.lastname@mail.example.com. However, firstname,lastname@example.com, which contains an illegal comma character in the local name, will fail validation.

The mobilePhone and homePhone fields are annotated with a @Pattern constraint that defines a regular expression to match phone numbers of the form (xxx) xxx-xxxx.

The @Past constraint is applied to the birthday field, which must be a java.util.Date in the past.

Here are the relevant parts of the Contact entity class:

@Entity
public class Contact implements Serializable {
    @Id
    @GeneratedValue(strategy = GenerationType.AUTO)
    private Long id;
    @NotNull
    protected String firstName;
    @NotNull
    protected String lastName;
    @Pattern(regexp = "[a-z0-9!#$%&'*+/=?^_`{|}~-]+(?:\\."
            + "[a-z0-9!#$%&'*+/=?^_`{|}~-]+)*@"
            + "(?:[a-z0-9](?:[a-z0-9-]*[a-z0-9])?\\.)+[a-z0-9]"
            + "(?:[a-z0-9-]*[a-z0-9])?",
            message = "{invalid.email}")
    protected String email;
    @Pattern(regexp = "^\\(?(\\d{3})\\)?[- ]?(\\d{3})[- ]?(\\d{4})$",
            message = "{invalid.phonenumber}")
    protected String mobilePhone;
    @Pattern(regexp = "^\\(?(\\d{3})\\)?[- ]?(\\d{3})[- ]?(\\d{4})$",
            message = "{invalid.phonenumber}")
    protected String homePhone;
    @Temporal(javax.persistence.TemporalType.DATE)
    @Past
    protected Date birthday;
    ...
}

38.3.2 Specifying Error Messages for Constraints in address-book

Some of the constraints in the Contact entity specify an optional message:

@Pattern(regexp = "^\\(?(\\d{3})\\)?[- ]?(\\d{3})[- ]?(\\d{4})$",
        message = "{invalid.phonenumber}")
protected String homePhone;

The optional message element in the @Pattern constraint overrides the default validation message. The message can be specified directly:

@Pattern(regexp = "^\\(?(\\d{3})\\)?[- ]?(\\d{3})[- ]?(\\d{4})$",
        message = "Invalid phone number!")
protected String homePhone;

The constraints in Contact, however, are strings in the resource bundle ValidationMessages.properties, under tut-install/examples/persistence/address-book/src/java/. This allows the validation messages to be located in one single properties file and the messages to be easily localized. Overridden Bean Validation messages must be placed in a resource bundle properties file named ValidationMessages.properties in the default package, with localized resource bundles taking the form ValidationMessages_locale-prefix.properties. For example, ValidationMessages_es.properties is the resource bundle used in Spanish-speaking locales.

38.3.3 Validating Contact Input from a JavaServer Faces Application

The address-book application uses a JavaServer Faces web front end to allow users to enter contacts. While JavaServer Faces has a form input validation mechanism using tags in Facelets XHTML files, address-book doesn't use these validation tags. Bean Validation constraints in JavaServer Faces managed beans, in this case in the Contact entity, automatically trigger validation when the forms are submitted.

The following code snippet from the Create.xhtml Facelets file shows some of the input form for creating new Contact instances:

<h:form>
    <table columns="3" role="presentation">
        <tr>
            <td><h:outputLabel value="#{bundle.CreateContactLabel_firstName}" 
                               for="firstName" /></td>
            <td><h:inputText id="firstName" 
                             value="#{contactController.selected.firstName}" 
                             title="#{bundle.CreateContactTitle_firstName}"/>
            </td>
            <td><h:message for="firstName" /></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td><h:outputLabel value="#{bundle.CreateContactLabel_lastName}" 
                               for="lastName" /></td>
            <td><h:inputText id="lastName" 
                             value="#{contactController.selected.lastName}" 
                             title="#{bundle.CreateContactTitle_lastName}" />
            </td>
            <td><h:message for="lastName" /></td>
        </tr>
        ...
    </table>
</h:form>

The <h:inputText> tags firstName and lastName are bound to the attributes in the Contact entity instance selected in the ContactController stateless session bean. Each <h:inputText> tag has an associated <h:message> tag that will display validation error messages. The form doesn't require any JavaServer Faces validation tags, however.

38.3.4 Running the address-book Example

You can use either NetBeans IDE or Maven to build, package, deploy, and run the address-book application.

38.3.4.1 To Run the address-book Example Using NetBeans IDE

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

If the database server is not already running, start it by following the instructions in Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server.

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/persistence

Select the address-book folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the address-book project and select Run.

After the application has been deployed, a web browser window appears at the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/address-book/

Click Show All Contact Items, then Create New Contact. Enter values in the fields; then click Save.

If any of the values entered violate the constraints in Contact, an error message will appear in red beside the field with the incorrect values.

38.3.4.2 To Run the address-book Example Using Maven

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

If the database server is not already running, start it by following the instructions in Starting and Stopping the Java DB Server.

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/persistence/address-book/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This will compile and assemble the address-book application into a WAR. The WAR file is then deployed to GlassFish Server.

Open a web browser window and enter the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/address-book/

Click Show All Contact Items, then Create New Contact. Enter values in the fields; then click Save.

If any of the values entered violate the constraints in Contact, an error message will appear in red beside the field with the incorrect values.

44 Using a Second-Level Cache with Java Persistence API Applications

This chapter explains how to modify the second-level cache mode settings to improve the performance of applications that use the Java Persistence API.

The following topics are addressed here:

Overview of the Second-Level Cache

Specifying the Cache Mode Settings to Improve Performance

44.1 Overview of the Second-Level Cache

A second-level cache is a local store of entity data managed by the persistence provider to improve application performance. A second-level cache helps improve performance by avoiding expensive database calls, keeping the entity data local to the application. A second-level cache is typically transparent to the application, as it is managed by the persistence provider and underlies the persistence context of an application. That is, the application reads and commits data through the normal entity manager operations without knowing about the cache.

Note:

Persistence providers are not required to support a second-level cache. Portable applications should not rely on support by persistence providers for a second-level cache.

The second-level cache for a persistence unit may be configured to one of several second-level cache modes. The following cache mode settings are defined by the Java Persistence API.

Table 44-1 Cache Mode Settings for the Second-Level Cache

Cache Mode Setting | Description

ALL

|

All entity data is stored in the second-level cache for this persistence unit.

NONE

|

No data is cached in the persistence unit. The persistence provider must not cache any data.

ENABLE_SELECTIVE

|

Enable caching for entities that have been explicitly set with the @Cacheable annotation.

DISABLE_SELECTIVE

|

Enable caching for all entities except those that have been explicitly set with the @Cacheable(false) annotation.

UNSPECIFIED

|

The caching behavior for the persistence unit is undefined. The persistence provider's default caching behavior will be used.

One consequence of using a second-level cache in an application is that the underlying data may have changed in the database tables, while the value in the cache has not, a circumstance called a stale read. To avoid stale reads, use any of these strategies:

Change the second-level cache to one of the cache mode settings

Control which entities may be cached (see Controlling whether Entities May Be Cached)

Change the cache's retrieval or store modes (see Setting the Cache Retrieval and Store Modes)

Which of these strategies works best to avoid stale reads depends upon the application.

44.1.1 Controlling whether Entities May Be Cached

The javax.persistence.Cacheable annotation is used to specify that an entity class, and any subclasses, may be cached when using the ENABLE_SELECTIVE or DISABLE_SELECTIVE cache modes. Subclasses may override the @Cacheable setting by adding a @Cacheable annotation and changing the value.

To specify that an entity may be cached, add a @Cacheable annotation at the class level:

@Cacheable
@Entity
public class Person { ... }

By default, the @Cacheable annotation is true. The following example is equivalent:

@Cacheable(true)
@Entity
public class Person{ ... }

To specify that an entity must not be cached, add a @Cacheable annotation and set it to false:

@Cacheable(false)
@Entity
public class OrderStatus { ... }

When the ENABLE_SELECTIVE cache mode is set, the persistence provider will cache any entities that have the @Cacheable(true) annotation and any subclasses of that entity that have not been overridden. The persistence provider will not cache entities that have @Cacheable(false) or have no @Cacheable annotation. That is, the ENABLE_SELECTIVE mode will cache only entities that have been explicitly marked for the cache using the @Cacheable annotation.

When the DISABLE_SELECTIVE cache mode is set, the persistence provider will cache any entities that do not have the @Cacheable(false) annotation. Entities that do not have @Cacheable annotations, and entities with the @Cacheable(true) annotation, will be cached. That is, the DISABLE_SELECTIVE mode will cache all entities that have not been explicitly prevented from being cached.

If the cache mode is set to UNDEFINED, or is left unset, the behavior of entities annotated with @Cacheable is undefined. If the cache mode is set to ALL or NONE, the value of the @Cacheable annotation is ignored by the persistence provider.

44.2 Specifying the Cache Mode Settings to Improve Performance

To adjust the cache mode settings for a persistence unit, specify one of the cache modes as the value of the shared-cache-mode element in the persistence.xml deployment descriptor (shown in bold):

<persistence-unit name="examplePU" transaction-type="JTA">
    <provider>org.eclipse.persistence.jpa.PersistenceProvider</provider>
    <jta-data-source>java:comp/DefaultDataSource</jta-data-source>
    <shared-cache-mode>DISABLE_SELECTIVE</shared-cache-mode>
</persistence-unit>

Note:

Because support for a second-level cache is not required by the Java Persistence API specification, setting the second-level cache mode in persistence.xml will have no effect when you use a persistence provider that does not implement a second-level cache.

Alternatively, you can specify the shared cache mode by setting the javax.persistence.sharedCache.mode property to one of the shared cache mode settings:

EntityManagerFactory emf = 
    Persistence.createEntityManagerFactory(
        "myExamplePU", new Properties().add(
            "javax.persistence.sharedCache.mode", "ENABLE_SELECTIVE"));

44.2.1 Setting the Cache Retrieval and Store Modes

If you have enabled the second-level cache for a persistence unit by setting the shared cache mode, you can further modify the behavior of the second-level cache by setting the javax.persistence.cache.retrieveMode and javax.persistence.cache.storeMode properties. You can set these properties at the persistence context level by passing the property name and value to the EntityManager.setProperty method, or you can set them on a per-EntityManager operation (EntityManager.find or EntityManager.refresh) or on a per-query level.

44.2.1.1 Cache Retrieval Mode

The cache retrieval mode, set by the javax.persistence.retrieveMode property, controls how data is read from the cache for calls to the EntityManager.find method and from queries.

You can set the retrieveMode property to one of the constants defined by the javax.persistence.CacheRetrieveMode enumerated type, either USE (the default) or BYPASS.

When the property is set to USE, data is retrieved from the second-level cache, if available. If the data is not in the cache, the persistence provider will read it from the database.

When the property is set to BYPASS, the second-level cache is bypassed and a call to the database is made to retrieve the data.

44.2.1.2 Cache Store Mode

The cache store mode, set by the javax.persistence.storeMode property, controls how data is stored in the cache.

The storeMode property can be set to one of the constants defined by the javax.persistence.CacheStoreMode enumerated type: either USE (the default), BYPASS, or REFRESH.

When the property is set to USE, the cache data is created or updated when data is read from or committed to the database. If data is already in the cache, setting the store mode to USE will not force a refresh when data is read from the database.

When the property is set to BYPASS, data read from or committed to the database is not inserted or updated in the cache. That is, the cache is unchanged.

When the property is set to REFRESH, the cache data is created or updated when data is read from or committed to the database, and a refresh is forced on data in the cache upon database reads.

44.2.1.3 Setting the Cache Retrieval or Store Mode

To set the cache retrieval or store mode for the persistence context, call the EntityManager.setProperty method with the property name and value pair:

EntityManager em = ...;
em.setProperty("javax.persistence.cache.storeMode", "BYPASS");

To set the cache retrieval or store mode when calling the EntityManager.find or EntityManager.refresh methods, first create a Map<String, Object> instance and add a name/value pair as follows:

EntityManager em = ...;
Map<String, Object> props = new HashMap<String, Object>();
props.put("javax.persistence.cache.retrieveMode", "BYPASS");
String personPK = ...;
Person person = em.find(Person.class, personPK, props);

Note:

The cache retrieval mode is ignored when calling the EntityManager.refresh method, as calls to refresh always result in data being read from the database, not the cache.

To set the retrieval or store mode when using queries, call the Query.setHint or TypedQuery.setHint methods, depending on the type of query:

EntityManager em = ...;
CriteriaQuery<Person> cq = ...;
TypedQuery<Person> q = em.createQuery(cq);
q.setHint("javax.persistence.cache.storeMode", "REFRESH");
...

Setting the store or retrieve mode in a query or when calling the EntityManager.find or EntityManager.refresh method overrides the setting of the entity manager.

44.2.2 Controlling the Second-Level Cache Programmatically

The javax.persistence.Cache interface defines methods for interacting with the second-level cache programmatically. The Cache interface defines methods to do the following:

Check whether a particular entity has cached data

Remove a particular entity from the cache

Remove all instances (and instances of subclasses) of an entity class from the cache

Clear the cache of all entity data

Note:

If the second-level cache has been disabled, calls to the Cache interface's methods have no effect, except for contains, which will always return false.

44.2.2.1 Checking whether an Entity's Data Is Cached

Call the Cache.contains method to find out whether a given entity is currently in the second-level cache. The contains method returns true if the entity's data is cached, and false if the data is not in the cache:

EntityManager em = ...;
Cache cache = em.getEntityManagerFactory().getCache();
String personPK = ...;
if (cache.contains(Person.class, personPK)) {
  // the data is cached
} else {
  // the data is NOT cached
}

44.2.2.2 Removing an Entity from the Cache

Call one of the Cache.evict methods to remove a particular entity or all entities of a given type from the second-level cache. To remove a particular entity from the cache, call the evict method and pass in the entity class and the primary key of the entity:

EntityManager em = ...;
Cache cache = em.getEntityManagerFactory().getCache();
String personPK = ...;
cache.evict(Person.class, personPK);

To remove all instances of a particular entity class, including subclasses, call the evict method and specify the entity class:

EntityManager em = ...;
Cache cache = em.getEntityManagerFactory().getCache();
cache.evict(Person.class);

All instances of the Person entity class will be removed from the cache. If the Person entity has a subclass, Student, calls to the above method will remove all instances of Student from the cache as well.

44.2.2.3 Removing All Data from the Cache

Call the Cache.evictAll method to completely clear the second-level cache:

EntityManager em = ...;
Cache cache = em.getEntityManagerFactory().getCache();
cache.evictAll();

40 Using the Criteria API to Create Queries

The Criteria API is used to define queries for entities and their persistent state by creating query-defining objects. Criteria queries are written using Java programming language APIs, are typesafe, and are portable. Such queries work regardless of the underlying data store.

The following topics are addressed here:

Overview of the Criteria and Metamodel APIs

Using the Metamodel API to Model Entity Classes

Using the Criteria API and Metamodel API to Create Basic Typesafe Queries

40.1 Overview of the Criteria and Metamodel APIs

Similar to JPQL, the Criteria API is based on the abstract schema of persistent entities, their relationships, and embedded objects. The Criteria API operates on this abstract schema to allow developers to find, modify, and delete persistent entities by invoking Java Persistence API entity operations. The Metamodel API works in concert with the Criteria API to model persistent entity classes for Criteria queries.

The Criteria API and JPQL are closely related and are designed to allow similar operations in their queries. Developers familiar with JPQL syntax will find equivalent object-level operations in the Criteria API.

The following simple Criteria query returns all instances of the Pet entity in the data source:

EntityManager em = ...;
CriteriaBuilder cb = em.getCriteriaBuilder();
CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
cq.select(pet);
TypedQuery<Pet> q = em.createQuery(cq);
List<Pet> allPets = q.getResultList();

The equivalent JPQL query is

SELECT p
FROM Pet p

This query demonstrates the basic steps to create a Criteria query.

Use an EntityManager instance to create a CriteriaBuilder object.

Create a query object by creating an instance of the CriteriaQuery interface. This query object's attributes will be modified with the details of the query.

Set the query root by calling the from method on the CriteriaQuery object.

Specify what the type of the query result will be by calling the select method of the CriteriaQuery object.

Prepare the query for execution by creating a TypedQuery<T> instance, specifying the type of the query result.

Execute the query by calling the getResultList method on the TypedQuery<T> object. Because this query returns a collection of entities, the result is stored in a List.

The tasks associated with each step are discussed in detail in this chapter.

To create a CriteriaBuilder instance, call the getCriteriaBuilder method on the EntityManager instance:

CriteriaBuilder cb = em.getCriteriaBuilder();

Use the CriteriaBuilder instance to create a query object:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);

The query will return instances of the Pet entity. To create a typesafe query, specify the type of the query when you create the CriteriaQuery object.

Call the from method of the query object to set the FROM clause of the query and to specify the root of the query:

Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);

Call the select method of the query object, passing in the query root, to set the SELECT clause of the query:

cq.select(pet);

Now, use the query object to create a TypedQuery<T> object that can be executed against the data source. The modifications to the query object are captured to create a ready-to-execute query:

TypedQuery<Pet> q = em.createQuery(cq);

Execute this typed query object by calling its getResultList method, because this query will return multiple entity instances. The following statement stores the results in a List<Pet> collection-valued object:

List<Pet> allPets = q.getResultList();

40.2 Using the Metamodel API to Model Entity Classes

Use the Metamodel API to create a metamodel of the managed entities in a particular persistence unit. For each entity class in a particular package, a metamodel class is created with a trailing underscore and with attributes that correspond to the persistent fields or properties of the entity class.

The following entity class, com.example.Pet, has four persistent fields: id, name, color, and owners:

package com.example;
...
@Entity
public class Pet {
    @Id
    protected Long id;
    protected String name;
    protected String color;
    @ManyToOne
    protected Set<Person> owners;
    ...
}

The corresponding Metamodel class is as follows:

package com.example;
...
@Static Metamodel(Pet.class)
public class Pet_ {

    public static volatile SingularAttribute<Pet, Long> id;
    public static volatile SingularAttribute<Pet, String> name;
    public static volatile SingularAttribute<Pet, String> color;
    public static volatile SetAttribute<Pet, Person> owners;
}

Criteria queries use the metamodel class and its attributes to refer to the managed entity classes and their persistent state and relationships.

40.2.1 Using Metamodel Classes

Metamodel classes that correspond to entity classes are of the following type:

javax.persistence.metamodel.EntityType<T>

Annotation processors typically generate metamodel classes either at development time or at runtime. Developers of applications that use Criteria queries may do either of the following:

Generate static metamodel classes by using the persistence provider's annotation processor

Obtain the metamodel class by doing one of the following:

Call the getModel method on the query root object

Obtain an instance of the Metamodel interface and then pass the entity type to the instance's entity method

The following code snippet shows how to obtain the Pet entity's metamodel class by calling Root<T>.getModel:

EntityManager em = ...;
CriteriaBuilder cb = em.getCriteriaBuilder();
CriteriaQuery cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
EntityType<Pet> Pet_ = pet.getModel();

The following code snippet shows how to obtain the Pet entity's metamodel class by first obtaining a metamodel instance by using EntityManager.getMetamodel and then calling entity on the metamodel instance:

EntityManager em = ...;
Metamodel m = em.getMetamodel();
EntityType<Pet> Pet_ = m.entity(Pet.class);

Note:

The most common use case is to generate typesafe static metamodel classes at development time. Obtaining the metamodel classes dynamically, by calling Root<T>.getModel or EntityManager.getMetamodel and then the entity method, doesn't allow for type safety and doesn't allow the application to call persistent field or property names on the metamodel class.

40.3 Using the Criteria API and Metamodel API to Create Basic Typesafe Queries

The basic semantics of a Criteria query consists of a SELECT clause, a FROM clause, and an optional WHERE clause, similar to a JPQL query. Criteria queries set these clauses by using Java programming language objects, so the query can be created in a typesafe manner.

40.3.1 Creating a Criteria Query

The javax.persistence.criteria.CriteriaBuilder interface is used to construct

Criteria queries

Selections

Expressions

Predicates

Ordering

To obtain an instance of the CriteriaBuilder interface, call the getCriteriaBuilder method on either an EntityManager or an EntityManagerFactory instance.

The following code shows how to obtain a CriteriaBuilder instance by using the EntityManager.getCriteriaBuilder method:

EntityManager em = ...;
CriteriaBuilder cb = em.getCriteriaBuilder();

Criteria queries are constructed by obtaining an instance of the following interface:

javax.persistence.criteria.CriteriaQuery

CriteriaQuery objects define a particular query that will navigate over one or more entities. Obtain CriteriaQuery instances by calling one of the CriteriaBuilder.createQuery methods. To create typesafe queries, call the CriteriaBuilder.createQuery method as follows:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);

The CriteriaQuery object's type should be set to the expected result type of the query. In the preceding code, the object's type is set to CriteriaQuery<Pet> for a query that will find instances of the Pet entity.

The following code snippet creates a CriteriaQuery object for a query that returns a String:

CriteriaQuery<String> cq = cb.createQuery(String.class);

40.3.2 Query Roots

For a particular CriteriaQuery object, the root entity of the query, from which all navigation originates, is called the query root. It is similar to the FROM clause in a JPQL query.

Create the query root by calling the from method on the CriteriaQuery instance. The argument to the from method is either the entity class or an EntityType<T> instance for the entity.

The following code sets the query root to the Pet entity:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);

The following code sets the query root to the Pet class by using an EntityType<T> instance:

EntityManager em = ...;
Metamodel m = em.getMetamodel();
EntityType<Pet> Pet_ = m.entity(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet_);

Criteria queries may have more than one query root. This usually occurs when the query navigates from several entities.

The following code has two Root instances:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet1 = cq.from(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet2 = cq.from(Pet.class);

40.3.3 Querying Relationships Using Joins

For queries that navigate to related entity classes, the query must define a join to the related entity by calling one of the From.join methods on the query root object or another join object. The join methods are similar to the JOIN keyword in JPQL.

The target of the join uses the Metamodel class of type EntityType<T> to specify the persistent field or property of the joined entity.

The join methods return an object of type Join<X, Y>, where X is the source entity and Y is the target of the join. In the following code snippet, Pet is the source entity, Owner is the target, and Pet_ is a statically generated metamodel class:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);

Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
Join<Pet, Owner> owner = pet.join(Pet_.owners);

You can chain joins together to navigate to related entities of the target entity without having to create a Join<X, Y> instance for each join:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);

Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
Join<Owner, Address> address = pet.join(Pet_.owners).join(Owner_.addresses);

40.3.4 Path Navigation in Criteria Queries

Path objects, which are used in the SELECT and WHERE clauses of a Criteria query, can be query root entities, join entities, or other Path objects. Use the Path.get method to navigate to attributes of the entities of a query.

The argument to the get method is the corresponding attribute of the entity's Metamodel class. The attribute can be either a single-valued attribute, specified by @SingularAttribute in the Metamodel class, or a collection-valued attribute, specified by one of @CollectionAttribute, @SetAttribute, @ListAttribute, or @MapAttribute.

The following query returns the names of all the pets in the data store. The get method is called on the query root, pet, with the name attribute of the Pet entity's Metamodel class, Pet_, as the argument:

CriteriaQuery<String> cq = cb.createQuery(String.class);

Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
cq.select(pet.get(Pet_.name));

40.3.5 Restricting Criteria Query Results

Conditions that are set by calling the CriteriaQuery.where method can restrict the results of a query on the CriteriaQuery object. Calling the where method is analogous to setting the WHERE clause in a JPQL query.

The where method evaluates instances of the Expression interface to restrict the results according to the conditions of the expressions. To create Expression instances, use methods defined in the Expression and CriteriaBuilder interfaces.

40.3.5.1 The Expression Interface Methods

An Expression object is used in a query's SELECT, WHERE, or HAVING clause. Table 40-1 shows conditional methods you can use with Expression objects.

Table 40-1 Conditional Methods in the Expression Interface

Method | Description

isNull

|

Tests whether an expression is null

isNotNull

|

Tests whether an expression is not null

in

|

Tests whether an expression is within a list of values

The following query uses the Expression.isNull method to find all pets where the color attribute is null:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
cq.where(pet.get(Pet_.color).isNull());

The following query uses the Expression.in method to find all brown and black pets:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
cq.where(pet.get(Pet_.color).in("brown", "black"));

The in method can also check whether an attribute is a member of a collection.

40.3.5.2 Expression Methods in the CriteriaBuilder Interface

The CriteriaBuilder interface defines additional methods for creating expressions. These methods correspond to the arithmetic, string, date, time, and case operators and functions of JPQL. Table 40-2 shows conditional methods you can use with CriteriaBuilder objects.

Table 40-2 Conditional Methods in the CriteriaBuilder Interface

Conditional Method | Description

equal

|

Tests whether two expressions are equal

notEqual

|

Tests whether two expressions are not equal

gt

|

Tests whether the first numeric expression is greater than the second numeric expression

ge

|

Tests whether the first numeric expression is greater than or equal to the second numeric expression

lt

|

Tests whether the first numeric expression is less than the second numeric expression

le

|

Tests whether the first numeric expression is less than or equal to the second numeric expression

between

|

Tests whether the first expression is between the second and third expression in value

like

|

Tests whether the expression matches a given pattern

The following code uses the CriteriaBuilder.equal method:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
cq.where(cb.equal(pet.get(Pet_.name), "Fido"));

The following code uses the CriteriaBuilder.gt method:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
Date someDate = new Date(...);
cq.where(cb.gt(pet.get(Pet_.birthday), date));

The following code uses the CriteriaBuilder.between method:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
Date firstDate = new Date(...);
Date secondDate = new Date(...);
cq.where(cb.between(pet.get(Pet_.birthday), firstDate, secondDate));

The following code uses the CriteriaBuilder.like method:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
cq.where(cb.like(pet.get(Pet_.name), "*do"));

To specify multiple conditional predicates, use the compound predicate methods of the CriteriaBuilder interface, as shown in Table 40-3.

Table 40-3 Compound Predicate Methods in the CriteriaBuilder Interface

Method | Description

and

|

A logical conjunction of two Boolean expressions

or

|

A logical disjunction of two Boolean expressions

not

|

A logical negation of the given Boolean expression

The following code shows the use of compound predicates in queries:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
cq.where(cb.equal(pet.get(Pet_.name), "Fido")
        .and(cb.equal(pet.get(Pet_.color), "brown")));

40.3.6 Managing Criteria Query Results

For queries that return more than one result, it is often helpful to organize those results. The CriteriaQuery interface defines the following ordering and grouping methods:

The orderBy method orders query results according to attributes of an entity

The groupBy method groups the results of a query together according to attributes of an entity, and the having method restricts those groups according to a condition

40.3.6.1 Ordering Results

To order the results of a query, call the CriteriaQuery.orderBy method, passing in an Order object. To create an Order object, call either the CriteriaBuilder.asc or the CriteriaBuilder.desc method. The asc method is used to order the results by ascending value of the passed expression parameter. The desc method is used to order the results by descending value of the passed expression parameter. The following query shows the use of the desc method:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
cq.select(pet);
cq.orderBy(cb.desc(pet.get(Pet_.birthday)));

In this query, the results will be ordered by the pet's birthday from highest to lowest. That is, pets born in December will appear before pets born in May.

The following query shows the use of the asc method:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
Join<Owner, Address> address = pet.join(Pet_.owners).join(Owner_.address);
cq.select(pet);
cq.orderBy(cb.asc(address.get(Address_.postalCode)));

In this query, the results will be ordered by the pet owner's postal code from lowest to highest. That is, pets whose owner lives in the 10001 zip code will appear before pets whose owner lives in the 91000 zip code.

If more than one Order object is passed to orderBy, the precedence is determined by the order in which they appear in the argument list of orderBy. The first Order object has precedence.

The following code orders results by multiple criteria:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
Join<Pet, Owner> owner = pet.join(Pet_.owners);
cq.select(pet);
cq.orderBy(cb.asc(owner.get(Owner_.lastName)), owner.get(Owner_.firstName)));

The results of this query will be ordered alphabetically by the pet owner's last name, then first name.

40.3.6.2 Grouping Results

The CriteriaQuery.groupBy method partitions the query results into groups. To set these groups, pass an expression to groupBy:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
cq.groupBy(pet.get(Pet_.color));

This query returns all Pet entities and groups the results by the pet's color.

Use the CriteriaQuery.having method in conjunction with groupBy to filter over the groups. The having method, which takes a conditional expression as a parameter, restricts the query result according to the conditional expression:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
Root<Pet> pet = cq.from(Pet.class);
cq.groupBy(pet.get(Pet_.color));
cq.having(cb.in(pet.get(Pet_.color)).value("brown").value("blonde"));

In this example, the query groups the returned Pet entities by color, as in the preceding example. However, the only returned groups will be Pet entities where the color attribute is set to brown or blonde. That is, no gray-colored pets will be returned in this query.

40.3.7 Executing Queries

To prepare a query for execution, create a TypedQuery<T> object with the type of the query result, passing the CriteriaQuery object to EntityManager.createQuery.

To execute a query, call either getSingleResult or getResultList on the TypedQuery<T> object.

40.3.7.1 Single-Valued Query Results

Use the TypedQuery<T>.getSingleResult method to execute queries that return a single result:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
...
TypedQuery<Pet> q = em.createQuery(cq);
Pet result = q.getSingleResult();

40.3.7.2 Collection-Valued Query Results

Use the TypedQuery<T>.getResultList method to execute queries that return a collection of objects:

CriteriaQuery<Pet> cq = cb.createQuery(Pet.class);
...
TypedQuery<Pet> q = em.createQuery(cq);
List<Pet> results = q.getResultList();

37 Introduction to the Java Persistence API

The Java Persistence API provides Java developers with an object/relational mapping facility for managing relational data in Java applications. Java Persistence consists of four areas:

The Java Persistence API

The query language

The Java Persistence Criteria API

Object/relational mapping metadata

The following topics are addressed here:

Entities

Entity Inheritance

Managing Entities

Querying Entities

Database Schema Creation

Further Information about Persistence

37.1 Entities

An entity is a lightweight persistence domain object. Typically, an entity represents a table in a relational database, and each entity instance corresponds to a row in that table. The primary programming artifact of an entity is the entity class, although entities can use helper classes.

The persistent state of an entity is represented through either persistent fields or persistent properties. These fields or properties use object/relational mapping annotations to map the entities and entity relationships to the relational data in the underlying data store.

37.1.1 Requirements for Entity Classes

An entity class must follow these requirements.

The class must be annotated with the javax.persistence.Entity annotation.

The class must have a public or protected, no-argument constructor. The class may have other constructors.

The class must not be declared final. No methods or persistent instance variables must be declared final.

If an entity instance is passed by value as a detached object, such as through a session bean's remote business interface, the class must implement the Serializable interface.

Entities may extend both entity and non-entity classes, and non-entity classes may extend entity classes.

Persistent instance variables must be declared private, protected, or package-private and can be accessed directly only by the entity class's methods. Clients must access the entity's state through accessor or business methods.

37.1.2 Persistent Fields and Properties in Entity Classes

The persistent state of an entity can be accessed through either the entity's instance variables or properties. The fields or properties must be of the following Java language types:

Java primitive types

java.lang.String

Other serializable types, including:

Wrappers of Java primitive types

java.math.BigInteger

java.math.BigDecimal

java.util.Date

java.util.Calendar

java.sql.Date

java.sql.Time

java.sql.TimeStamp

User-defined serializable types

byte[]

Byte[]

char[]

Character[]

Enumerated types

Other entities and/or collections of entities

Embeddable classes

Entities may use persistent fields, persistent properties, or a combination of both. If the mapping annotations are applied to the entity's instance variables, the entity uses persistent fields. If the mapping annotations are applied to the entity's getter methods for JavaBeans-style properties, the entity uses persistent properties.

37.1.2.1 Persistent Fields

If the entity class uses persistent fields, the Persistence runtime accesses entity-class instance variables directly. All fields not annotated javax.persistence.Transient or not marked as Java transient will be persisted to the data store. The object/relational mapping annotations must be applied to the instance variables.

37.1.2.2 Persistent Properties

If the entity uses persistent properties, the entity must follow the method conventions of JavaBeans components. JavaBeans-style properties use getter and setter methods that are typically named after the entity class's instance variable names. For every persistent property property of type Type of the entity, there is a getter method getProperty and setter method setProperty. If the property is a Boolean, you may use isProperty instead of getProperty. For example, if a Customer entity uses persistent properties and has a private instance variable called firstName, the class defines a getFirstName and setFirstName method for retrieving and setting the state of the firstName instance variable.

The method signatures for single-valued persistent properties are as follows:

Type getProperty()
void setProperty(Type type)

The object/relational mapping annotations for persistent properties must be applied to the getter methods. Mapping annotations cannot be applied to fields or properties annotated @Transient or marked transient.

37.1.2.3 Using Collections in Entity Fields and Properties

Collection-valued persistent fields and properties must use the supported Java collection interfaces regardless of whether the entity uses persistent fields or properties. The following collection interfaces may be used:

java.util.Collection

java.util.Set

java.util.List

java.util.Map

If the entity class uses persistent fields, the type in the preceding method signatures must be one of these collection types. Generic variants of these collection types may also be used. For example, if it has a persistent property that contains a set of phone numbers, the Customer entity would have the following methods:

Set<PhoneNumber> getPhoneNumbers() { ... }
void setPhoneNumbers(Set<PhoneNumber>) { ... }

If a field or property of an entity consists of a collection of basic types or embeddable classes, use the javax.persistence.ElementCollection annotation on the field or property.

The two attributes of @ElementCollection are targetClass and fetch. The targetClass attribute specifies the class name of the basic or embeddable class and is optional if the field or property is defined using Java programming language generics. The optional fetch attribute is used to specify whether the collection should be retrieved lazily or eagerly, using the javax.persistence.FetchType constants of either LAZY or EAGER, respectively. By default, the collection will be fetched lazily.

The following entity, Person, has a persistent field, nicknames, which is a collection of String classes that will be fetched eagerly. The targetClass element is not required, because it uses generics to define the field:

@Entity
public class Person {
    ...
    @ElementCollection(fetch=EAGER)
    protected Set<String> nickname = new HashSet();
    ...
}

Collections of entity elements and relationships may be represented by java.util.Map collections. A Map consists of a key and a value.

When using Map elements or relationships, the following rules apply.

The Map key or value may be a basic Java programming language type, an embeddable class, or an entity.

When the Map value is an embeddable class or basic type, use the @ElementCollection annotation.

When the Map value is an entity, use the @OneToMany or @ManyToMany annotation.

Use the Map type on only one side of a bidirectional relationship.

If the key type of a Map is a Java programming language basic type, use the annotation javax.persistence.MapKeyColumn to set the column mapping for the key. By default, the name attribute of @MapKeyColumn is of the form RELATIONSHIP-FIELD/PROPERTY-NAME_KEY. For example, if the referencing relationship field name is image, the default name attribute is IMAGE_KEY.

If the key type of a Map is an entity, use the javax.persistence.MapKeyJoinColumn annotation. If the multiple columns are needed to set the mapping, use the annotation javax.persistence.MapKeyJoinColumns to include multiple @MapKeyJoinColumn annotations. If no @MapKeyJoinColumn is present, the mapping column name is by default set to RELATIONSHIP-FIELD/PROPERTY-NAME_KEY. For example, if the relationship field name is employee, the default name attribute is EMPLOYEE_KEY.

If Java programming language generic types are not used in the relationship field or property, the key class must be explicitly set using the javax.persistence.MapKeyClass annotation.

If the Map key is the primary key or a persistent field or property of the entity that is the Map value, use the javax.persistence.MapKey annotation. The @MapKeyClass and @MapKey annotations cannot be used on the same field or property.

If the Map value is a Java programming language basic type or an embeddable class, it will be mapped as a collection table in the underlying database. If generic types are not used, the @ElementCollection annotation's targetClass attribute must be set to the type of the Map value.

If the Map value is an entity and part of a many-to-many or one-to-many unidirectional relationship, it will be mapped as a join table in the underlying database. A unidirectional one-to-many relationship that uses a Map may also be mapped using the @JoinColumn annotation.

If the entity is part of a one-to-many/many-to-one bidirectional relationship, it will be mapped in the table of the entity that represents the value of the Map. If generic types are not used, the targetEntity attribute of the @OneToMany and @ManyToMany annotations must be set to the type of the Map value.

37.1.2.4 Validating Persistent Fields and Properties

The Java API for JavaBeans Validation (Bean Validation) provides a mechanism for validating application data. Bean Validation is integrated into the Java EE containers, allowing the same validation logic to be used in any of the tiers of an enterprise application.

Bean Validation constraints may be applied to persistent entity classes, embeddable classes, and mapped superclasses. By default, the Persistence provider will automatically perform validation on entities with persistent fields or properties annotated with Bean Validation constraints immediately after the PrePersist, PreUpdate, and PreRemove lifecycle events.

Bean Validation constraints are annotations applied to the fields or properties of Java programming language classes. Bean Validation provides a set of constraints as well as an API for defining custom constraints. Custom constraints can be specific combinations of the default constraints, or new constraints that don't use the default constraints. Each constraint is associated with at least one validator class that validates the value of the constrained field or property. Custom constraint developers must also provide a validator class for the constraint.

Bean Validation constraints are applied to the persistent fields or properties of persistent classes. When adding Bean Validation constraints, use the same access strategy as the persistent class. That is, if the persistent class uses field access, apply the Bean Validation constraint annotations on the class's fields. If the class uses property access, apply the constraints on the getter methods.

Table 21-1 lists Bean Validation's built-in constraints, defined in the javax.validation.constraints package.

All the built-in constraints listed in Table 21-1 have a corresponding annotation, ConstraintName.List, for grouping multiple constraints of the same type on the same field or property. For example, the following persistent field has two @Pattern constraints:

@Pattern.List({
    @Pattern(regexp="..."),
    @Pattern(regexp="...")
})

The following entity class, Contact, has Bean Validation constraints applied to its persistent fields:

@Entity
public class Contact implements Serializable {
    @Id
    @GeneratedValue(strategy = GenerationType.AUTO)
    private Long id;
    @NotNull
    protected String firstName;
    @NotNull
    protected String lastName;
    @Pattern(regexp = "[a-z0-9!#$%&'*+/=?^_`{|}~-]+(?:\\."
            + "[a-z0-9!#$%&'*+/=?^_`{|}~-]+)*@"
            + "(?:[a-z0-9](?:[a-z0-9-]*[a-z0-9])?\\.)+[a-z0-9]"
            + "(?:[a-z0-9-]*[a-z0-9])?",
            message = "{invalid.email}")
    protected String email;
    @Pattern(regexp = "^\\(?(\\d{3})\\)?[- ]?(\\d{3})[- ]?(\\d{4})$",
            message = "{invalid.phonenumber}")
    protected String mobilePhone;
    @Pattern(regexp = "^\\(?(\\d{3})\\)?[- ]?(\\d{3})[- ]?(\\d{4})$",
            message = "{invalid.phonenumber}")
    protected String homePhone;
    @Temporal(javax.persistence.TemporalType.DATE)
    @Past
    protected Date birthday;
    ...
}

The @NotNull annotation on the firstName and lastName fields specifies that those fields are now required. If a new Contact instance is created where firstName or lastName have not been initialized, Bean Validation will throw a validation error. Similarly, if a previously created instance of Contact has been modified so that firstName or lastName are null, a validation error will be thrown.

The email field has a @Pattern constraint applied to it, with a complicated regular expression that matches most valid email addresses. If the value of email doesn't match this regular expression, a validation error will be thrown.

The homePhone and mobilePhone fields have the same @Pattern constraints. The regular expression matches 10 digit telephone numbers in the United States and Canada of the form (xxx) xxx-xxxx.

The birthday field is annotated with the @Past constraint, which ensures that the value of birthday must be in the past.

37.1.3 Primary Keys in Entities

Each entity has a unique object identifier. A customer entity, for example, might be identified by a customer number. The unique identifier, or primary key, enables clients to locate a particular entity instance. Every entity must have a primary key. An entity may have either a simple or a composite primary key.

Simple primary keys use the javax.persistence.Id annotation to denote the primary key property or field.

Composite primary keys are used when a primary key consists of more than one attribute, which corresponds to a set of single persistent properties or fields. Composite primary keys must be defined in a primary key class. Composite primary keys are denoted using the javax.persistence.EmbeddedId and javax.persistence.IdClass annotations.

The primary key, or the property or field of a composite primary key, must be one of the following Java language types:

Java primitive types

Java primitive wrapper types

java.lang.String

java.util.Date (the temporal type should be DATE)

java.sql.Date

java.math.BigDecimal

java.math.BigInteger

Floating-point types should never be used in primary keys. If you use a generated primary key, only integral types will be portable.

A primary key class must meet these requirements.

The access control modifier of the class must be public.

The properties of the primary key class must be public or protected if property-based access is used.

The class must have a public default constructor.

The class must implement the hashCode() and equals(Object other) methods.

The class must be serializable.

A composite primary key must be represented and mapped to multiple fields or properties of the entity class or must be represented and mapped as an embeddable class.

If the class is mapped to multiple fields or properties of the entity class, the names and types of the primary key fields or properties in the primary key class must match those of the entity class.

The following primary key class is a composite key, and the customerOrder and itemId fields together uniquely identify an entity:

public final class LineItemKey implements Serializable {
    private Integer customerOrder;
    private int itemId;

    public LineItemKey() {}

    public LineItemKey(Integer order, int itemId) {
        this.setCustomerOrder(order);
        this.setItemId(itemId);
    }

    @Override
    public int hashCode() {
        return ((this.getCustomerOrder() == null
                ? 0 : this.getCustomerOrder().hashCode())
                ^ ((int) this.getItemId()));
    }

    @Override
    public boolean equals(Object otherOb) {
        if (this == otherOb) {
            return true;
        }
        if (!(otherOb instanceof LineItemKey)) {
            return false;
        }
        LineItemKey other = (LineItemKey) otherOb;
        return ((this.getCustomerOrder() == null
                ? other.getCustomerOrder() == null : this.getCustomerOrder()
                .equals(other.getCustomerOrder()))
                && (this.getItemId() == other.getItemId()));
    }

    @Override
    public String toString() {
        return "" + getCustomerOrder() + "-" + getItemId();
    }
    /* Getters and setters */
}

37.1.4 Multiplicity in Entity Relationships

Multiplicities are of the following types.

One-to-one: Each entity instance is related to a single instance of another entity. For example, to model a physical warehouse in which each storage bin contains a single widget, StorageBin and Widget would have a one-to-one relationship. One-to-one relationships use the javax.persistence.OneToOne annotation on the corresponding persistent property or field.

One-to-many: An entity instance can be related to multiple instances of the other entities. A sales order, for example, can have multiple line items. In the order application, CustomerOrder would have a one-to-many relationship with LineItem. One-to-many relationships use the javax.persistence.OneToMany annotation on the corresponding persistent property or field.

Many-to-one: Multiple instances of an entity can be related to a single instance of the other entity. This multiplicity is the opposite of a one-to-many relationship. In the example just mentioned, the relationship to CustomerOrder from the perspective of LineItem is many-to-one. Many-to-one relationships use the javax.persistence.ManyToOne annotation on the corresponding persistent property or field.

Many-to-many: The entity instances can be related to multiple instances of each other. For example, each college course has many students, and every student may take several courses. Therefore, in an enrollment application, Course and Student would have a many-to-many relationship. Many-to-many relationships use the javax.persistence.ManyToMany annotation on the corresponding persistent property or field.

37.1.5 Direction in Entity Relationships

The direction of a relationship can be either bidirectional or unidirectional. A bidirectional relationship has both an owning side and an inverse side. A unidirectional relationship has only an owning side. The owning side of a relationship determines how the Persistence runtime makes updates to the relationship in the database.

37.1.5.1 Bidirectional Relationships

In a bidirectional relationship, each entity has a relationship field or property that refers to the other entity. Through the relationship field or property, an entity class's code can access its related object. If an entity has a related field, the entity is said to "know" about its related object. For example, if CustomerOrder knows what LineItem instances it has and if LineItem knows what CustomerOrder it belongs to, they have a bidirectional relationship.

Bidirectional relationships must follow these rules.

The inverse side of a bidirectional relationship must refer to its owning side by using the mappedBy element of the @OneToOne, @OneToMany, or @ManyToMany annotation. The mappedBy element designates the property or field in the entity that is the owner of the relationship.

The many side of many-to-one bidirectional relationships must not define the mappedBy element. The many side is always the owning side of the relationship.

For one-to-one bidirectional relationships, the owning side corresponds to the side that contains the corresponding foreign key.

For many-to-many bidirectional relationships, either side may be the owning side.

37.1.5.2 Unidirectional Relationships

In a unidirectional relationship, only one entity has a relationship field or property that refers to the other. For example, LineItem would have a relationship field that identifies Product, but Product would not have a relationship field or property for LineItem. In other words, LineItem knows about Product, but Product doesn't know which LineItem instances refer to it.

37.1.5.3 Queries and Relationship Direction

Java Persistence query language and Criteria API queries often navigate across relationships. The direction of a relationship determines whether a query can navigate from one entity to another. For example, a query can navigate from LineItem to Product but cannot navigate in the opposite direction. For CustomerOrder and LineItem, a query could navigate in both directions because these two entities have a bidirectional relationship.

37.1.5.4 Cascade Operations and Relationships

Entities that use relationships often have dependencies on the existence of the other entity in the relationship. For example, a line item is part of an order; if the order is deleted, the line item also should be deleted. This is called a cascade delete relationship.

The javax.persistence.CascadeType enumerated type defines the cascade operations that are applied in the cascade element of the relationship annotations. Table 37-1 lists the cascade operations for entities.

Table 37-1 Cascade Operations for Entities

Cascade Operation | Description

ALL

|

All cascade operations will be applied to the parent entity's related entity. All is equivalent to specifying cascade={DETACH, MERGE, PERSIST, REFRESH, REMOVE}

DETACH

|

If the parent entity is detached from the persistence context, the related entity will also be detached.

MERGE

|

If the parent entity is merged into the persistence context, the related entity will also be merged.

PERSIST

|

If the parent entity is persisted into the persistence context, the related entity will also be persisted.

REFRESH

|

If the parent entity is refreshed in the current persistence context, the related entity will also be refreshed.

REMOVE

|

If the parent entity is removed from the current persistence context, the related entity will also be removed.

Cascade delete relationships are specified using the cascade=REMOVE element specification for @OneToOne and @OneToMany relationships. For example:

@OneToMany(cascade=REMOVE, mappedBy="customer")public SetCustomerOrder getOrders() { return orders; }

37.1.5.5 Orphan Removal in Relationships

When a target entity in a one-to-one or one-to-many relationship is removed from the relationship, it is often desirable to cascade the remove operation to the target entity. Such target entities are considered "orphans," and the orphanRemoval attribute can be used to specify that orphaned entities should be removed. For example, if an order has many line items and one of them is removed from the order, the removed line item is considered an orphan. If orphanRemoval is set to true, the line item entity will be deleted when the line item is removed from the order.

The orphanRemoval attribute in @OneToMany and @oneToOne takes a Boolean value and is by default false.

The following example will cascade the remove operation to the orphaned order entity when the customer entity is deleted:

@OneToMany(mappedBy="customer", orphanRemoval="true")
public List<CustomerOrder> getOrders() { ... }

37.1.6 Embeddable Classes in Entities

Embeddable classes are used to represent the state of an entity but don't have a persistent identity of their own, unlike entity classes. Instances of an embeddable class share the identity of the entity that owns it. Embeddable classes exist only as the state of another entity. An entity may have single-valued or collection-valued embeddable class attributes.

Embeddable classes have the same rules as entity classes but are annotated with the javax.persistence.Embeddable annotation instead of @Entity.

The following embeddable class, ZipCode, has the fields zip and plusFour:

@Embeddable
public class ZipCode {
    String zip;
    String plusFour;
    ...
}

This embeddable class is used by the Address entity:

@Entity
public class Address {
    @Id
    protected long id
    String street1;
    String street2;
    String city;
    String province;
    @Embedded
    ZipCode zipCode;
    String country;
    ...
}

Entities that own embeddable classes as part of their persistent state may annotate the field or property with the javax.persistence.Embedded annotation but are not required to do so.

Embeddable classes may themselves use other embeddable classes to represent their state. They may also contain collections of basic Java programming language types or other embeddable classes. Embeddable classes may also contain relationships to other entities or collections of entities. If the embeddable class has such a relationship, the relationship is from the target entity or collection of entities to the entity that owns the embeddable class.

37.2 Entity Inheritance

Entities support class inheritance, polymorphic associations, and polymorphic queries. Entity classes can extend non-entity classes, and non-entity classes can extend entity classes. Entity classes can be both abstract and concrete.

The roster example application demonstrates entity inheritance, as described in Entity Inheritance in the roster Application.

37.2.1 Abstract Entities

An abstract class may be declared an entity by decorating the class with @Entity. Abstract entities are like concrete entities but cannot be instantiated.

Abstract entities can be queried just like concrete entities. If an abstract entity is the target of a query, the query operates on all the concrete subclasses of the abstract entity:

@Entity
public abstract class Employee {
    @Id
    protected Integer employeeId;
    ...
}
@Entity
public class FullTimeEmployee extends Employee {
    protected Integer salary;
    ...
}
@Entity
public class PartTimeEmployee extends Employee {
    protected Float hourlyWage;
}

37.2.2 Mapped Superclasses

Entities may inherit from superclasses that contain persistent state and mapping information but are not entities. That is, the superclass is not decorated with the @Entity annotation and is not mapped as an entity by the Java Persistence provider. These superclasses are most often used when you have state and mapping information common to multiple entity classes.

Mapped superclasses are specified by decorating the class with the annotation javax.persistence.MappedSuperclass:

@MappedSuperclass
public class Employee {
    @Id
    protected Integer employeeId;
    ...
}
@Entity
public class FullTimeEmployee extends Employee {
    protected Integer salary;
    ...
}
@Entity
public class PartTimeEmployee extends Employee {
    protected Float hourlyWage;
    ...
}

Mapped superclasses cannot be queried and cannot be used in EntityManager or Query operations. You must use entity subclasses of the mapped superclass in EntityManager or Query operations. Mapped superclasses can't be targets of entity relationships. Mapped superclasses can be abstract or concrete.

Mapped superclasses do not have any corresponding tables in the underlying datastore. Entities that inherit from the mapped superclass define the table mappings. For instance, in the preceding code sample, the underlying tables would be FULLTIMEEMPLOYEE and PARTTIMEEMPLOYEE, but there is no EMPLOYEE table.

37.2.3 Non-Entity Superclasses

Entities may have non-entity superclasses, and these superclasses can be either abstract or concrete. The state of non-entity superclasses is nonpersistent, and any state inherited from the non-entity superclass by an entity class is nonpersistent. Non-entity superclasses may not be used in EntityManager or Query operations. Any mapping or relationship annotations in non-entity superclasses are ignored.

37.2.4 Entity Inheritance Mapping Strategies

You can configure how the Java Persistence provider maps inherited entities to the underlying datastore by decorating the root class of the hierarchy with the annotation javax.persistence.Inheritance. The following mapping strategies are used to map the entity data to the underlying database:

A single table per class hierarchy

A table per concrete entity class

A "join" strategy, whereby fields or properties that are specific to a subclass are mapped to a different table than the fields or properties that are common to the parent class

The strategy is configured by setting the strategy element of @Inheritance to one of the options defined in the javax.persistence.InheritanceType enumerated type:

public enum InheritanceType {
    SINGLE_TABLE,
    JOINED,
    TABLE_PER_CLASS
};

The default strategy, InheritanceType.SINGLE_TABLE, is used if the @Inheritance annotation is not specified on the root class of the entity hierarchy.

37.2.4.1 The Single Table per Class Hierarchy Strategy

With this strategy, which corresponds to the default InheritanceType.SINGLE_TABLE, all classes in the hierarchy are mapped to a single table in the database. This table has a discriminator column containing a value that identifies the subclass to which the instance represented by the row belongs.

The discriminator column, whose elements are shown in Table 37-2, can be specified by using the javax.persistence.DiscriminatorColumn annotation on the root of the entity class hierarchy.

Table 37-2 @DiscriminatorColumn Elements

Type | Name | Description

String

|

name

|

The name of the column to be used as the discriminator column. The default is DTYPE. This element is optional.

DiscriminatorType

|

discriminatorType

|

The type of the column to be used as a discriminator column. The default is DiscriminatorType.STRING. This element is optional.

String

|

columnDefinition

|

The SQL fragment to use when creating the discriminator column. The default is generated by the Persistence provider and is implementation-specific. This element is optional.

String

|

length

|

The column length for String-based discriminator types. This element is ignored for non-String discriminator types. The default is 31. This element is optional.

The javax.persistence.DiscriminatorType enumerated type is used to set the type of the discriminator column in the database by setting the discriminatorType element of @DiscriminatorColumn to one of the defined types. DiscriminatorType is defined as follows:

public enum DiscriminatorType {
    STRING,
    CHAR,
    INTEGER
}

If @DiscriminatorColumn is not specified on the root of the entity hierarchy and a discriminator column is required, the Persistence provider assumes a default column name of DTYPE and column type of DiscriminatorType.STRING.

The javax.persistence.DiscriminatorValue annotation may be used to set the value entered into the discriminator column for each entity in a class hierarchy. You may decorate only concrete entity classes with @DiscriminatorValue.

If @DiscriminatorValue is not specified on an entity in a class hierarchy that uses a discriminator column, the Persistence provider will provide a default, implementation-specific value. If the discriminatorType element of @DiscriminatorColumn is DiscriminatorType.STRING, the default value is the name of the entity.

This strategy provides good support for polymorphic relationships between entities and queries that cover the entire entity class hierarchy. However, this strategy requires the columns that contain the state of subclasses to be nullable.

37.2.4.2 The Table per Concrete Class Strategy

In this strategy, which corresponds to InheritanceType.TABLE_PER_CLASS, each concrete class is mapped to a separate table in the database. All fields or properties in the class, including inherited fields or properties, are mapped to columns in the class's table in the database.

This strategy provides poor support for polymorphic relationships and usually requires either SQL UNION queries or separate SQL queries for each subclass for queries that cover the entire entity class hierarchy.

Support for this strategy is optional and may not be supported by all Java Persistence API providers. The default Java Persistence API provider in GlassFish Server does not support this strategy.

37.2.4.3 The Joined Subclass Strategy

In this strategy, which corresponds to InheritanceType.JOINED, the root of the class hierarchy is represented by a single table, and each subclass has a separate table that contains only those fields specific to that subclass. That is, the subclass table does not contain columns for inherited fields or properties. The subclass table also has a column or columns that represent its primary key, which is a foreign key to the primary key of the superclass table.

This strategy provides good support for polymorphic relationships but requires one or more join operations to be performed when instantiating entity subclasses. This may result in poor performance for extensive class hierarchies. Similarly, queries that cover the entire class hierarchy require join operations between the subclass tables, resulting in decreased performance.

Some Java Persistence API providers, including the default provider in GlassFish Server, require a discriminator column that corresponds to the root entity when using the joined subclass strategy. If you are not using automatic table creation in your application, make sure that the database table is set up correctly for the discriminator column defaults, or use the @DiscriminatorColumn annotation to match your database schema. For information on discriminator columns, see The Single Table per Class Hierarchy Strategy.

37.3 Managing Entities

Entities are managed by the entity manager, which is represented by javax.persistence.EntityManager instances. Each EntityManager instance is associated with a persistence context: a set of managed entity instances that exist in a particular data store. A persistence context defines the scope under which particular entity instances are created, persisted, and removed. The EntityManager interface defines the methods that are used to interact with the persistence context.

37.3.1 The EntityManager Interface

The EntityManager API creates and removes persistent entity instances, finds entities by the entity's primary key, and allows queries to be run on entities.

37.3.1.1 Container-Managed Entity Managers

With a container-managed entity manager, an EntityManager instance's persistence context is automatically propagated by the container to all application components that use the EntityManager instance within a single Java Transaction API (JTA) transaction.

JTA transactions usually involve calls across application components. To complete a JTA transaction, these components usually need access to a single persistence context. This occurs when an EntityManager is injected into the application components by means of the javax.persistence.PersistenceContext annotation. The persistence context is automatically propagated with the current JTA transaction, and EntityManager references that are mapped to the same persistence unit provide access to the persistence context within that transaction. By automatically propagating the persistence context, application components don't need to pass references to EntityManager instances to each other in order to make changes within a single transaction. The Java EE container manages the lifecycle of container-managed entity managers.

To obtain an EntityManager instance, inject the entity manager into the application component:

@PersistenceContext
EntityManager em;

37.3.1.2 Application-Managed Entity Managers

With an application-managed entity manager, on the other hand, the persistence context is not propagated to application components, and the lifecycle of EntityManager instances is managed by the application.

Application-managed entity managers are used when applications need to access a persistence context that is not propagated with the JTA transaction across EntityManager instances in a particular persistence unit. In this case, each EntityManager creates a new, isolated persistence context. The EntityManager and its associated persistence context are created and destroyed explicitly by the application. They are also used when directly injecting EntityManager instances can't be done because EntityManager instances are not thread-safe. EntityManagerFactory instances are thread-safe.

Applications create EntityManager instances in this case by using the createEntityManager method of javax.persistence.EntityManagerFactory.

To obtain an EntityManager instance, you first must obtain an EntityManagerFactory instance by injecting it into the application component by means of the javax.persistence.PersistenceUnit annotation:

@PersistenceUnit
EntityManagerFactory emf;

Then obtain an EntityManager from the EntityManagerFactory instance:

EntityManager em = emf.createEntityManager();

Application-managed entity managers don't automatically propagate the JTA transaction context. Such applications need to manually gain access to the JTA transaction manager and add transaction demarcation information when performing entity operations. The javax.transaction.UserTransaction interface defines methods to begin, commit, and roll back transactions. Inject an instance of UserTransaction by creating an instance variable annotated with @Resource:

@Resource
UserTransaction utx;

To begin a transaction, call the UserTransaction.begin method. When all the entity operations are complete, call the UserTransaction.commit method to commit the transaction. The UserTransaction.rollback method is used to roll back the current transaction.

The following example shows how to manage transactions in an application that uses an application-managed entity manager:

@PersistenceUnit
EntityManagerFactory emf;
EntityManager em;
@Resource
UserTransaction utx;
...
em = emf.createEntityManager();
try {
    utx.begin();
    em.persist(SomeEntity);
    em.merge(AnotherEntity);
    em.remove(ThirdEntity);
    utx.commit();
} catch (Exception e) {
    utx.rollback();
}

37.3.1.3 Finding Entities Using the EntityManager

The EntityManager.find method is used to look up entities in the data store by the entity's primary key:

@PersistenceContext
EntityManager em;
public void enterOrder(int custID, CustomerOrder newOrder) {
    Customer cust = em.find(Customer.class, custID);
    cust.getOrders().add(newOrder);
    newOrder.setCustomer(cust);
}

37.3.1.4 Managing an Entity Instance's Lifecycle

You manage entity instances by invoking operations on the entity by means of an EntityManager instance. Entity instances are in one of four states: new, managed, detached, or removed.

New entity instances have no persistent identity and are not yet associated with a persistence context.

Managed entity instances have a persistent identity and are associated with a persistence context.

Detached entity instances have a persistent identity and are not currently associated with a persistence context.

Removed entity instances have a persistent identity, are associated with a persistent context, and are scheduled for removal from the data store.

37.3.1.5 Persisting Entity Instances

New entity instances become managed and persistent either by invoking the persist method or by a cascading persist operation invoked from related entities that have the cascade=PERSIST or cascade=ALL elements set in the relationship annotation. This means that the entity's data is stored to the database when the transaction associated with the persist operation is completed. If the entity is already managed, the persist operation is ignored, although the persist operation will cascade to related entities that have the cascade element set to PERSIST or ALL in the relationship annotation. If persist is called on a removed entity instance, the entity becomes managed. If the entity is detached, either persist will throw an IllegalArgumentException, or the transaction commit will fail. The following method performs a persist operation:

@PersistenceContext
EntityManager em;
...
public LineItem createLineItem(CustomerOrder order, Product product,
        int quantity) {
    LineItem li = new LineItem(order, product, quantity);
    order.getLineItems().add(li);
    em.persist(li);
    return li;
}

The persist operation is propagated to all entities related to the calling entity that have the cascade element set to ALL or PERSIST in the relationship annotation:

@OneToMany(cascade=ALL, mappedBy="order")
public Collection<LineItem> getLineItems() {
    return lineItems;
}

37.3.1.6 Removing Entity Instances

Managed entity instances are removed by invoking the remove method or by a cascading remove operation invoked from related entities that have the cascade=REMOVE or cascade=ALL elements set in the relationship annotation. If the remove method is invoked on a new entity, the remove operation is ignored, although remove will cascade to related entities that have the cascade element set to REMOVE or ALL in the relationship annotation. If remove is invoked on a detached entity, either remove will throw an IllegalArgumentException, or the transaction commit will fail. If invoked on an already removed entity, remove will be ignored. The entity's data will be removed from the data store when the transaction is completed or as a result of the flush operation.

In the following example, all LineItem entities associated with the order are also removed, as CustomerOrder.getLineItems has cascade=ALL set in the relationship annotation:

public void removeOrder(Integer orderId) {
    try {
        CustomerOrder order = em.find(CustomerOrder.class, orderId);
        em.remove(order);
    }...

37.3.1.7 Synchronizing Entity Data to the Database

The state of persistent entities is synchronized to the database when the transaction with which the entity is associated commits. If a managed entity is in a bidirectional relationship with another managed entity, the data will be persisted, based on the owning side of the relationship.

To force synchronization of the managed entity to the data store, invoke the flush method of the EntityManager instance. If the entity is related to another entity and the relationship annotation has the cascade element set to PERSIST or ALL, the related entity's data will be synchronized with the data store when flush is called.

If the entity is removed, calling flush will remove the entity data from the data store.

37.3.2 Persistence Units

A persistence unit defines a set of all entity classes that are managed by EntityManager instances in an application. This set of entity classes represents the data contained within a single data store.

Persistence units are defined by the persistence.xml configuration file. The following is an example persistence.xml file:

<persistence>
    <persistence-unit name="OrderManagement">
        <description>This unit manages orders and customers.
            It does not rely on any vendor-specific features and can
            therefore be deployed to any persistence provider.
        </description>
        <jta-data-source>jdbc/MyOrderDB</jta-data-source>
        <jar-file>MyOrderApp.jar</jar-file>
        <class>com.widgets.CustomerOrder</class>
        <class>com.widgets.Customer</class>
    </persistence-unit>
</persistence>

This file defines a persistence unit named OrderManagement, which uses a JTA-aware data source, jdbc/MyOrderDB. The jar-file and class elements specify managed persistence classes: entity classes, embeddable classes, and mapped superclasses. The jar-file element specifies JAR files that are visible to the packaged persistence unit that contain managed persistence classes, whereas the class element explicitly names managed persistence classes.

The jta-data-source (for JTA-aware data sources) and non-jta-data-source (for non-JTA-aware data sources) elements specify the global JNDI name of the data source to be used by the container.

The JAR file or directory whose META-INF directory contains persistence.xml is called the root of the persistence unit. The scope of the persistence unit is determined by the persistence unit's root. Each persistence unit must be identified with a name that is unique to the persistence unit's scope.

Persistent units can be packaged as part of a WAR or EJB JAR file or can be packaged as a JAR file that can then be included in an WAR or EAR file.

If you package the persistent unit as a set of classes in an EJB JAR file, persistence.xml should be put in the EJB JAR's META-INF directory.

If you package the persistence unit as a set of classes in a WAR file, persistence.xml should be located in the WAR file's WEB-INF/classes/META-INF directory.

If you package the persistence unit in a JAR file that will be included in a WAR or EAR file, the JAR file should be located in either

The WEB-INF/lib directory of a WAR

Or the EAR file's library directory

Note:

In the Java Persistence API 1.0, JAR files could be located at the root of an EAR file as the root of the persistence unit. This is no longer supported. Portable applications should use the EAR file's library directory as the root of the persistence unit.

37.4 Querying Entities

The Java Persistence API provides the following methods for querying entities.

The Java Persistence query language (JPQL) is a simple, string-based language similar to SQL used to query entities and their relationships. See Chapter 39, "The Java Persistence Query Language" for more information.

The Criteria API is used to create typesafe queries using Java programming language APIs to query for entities and their relationships. See Chapter 40, "Using the Criteria API to Create Queries" for more information.

Both JPQL and the Criteria API have advantages and disadvantages.

Just a few lines long, JPQL queries are typically more concise and more readable than Criteria queries. Developers familiar with SQL will find it easy to learn the syntax of JPQL. JPQL named queries can be defined in the entity class using a Java programming language annotation or in the application's deployment descriptor. JPQL queries are not typesafe, however, and require a cast when retrieving the query result from the entity manager. This means that type-casting errors may not be caught at compile time. JPQL queries don't support open-ended parameters.

Criteria queries allow you to define the query in the business tier of the application. Although this is also possible using JPQL dynamic queries, Criteria queries provide better performance because JPQL dynamic queries must be parsed each time they are called. Criteria queries are typesafe and therefore don't require casting, as JPQL queries do. The Criteria API is just another Java programming language API and doesn't require developers to learn the syntax of another query language. Criteria queries are typically more verbose than JPQL queries and require the developer to create several objects and perform operations on those objects before submitting the query to the entity manager.

37.5 Database Schema Creation

The persistence provider can be configured to automatically create the database tables, load data into the tables, and remove the tables during application deployment using standard properties in the application's deployment descriptor. These tasks are typically used during the development phase of a release, not against a production database.

The following is an example of a persistence.xml deployment descriptor that specifies that the provider should drop all database artifacts using a provided script, create the artifacts with a provided script, and load data from a provided script when the application is deployed:

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<persistence version="2.1" xmlns="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/persistence"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/persistence
 http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/persistence/persistence_2_1.xsd">
  <persistence-unit name="examplePU" transaction-type="JTA">
    <jta-data-source>java:global/ExampleDataSource</jta-data-source>
    <properties>
        <property name="javax.persistence.schema-generation.database.action"
                  value="drop-and-create"/>
        <property name="javax.persistence.schema-generation.create-source"
                  value="script"/>
        <property name="javax.persistence.schema-generation.create-script-source"
                  value="META-INF/sql/create.sql" />
        <property name="javax.persistence.sql-load-script-source"
                  value="META-INF/sql/data.sql" />
        <property name="javax.persistence.schema-generation.drop-source"
                  value="script" />
        <property name="javax.persistence.schema-generation.drop-script-source"
                  value="META-INF/sql/drop.sql" />
    </properties>
  </persistence-unit>
</persistence>

37.5.1 Configuring an Application to Create or Drop Database Tables

The javax.persistence.schema-generation.database.action property is used to specify the action taken by the persistence provider when an application is deployed. If the property is not set, the persistence provider will not create or drop any database artifacts.

Table 37-3 Schema Creation Actions

Setting | Description

none

|

No schema creation or deletion will take place.

create

|

The provider will create the database artifacts on application deployment. The artifacts will remain unchanged after application redeployment.

drop-and-create

|

Any artifacts in the database will be deleted, and the provider will create the database artifacts on deployment.

drop

|

Any artifacts in the database will be deleted on application deployment.

In this example, the persistence provider will delete any remaining database artifacts and then create the artifacts when the application is deployed:

<property name="javax.persistence.schema-generation.database.action"
           value="drop-and-create"/>

By default, the object/relational metadata in the persistence unit is used to create the database artifacts. You may also supply scripts used by the provider to create and delete the database artifacts. The javax.persistence.schema-generation.create-source and javax.persistence.schema-generation.drop-source properties control how the provider will create or delete the database artifacts.

Table 37-4 Settings for Create and Delete Source Properties

Setting | Description

metadata

|

Use the object/relational metadata in the application to create or delete the database artifacts.

script

|

Use a provided script for creating or deleting the database artifacts.

metadata-then-script

|

Use a combination of object/relational metadata, then a user-provided script to create or delete the database artifacts.

script-then-metadata

|

Use a combination of a user-provided script, then the object/relational metadata to create and delete the database artifacts.

In this example, the persistence provider will use a script packaged within the application to create the database artifacts:

<property name="javax.persistence.schema-generation.create-source"
           value="script"/>

If you specify a script in create-source or drop-source, specify the location of the script using the javax.persistence.schema-generation.create-script-source or javax.persistence.schema-generation.drop-script-source property. The location of the script is relative to the root of the persistence unit:

<property name="javax.persistence.schema-generation.create-script-source"
           value="META-INF/sql/create.sql" />

In the above example, the create-script-source is set to a SQL file called create.sql in the META-INF/sql directory relative to root of the persistence unit.

37.5.2 Loading Data Using SQL Scripts

If you want to populate the database tables with data before the application loads, specify the location of a load script in the javax.persistence.sql-load-script-source property. The location specified in this property is relative to the root of the persistence unit.

In this example, the load script is a file called data.sql in the META-INF/sql directory relative to the root of the persistence unit:

<property name="javax.persistence.sql-load-script-source"
          value="META-INF/sql/data.sql" />

37.6 Further Information about Persistence

For more information about the Java Persistence API, see

Java Persistence 2.1 API specification:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=338

EclipseLink, the Java Persistence API implementation in GlassFish Server:

http://www.eclipse.org/eclipselink/jpa.php

EclipseLink team blog:

http://eclipselink.blogspot.com/

EclipseLink wiki documentation:

http://wiki.eclipse.org/EclipseLink

42 Controlling Concurrent Access to Entity Data with Locking

This chapter details how to handle concurrent access to entity data, and the locking strategies available to Java Persistence API application developers.

The following topics are addressed here:

Overview of Entity Locking and Concurrency

Lock Modes

42.1 Overview of Entity Locking and Concurrency

Entity data is concurrently accessed if the data in a data source is accessed at the same time by multiple applications. Ensure that the underlying data's integrity is preserved when it is accessed concurrently.

When data is updated in the database tables in a transaction, the persistence provider assumes the database management system will hold short-term read locks and long-term write locks to maintain data integrity. Most persistence providers will delay database writes until the end of the transaction, except when the application explicitly calls for a flush (that is, the application calls the EntityManager.flush method or executes queries with the flush mode set to AUTO).

By default, persistence providers use optimistic locking, where, before committing changes to the data, the persistence provider checks that no other transaction has modified or deleted the data since the data was read. This is accomplished by a version column in the database table, with a corresponding version attribute in the entity class. When a row is modified, the version value is incremented. The original transaction checks the version attribute, and if the data has been modified by another transaction, a javax.persistence.OptimisticLockException will be thrown, and the original transaction will be rolled back. When the application specifies optimistic lock modes, the persistence provider verifies that a particular entity has not changed since it was read from the database even if the entity data was not modified.

Pessimistic locking goes further than optimistic locking. With pessimistic locking, the persistence provider creates a transaction that obtains a long-term lock on the data until the transaction is completed, which prevents other transactions from modifying or deleting the data until the lock has ended. Pessimistic locking is a better strategy than optimistic locking when the underlying data is frequently accessed and modified by many transactions.

Note:

Using pessimistic locks on entities that are not subject to frequent modification may result in decreased application performance.

42.1.1 Using Optimistic Locking

Use the javax.persistence.Version annotation to mark a persistent field or property as a version attribute of an entity. The version attribute enables the entity for optimistic concurrency control. The persistence provider reads and updates the version attribute when an entity instance is modified during a transaction. The application may read the version attribute, but must not modify the value.

Note:

Although some persistence providers may support optimistic locking for entities that do not have version attributes, portable applications should always use entities with version attributes when using optimistic locking. If the application attempts to lock an entity that does not have a version attribute, and the persistence provider does not support optimistic locking for non-versioned entities, a PersistenceException will be thrown.

The @Version annotation has the following requirements.

Only a single @Version attribute may be defined per entity.

The @Version attribute must be in the primary table for an entity mapped to multiple tables.

The type of the @Version attribute must be one of the following: int, Integer, long, Long, short, Short, or java.sql.Timestamp.

The following code snippet shows how to define a version attribute in an entity with persistent fields:

@Version
protected int version;

The following code snippet shows how to define a version attribute in an entity with persistent properties:

@Version
protected Short getVersion() { ... }

42.2 Lock Modes

The application may increase the level of locking for an entity by specifying the use of lock modes. Lock modes may be specified to increase the level of optimistic locking or to request the use of pessimistic locks.

The use of optimistic lock modes causes the persistence provider to check the version attributes for entities that were read (but not modified) during a transaction as well as for entities that were updated.

The use of pessimistic lock modes specifies that the persistence provider is to immediately acquire long-term read or write locks for the database data corresponding to entity state.

You can set the lock mode for an entity operation by specifying one of the lock modes defined in the javax.persistence.LockModeType enumerated type, listed in Table 42-1.

Table 42-1 Lock Modes for Concurrent Entity Access

Lock Mode | Description

OPTIMISTIC

|

Obtain an optimistic read lock for all entities with version attributes.

OPTIMISTIC_FORCE_INCREMENT

|

Obtain an optimistic read lock for all entities with version attributes, and increment the version attribute value.

PESSIMISTIC_READ

|

Immediately obtain a long-term read lock on the data to prevent the data from being modified or deleted. Other transactions may read the data while the lock is maintained, but may not modify or delete the data.

The persistence provider is permitted to obtain a database write lock when a read lock was requested, but not vice versa.

PESSIMISTIC_WRITE

|

Immediately obtain a long-term write lock on the data to prevent the data from being read, modified, or deleted.

PESSIMISTIC_FORCE_INCREMENT

|

Immediately obtain a long-term lock on the data to prevent the data from being modified or deleted, and increment the version attribute of versioned entities.

READ

|

A synonym for OPTIMISTIC. Use of LockModeType.OPTIMISTIC is to be preferred for new applications.

WRITE

|

A synonym for OPTIMISTIC_FORCE_INCREMENT. Use of LockModeType.OPTIMISTIC_FORCE_INCREMENT is to be preferred for new applications.

NONE

|

No additional locking will occur on the data in the database.

42.2.1 Setting the Lock Mode

To specify the lock mode, use one of the following techniques.

Call the EntityManager.lock method, passing in one of the lock modes:

EntityManager em = ...;
Person person = ...;
em.lock(person, LockModeType.OPTIMISTIC);

Call one of the EntityManager.find methods that take the lock mode as a parameter:

EntityManager em = ...;
String personPK = ...;
Person person = em.find(Person.class, personPK, 
    LockModeType.PESSIMISTIC_WRITE);

Call one of the EntityManager.refresh methods that take the lock mode as a parameter:

EntityManager em = ...;
String personPK = ...;
Person person = em.find(Person.class, personPK);
...
em.refresh(person, LockModeType.OPTIMISTIC_FORCE_INCREMENT);

Call the Query.setLockMode or TypedQuery.setLockMode method, passing the lock mode as the parameter:

Query q = em.createQuery(...);
q.setLockMode(LockModeType.PESSIMISTIC_FORCE_INCREMENT);

Add a lockMode element to the @NamedQuery annotation:

@NamedQuery(name="lockPersonQuery",
  query="SELECT p FROM Person p WHERE p.name LIKE :name",
  lockMode=PESSIMISTIC_READ)

42.2.2 Using Pessimistic Locking

Versioned entities, as well as entities that do not have version attributes, can be locked pessimistically.

To lock entities pessimistically, set the lock mode to PESSIMISTIC_READ, PESSIMISTIC_WRITE, or PESSIMISTIC_FORCE_INCREMENT.

If a pessimistic lock cannot be obtained on the database rows, and the failure to lock the data results in a transaction rollback, a PessimisticLockException is thrown. If a pessimistic lock cannot be obtained, but the locking failure doesn't result in a transaction rollback, a LockTimeoutException is thrown.

Pessimistically locking a versioned entity with PESSIMISTIC_FORCE_INCREMENT results in the version attribute being incremented even if the entity data is unmodified. When pessimistically locking a versioned entity, the persistence provider will perform the version checks that occur during optimistic locking, and if the version check fails, an OptimisticLockException will be thrown. An attempt to lock a non-versioned entity with PESSIMISTIC_FORCE_INCREMENT is not portable and may result in a PersistenceException if the persistence provider does not support optimistic locks for non-versioned entities. Locking a versioned entity with PESSIMISTIC_WRITE results in the version attribute being incremented if the transaction was successfully committed.

42.2.2.1 Pessimistic Locking Timeouts

Use the javax.persistence.lock.timeout property to specify the length of time in milliseconds the persistence provider should wait to obtain a lock on the database tables. If the time it takes to obtain a lock exceeds the value of this property, a LockTimeoutException will be thrown, but the current transaction will not be marked for rollback. If you set this property to 0, the persistence provider should throw a LockTimeoutException if it cannot immediately obtain a lock.

Note:

Portable applications should not rely on the setting of javax.persistence.lock.timeout, because the locking strategy and underlying database may mean that the timeout value cannot be used. The value of javax.persistence.lock.timeout is a hint, not a contract.

This property may be set programmatically by passing it to the EntityManager methods that allow lock modes to be specified, the Query.setLockMode and TypedQuery.setLockMode methods, the @NamedQuery annotation, and the Persistence.createEntityManagerFactory method. It may also be set as a property in the persistence.xml deployment descriptor.

If javax.persistence.lock.timeout is set in multiple places, the value will be determined in the following order:

The argument to one of the EntityManager or Query methods

The setting in the @NamedQuery annotation

The argument to the Persistence.createEntityManagerFactory method

The value in the persistence.xml deployment descriptor

39 The Java Persistence Query Language

The Java Persistence query language defines queries for entities and their persistent state. The query language allows you to write portable queries that work regardless of the underlying data store.

The query language uses the abstract persistence schemas of entities, including their relationships, for its data model and defines operators and expressions based on this data model. The scope of a query spans the abstract schemas of related entities that are packaged in the same persistence unit. The query language uses an SQL-like syntax to select objects or values based on entity abstract schema types and relationships among them.

This chapter relies on the material presented in earlier chapters. For conceptual information, see Chapter 37, "Introduction to the Java Persistence API". For code examples, see Chapter 38, "Running the Persistence Examples."

The following topics are addressed here:

Query Language Terminology

Creating Queries Using the Java Persistence Query Language

Simplified Query Language Syntax

Example Queries

Full Query Language Syntax

39.1 Query Language Terminology

The following list defines some of the terms referred to in this chapter.

Abstract schema: The persistent schema abstraction (persistent entities, their state, and their relationships) over which queries operate. The query language translates queries over this persistent schema abstraction into queries that are executed over the database schema to which entities are mapped.

Abstract schema type: The type to which the persistent property of an entity evaluates in the abstract schema. That is, each persistent field or property in an entity has a corresponding state field of the same type in the abstract schema. The abstract schema type of an entity is derived from the entity class and the metadata information provided by Java language annotations.

Backus-Naur Form (BNF): A notation that describes the syntax of high-level languages. The syntax diagrams in this chapter are in BNF notation.

Navigation: The traversal of relationships in a query language expression. The navigation operator is a period.

Path expression: An expression that navigates to an entity's state or relationship field.

State field: A persistent field of an entity.

Relationship field: A persistent field of an entity whose type is the abstract schema type of the related entity.

39.2 Creating Queries Using the Java Persistence Query Language

The EntityManager.createQuery and EntityManager.createNamedQuery methods are used to query the datastore by using Java Persistence query language queries.

The createQuery method is used to create dynamic queries, which are queries defined directly within an application's business logic:

public List findWithName(String name) {
return em.createQuery(
    "SELECT c FROM Customer c WHERE c.name LIKE :custName")
    .setParameter("custName", name)
    .setMaxResults(10)
    .getResultList();
}

The createNamedQuery method is used to create static queries, or queries that are defined in metadata by using the javax.persistence.NamedQuery annotation. The name element of @NamedQuery specifies the name of the query that will be used with the createNamedQuery method. The query element of @NamedQuery is the query:

@NamedQuery(
    name="findAllCustomersWithName",
    query="SELECT c FROM Customer c WHERE c.name LIKE :custName"
)

Here's an example of createNamedQuery, which uses the @NamedQuery:

@PersistenceContext
public EntityManager em;
...
customers = em.createNamedQuery("findAllCustomersWithName")
    .setParameter("custName", "Smith")
    .getResultList();

39.2.1 Named Parameters in Queries

Named parameters are query parameters that are prefixed with a colon (:). Named parameters in a query are bound to an argument by the following method:

javax.persistence.Query.setParameter(String name, Object value)

In the following example, the name argument to the findWithName business method is bound to the :custName named parameter in the query by calling Query.setParameter:

public List findWithName(String name) {
    return em.createQuery(
        "SELECT c FROM Customer c WHERE c.name LIKE :custName")
        .setParameter("custName", name)
        .getResultList();
}

Named parameters are case-sensitive and may be used by both dynamic and static queries.

39.2.2 Positional Parameters in Queries

You may use positional parameters instead of named parameters in queries. Positional parameters are prefixed with a question mark (?) followed by the numeric position of the parameter in the query. The method Query.setParameter(integer position, Object value) is used to set the parameter values.

In the following example, the findWithName business method is rewritten to use input parameters:

public List findWithName(String name) {
    return em.createQuery(
        "SELECT c FROM Customer c WHERE c.name LIKE ?1")
        .setParameter(1, name)
        .getResultList();
}

Input parameters are numbered starting from 1. Input parameters are case-sensitive, and may be used by both dynamic and static queries.

39.3 Simplified Query Language Syntax

This section briefly describes the syntax of the query language so that you can quickly move on to Example Queries. When you are ready to learn about the syntax in more detail, see Full Query Language Syntax.

39.3.1 Select Statements

A select query has six clauses: SELECT, FROM, WHERE, GROUP BY, HAVING, and ORDER BY. The SELECT and FROM clauses are required, but the WHERE, GROUP BY, HAVING, and ORDER BY clauses are optional. Here is the high-level BNF syntax of a query language select query:

QL_statement ::= select_clause from_clause 
  [where_clause][groupby_clause][having_clause][orderby_clause]

The BNF syntax defines the following clauses.

The SELECT clause defines the types of the objects or values returned by the query.

The FROM clause defines the scope of the query by declaring one or more identification variables, which can be referenced in the SELECT and WHERE clauses. An identification variable represents one of the following elements:

The abstract schema name of an entity

An element of a collection relationship

An element of a single-valued relationship

A member of a collection that is the multiple side of a one-to-many relationship

The WHERE clause is a conditional expression that restricts the objects or values retrieved by the query. Although the clause is optional, most queries have a WHERE clause.

The GROUP BY clause groups query results according to a set of properties.

The HAVING clause is used with the GROUP BY clause to further restrict the query results according to a conditional expression.

The ORDER BY clause sorts the objects or values returned by the query into a specified order.

39.3.2 Update and Delete Statements

Update and delete statements provide bulk operations over sets of entities. These statements have the following syntax:

update_statement :: = update_clause [where_clause] 
delete_statement :: = delete_clause [where_clause]

The update and delete clauses determine the type of the entities to be updated or deleted. The WHERE clause may be used to restrict the scope of the update or delete operation.

39.4 Example Queries

The following queries are from the Player entity of the roster application, which is documented in The roster Application.

39.4.1 Simple Queries

If you are unfamiliar with the query language, these simple queries are a good place to start.

39.4.1.1 A Basic Select Query

SELECT p
FROM Player p

Data retrieved: All players.

Description: The FROM clause declares an identification variable named p, omitting the optional keyword AS. If the AS keyword were included, the clause would be written as follows:

FROM Player AS p

The Player element is the abstract schema name of the Player entity.

See also: Identification Variables.

39.4.1.2 Eliminating Duplicate Values

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p
WHERE p.position = ?1

Data retrieved: The players with the position specified by the query's parameter.

Description: The DISTINCT keyword eliminates duplicate values.

The WHERE clause restricts the players retrieved by checking their position, a persistent field of the Player entity. The ?1 element denotes the input parameter of the query.

See also: Input Parameters and The DISTINCT Keyword.

39.4.1.3 Using Named Parameters

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p
WHERE p.position = :position AND p.name = :name

Data retrieved: The players having the specified positions and names.

Description: The position and name elements are persistent fields of the Player entity. The WHERE clause compares the values of these fields with the named parameters of the query, set using the Query.setNamedParameter method. The query language denotes a named input parameter using a colon (:) followed by an identifier. The first input parameter is :position, the second is :name.

39.4.2 Queries That Navigate to Related Entities

In the query language, an expression can traverse, or navigate, to related entities. These expressions are the primary difference between the Java Persistence query language and SQL. Queries navigates to related entities, whereas SQL joins tables.

39.4.2.1 A Simple Query with Relationships

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p, IN (p.teams) t

Data retrieved: All players who belong to a team.

Description: The FROM clause declares two identification variables: p and t. The p variable represents the Player entity, and the t variable represents the related Team entity. The declaration for t references the previously declared p variable. The IN keyword signifies that teams is a collection of related entities. The p.teams expression navigates from a Player to its related Team. The period in the p.teams expression is the navigation operator.

You may also use the JOIN statement to write the same query:

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p JOIN p.teams t

This query could also be rewritten as:

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p
WHERE p.team IS NOT EMPTY

39.4.2.2 Navigating to Single-Valued Relationship Fields

Use the JOIN clause statement to navigate to a single-valued relationship field:

SELECT t
FROM Team t JOIN t.league l
WHERE l.sport = 'soccer' OR l.sport ='football'

In this example, the query will return all teams that are in either soccer or football leagues.

39.4.2.3 Traversing Relationships with an Input Parameter

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p, IN (p.teams) AS t
WHERE t.city = :city

Data retrieved: The players whose teams belong to the specified city.

Description: This query is similar to the previous example but adds an input parameter. The AS keyword in the FROM clause is optional. In the WHERE clause, the period preceding the persistent variable city is a delimiter, not a navigation operator. Strictly speaking, expressions can navigate to relationship fields (related entities) but not to persistent fields. To access a persistent field, an expression uses the period as a delimiter.

Expressions cannot navigate beyond (or further qualify) relationship fields that are collections. In the syntax of an expression, a collection-valued field is a terminal symbol. Because the teams field is a collection, the WHERE clause cannot specify p.teams.city (an illegal expression).

See also: Path Expressions.

39.4.2.4 Traversing Multiple Relationships

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p, IN (p.teams) t
WHERE t.league = :league

Data retrieved: The players who belong to the specified league.

Description: The expressions in this query navigate over two relationships. The p.teams expression navigates the Player-Team relationship, and the t.league expression navigates the Team-League relationship.

In the other examples, the input parameters are String objects; in this example, the parameter is an object whose type is a League. This type matches the league relationship field in the comparison expression of the WHERE clause.

39.4.2.5 Navigating According to Related Fields

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p, IN (p.teams) t
WHERE t.league.sport = :sport

Data retrieved: The players who participate in the specified sport.

Description: The sport persistent field belongs to the League entity. To reach the sport field, the query must first navigate from the Player entity to Team (p.teams) and then from Team to the League entity (t.league). Because it is not a collection, the league relationship field can be followed by the sport persistent field.

39.4.3 Queries with Other Conditional Expressions

Every WHERE clause must specify a conditional expression, of which there are several kinds. In the previous examples, the conditional expressions are comparison expressions that test for equality. The following examples demonstrate some of the other kinds of conditional expressions. For descriptions of all conditional expressions, see WHERE Clause.

39.4.3.1 The LIKE Expression

SELECT p
FROM Player p
WHERE p.name LIKE 'Mich%'

Data retrieved: All players whose names begin with "Mich."

Description: The LIKE expression uses wildcard characters to search for strings that match the wildcard pattern. In this case, the query uses the LIKE expression and the % wildcard to find all players whose names begin with the string "Mich." For example, "Michael" and "Michelle" both match the wildcard pattern.

See also: LIKE Expressions.

39.4.3.2 The IS NULL Expression

SELECT t
FROM Team t
WHERE t.league IS NULL

Data retrieved: All teams not associated with a league.

Description: The IS NULL expression can be used to check whether a relationship has been set between two entities. In this case, the query checks whether the teams are associated with any leagues and returns the teams that do not have a league.

See also: NULL Comparison Expressions and NULL Values.

39.4.3.3 The IS EMPTY Expression

SELECT p
FROM Player p
WHERE p.teams IS EMPTY

Data retrieved: All players who do not belong to a team.

Description: The teams relationship field of the Player entity is a collection. If a player does not belong to a team, the teams collection is empty, and the conditional expression is TRUE.

See also: Empty Collection Comparison Expressions.

39.4.3.4 The BETWEEN Expression

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p
WHERE p.salary BETWEEN :lowerSalary AND :higherSalary

Data retrieved: The players whose salaries fall within the range of the specified salaries.

Description: This BETWEEN expression has three arithmetic expressions: a persistent field (p.salary) and the two input parameters (:lowerSalary and :higherSalary). The following expression is equivalent to the BETWEEN expression:

p.salary >= :lowerSalary AND p.salary <= :higherSalary

See also: BETWEEN Expressions.

39.4.3.5 Comparison Operators

SELECT DISTINCT p1
FROM Player p1, Player p2
WHERE p1.salary > p2.salary AND p2.name = :name

Data retrieved: All players whose salaries are higher than the salary of the player with the specified name.

Description: The FROM clause declares two identification variables (p1 and p2) of the same type (Player). Two identification variables are needed because the WHERE clause compares the salary of one player (p2) with that of the other players (p1).

See also: Identification Variables.

39.4.4 Bulk Updates and Deletes

The following examples show how to use the UPDATE and DELETE expressions in queries. UPDATE and DELETE operate on multiple entities according to the condition or conditions set in the WHERE clause. The WHERE clause in UPDATE and DELETE queries follows the same rules as SELECT queries.

39.4.4.1 Update Queries

UPDATE Player p
SET p.status = 'inactive'
WHERE p.lastPlayed < :inactiveThresholdDate

Description: This query sets the status of a set of players to inactive if the player's last game was longer ago than the date specified in inactiveThresholdDate.

39.4.4.2 Delete Queries

DELETE
FROM Player p
WHERE p.status = 'inactive'
AND p.teams IS EMPTY

Description: This query deletes all inactive players who are not on a team.

39.5 Full Query Language Syntax

This section discusses the query language syntax, as defined in the Java Persistence API 2.0 specification available at http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=317. Much of the following material paraphrases or directly quotes the specification.

39.5.1 BNF Symbols

Table 39-1 describes the BNF symbols used in this chapter.

Table 39-1 BNF Symbol Summary

Symbol | Description

::=

|

The element to the left of the symbol is defined by the constructs on the right.

*

|

The preceding construct may occur zero or more times.

{...}

|

The constructs within the braces are grouped together.

[...]

|

The constructs within the brackets are optional.

|

|

An exclusive OR.

BOLDFACE

|

A keyword; although capitalized in the BNF diagram, keywords are not case-sensitive.

White space

|

A whitespace character can be a space, a horizontal tab, or a line feed.

39.5.2 BNF Grammar of the Java Persistence Query Language

Here is the entire BNF diagram for the query language:

QL_statement ::= select_statement | update_statement | delete_statement
select_statement ::= select_clause from_clause [where_clause] [groupby_clause] 
    [having_clause] [orderby_clause]
update_statement ::= update_clause [where_clause]
delete_statement ::= delete_clause [where_clause]
from_clause ::=
    FROM identification_variable_declaration
        {, {identification_variable_declaration |
            collection_member_declaration}}*
identification_variable_declaration ::=
        range_variable_declaration { join | fetch_join }*
range_variable_declaration ::= abstract_schema_name [AS]
        identification_variable
join ::= join_spec join_association_path_expression [AS]
        identification_variable
fetch_join ::= join_specFETCH join_association_path_expression
association_path_expression ::=
        collection_valued_path_expression |
        single_valued_association_path_expression
join_spec::= [LEFT [OUTER] |INNER] JOIN
join_association_path_expression ::=
        join_collection_valued_path_expression |
        join_single_valued_association_path_expression
join_collection_valued_path_expression::=
    identification_variable.collection_valued_association_field
join_single_valued_association_path_expression::=
        identification_variable.single_valued_association_field
collection_member_declaration ::=
        IN (collection_valued_path_expression) [AS]
        identification_variable
single_valued_path_expression ::=
        state_field_path_expression |
        single_valued_association_path_expression
state_field_path_expression ::=
    {identification_variable |
    single_valued_association_path_expression}.state_field
single_valued_association_path_expression ::=
    identification_variable.{single_valued_association_field.}*
    single_valued_association_field
collection_valued_path_expression ::=
    identification_variable.{single_valued_association_field.}*
    collection_valued_association_field
state_field ::=
    {embedded_class_state_field.}*simple_state_field
update_clause ::=UPDATE abstract_schema_name [[AS]
    identification_variable] SET update_item {, update_item}*
update_item ::= [identification_variable.]{state_field |
    single_valued_association_field} = new_value
new_value ::=
     simple_arithmetic_expression |
    string_primary |
    datetime_primary |
    boolean_primary |
    enum_primary simple_entity_expression |
    NULL
delete_clause ::= DELETE FROM abstract_schema_name [[AS]
    identification_variable]
select_clause ::= SELECT [DISTINCT] select_expression {,
    select_expression}*
select_expression ::=
    single_valued_path_expression |
    aggregate_expression |
    identification_variable |
    OBJECT(identification_variable) |
    constructor_expression
constructor_expression ::=
    NEW constructor_name(constructor_item {,
    constructor_item}*)
constructor_item ::= single_valued_path_expression |
    aggregate_expression
aggregate_expression ::=
    {AVG |MAX |MIN |SUM} ([DISTINCT]
        state_field_path_expression) |
    COUNT ([DISTINCT] identification_variable |
        state_field_path_expression |
        single_valued_association_path_expression)
where_clause ::= WHERE conditional_expression
groupby_clause ::= GROUP BY groupby_item {, groupby_item}*
groupby_item ::= single_valued_path_expression
having_clause ::= HAVING conditional_expression
orderby_clause ::= ORDER BY orderby_item {, orderby_item}*
orderby_item ::= state_field_path_expression [ASC |DESC]
subquery ::= simple_select_clause subquery_from_clause
    [where_clause] [groupby_clause] [having_clause]
subquery_from_clause ::=
    FROM subselect_identification_variable_declaration
        {, subselect_identification_variable_declaration}*
subselect_identification_variable_declaration ::=
    identification_variable_declaration |
    association_path_expression [AS] identification_variable |
    collection_member_declaration
simple_select_clause ::= SELECT [DISTINCT]
    simple_select_expression
simple_select_expression::=
    single_valued_path_expression |
    aggregate_expression |
    identification_variable
conditional_expression ::= conditional_term |
    conditional_expression OR conditional_term
conditional_term ::= conditional_factor | conditional_term AND
    conditional_factor
conditional_factor ::= [NOT] conditional_primary
conditional_primary ::= simple_cond_expression |(
    conditional_expression)
simple_cond_expression ::=
    comparison_expression |
    between_expression |
    like_expression |
    in_expression |
    null_comparison_expression |
    empty_collection_comparison_expression |
    collection_member_expression |
    exists_expression
between_expression ::=
    arithmetic_expression [NOT] BETWEEN
        arithmetic_expressionAND arithmetic_expression |
    string_expression [NOT] BETWEEN string_expression AND
        string_expression |
    datetime_expression [NOT] BETWEEN
        datetime_expression AND datetime_expression
in_expression ::=
    state_field_path_expression [NOT] IN (in_item {, in_item}*
    | subquery)
in_item ::= literal | input_parameter
like_expression ::=
    string_expression [NOT] LIKE pattern_value [ESCAPE
        escape_character]
null_comparison_expression ::=
    {single_valued_path_expression | input_parameter} IS [NOT]
        NULL
empty_collection_comparison_expression ::=
    collection_valued_path_expression IS [NOT] EMPTY
collection_member_expression ::= entity_expression
    [NOT] MEMBER [OF] collection_valued_path_expression
exists_expression::= [NOT] EXISTS (subquery)
all_or_any_expression ::= {ALL |ANY |SOME} (subquery)
comparison_expression ::=
    string_expression comparison_operator {string_expression |
    all_or_any_expression} |
    boolean_expression {= |<> } {boolean_expression |
    all_or_any_expression} |
    enum_expression {= |<> } {enum_expression |
    all_or_any_expression} |
    datetime_expression comparison_operator
        {datetime_expression | all_or_any_expression} |
    entity_expression {= |<> } {entity_expression |
    all_or_any_expression} |
    arithmetic_expression comparison_operator
        {arithmetic_expression | all_or_any_expression}
comparison_operator ::= = |> |>= |< |<= |<>
arithmetic_expression ::= simple_arithmetic_expression |
    (subquery)
simple_arithmetic_expression ::=
    arithmetic_term | simple_arithmetic_expression {+ |- }
        arithmetic_term
arithmetic_term ::= arithmetic_factor | arithmetic_term {* |/ }
    arithmetic_factor
arithmetic_factor ::= [{+ |- }] arithmetic_primary
arithmetic_primary ::=
    state_field_path_expression |
    numeric_literal |
    (simple_arithmetic_expression) |
    input_parameter |
    functions_returning_numerics |
    aggregate_expression
string_expression ::= string_primary | (subquery)
string_primary ::=
    state_field_path_expression |
    string_literal |
    input_parameter |
    functions_returning_strings |
    aggregate_expression
datetime_expression ::= datetime_primary | (subquery)
datetime_primary ::=
    state_field_path_expression |
    input_parameter |
    functions_returning_datetime |
    aggregate_expression
boolean_expression ::= boolean_primary | (subquery)
boolean_primary ::=
    state_field_path_expression |
    boolean_literal |
    input_parameter
 enum_expression ::= enum_primary | (subquery)
enum_primary ::=
    state_field_path_expression |
    enum_literal |
    input_parameter
entity_expression ::=
    single_valued_association_path_expression |
        simple_entity_expression
simple_entity_expression ::=
    identification_variable |
    input_parameter
functions_returning_numerics::=
    LENGTH(string_primary) |
    LOCATE(string_primary, string_primary[,
        simple_arithmetic_expression]) |
    ABS(simple_arithmetic_expression) |
    SQRT(simple_arithmetic_expression) |
    MOD(simple_arithmetic_expression,
        simple_arithmetic_expression) |
    SIZE(collection_valued_path_expression)
functions_returning_datetime ::=
    CURRENT_DATE |
    CURRENT_TIME |
    CURRENT_TIMESTAMP
functions_returning_strings ::=
    CONCAT(string_primary, string_primary) |
    SUBSTRING(string_primary,
        simple_arithmetic_expression,
        simple_arithmetic_expression)|
    TRIM([[trim_specification] [trim_character] FROM]
        string_primary) |
    LOWER(string_primary) |
    UPPER(string_primary)
trim_specification ::= LEADING | TRAILING | BOTH

39.5.3 FROM Clause

The FROM clause defines the domain of the query by declaring identification variables.

39.5.3.1 Identifiers

An identifier is a sequence of one or more characters. The first character must be a valid first character (letter, $, _) in an identifier of the Java programming language, hereafter in this chapter called simply "Java." Each subsequent character in the sequence must be a valid nonfirst character (letter, digit, $, _) in a Java identifier. (For details, see the Java SE API documentation of the isJavaIdentifierStart and isJavaIdentifierPart methods of the Character class.) The question mark (?) is a reserved character in the query language and cannot be used in an identifier.

A query language identifier is case-sensitive, with two exceptions:

Keywords

Identification variables

An identifier cannot be the same as a query language keyword. Here is a list of query language keywords:

ABS
ALL
AND
ANY
AS
ASC
AVG
BETWEEN
BIT_LENGTH
BOTH
BY
CASE
CHAR_LENGTH
CHARACTER_LENGTH
CLASS
COALESCE
CONCAT
COUNT
CURRENT_DATE
CURRENT_TIMESTAMP
DELETE
DESC
DISTINCT
ELSE
EMPTY
END
ENTRY
ESCAPE
EXISTS
FALSE
FETCH
FROM
GROUP
HAVING
IN
INDEX
INNER
IS
JOIN
KEY
LEADING
LEFT
LENGTH
LIKE
LOCATE
LOWER
MAX
MEMBER
MIN
MOD
NEW
NOT
NULL
NULLIF
OBJECT
OF
OR
ORDER
OUTER
POSITION
SELECT
SET
SIZE
SOME
SQRT
SUBSTRING
SUM
THEN
TRAILING
TRIM
TRUE
TYPE
UNKNOWN
UPDATE
UPPER
VALUE
WHEN
WHERE

It is not recommended that you use an SQL keyword as an identifier, because the list of keywords may expand to include other reserved SQL words in the future.

39.5.3.2 Identification Variables

An identification variable is an identifier declared in the FROM clause. Although they can reference identification variables, the SELECT and WHERE clauses cannot declare them. All identification variables must be declared in the FROM clause.

Because it is an identifier, an identification variable has the same naming conventions and restrictions as an identifier, with the exception that an identification variable is case-insensitive. For example, an identification variable cannot be the same as a query language keyword. (See Identifiers for more naming rules.) Also, within a given persistence unit, an identification variable name must not match the name of any entity or abstract schema.

The FROM clause can contain multiple declarations, separated by commas. A declaration can reference another identification variable that has been previously declared (to the left). In the following FROM clause, the variable t references the previously declared variable p:

FROM Player p, IN (p.teams) AS t

Even if it is not used in the WHERE clause, an identification variable's declaration can affect the results of the query. For example, compare the next two queries. The following query returns all players, whether or not they belong to a team:

SELECT p
FROM Player p

In contrast, because it declares the t identification variable, the next query fetches all players who belong to a team:

SELECT p
FROM Player p, IN (p.teams) AS t

The following query returns the same results as the preceding query, but the WHERE clause makes it easier to read:

SELECT p
FROM Player p
WHERE p.teams IS NOT EMPTY

An identification variable always designates a reference to a single value whose type is that of the expression used in the declaration. There are two kinds of declarations: range variable and collection member.

39.5.3.3 Range Variable Declarations

To declare an identification variable as an abstract schema type, you specify a range variable declaration. In other words, an identification variable can range over the abstract schema type of an entity. In the following example, an identification variable named p represents the abstract schema named Player:

FROM Player p

A range variable declaration can include the optional AS operator:

FROM Player AS p

To obtain objects, a query usually uses path expressions to navigate through the relationships. But for those objects that cannot be obtained by navigation, you can use a range variable declaration to designate a starting point, or query root.

If the query compares multiple values of the same abstract schema type, the FROM clause must declare multiple identification variables for the abstract schema:

FROM Player p1, Player p2

For an example of such a query, see Comparison Operators.

39.5.3.4 Collection Member Declarations

In a one-to-many relationship, the multiple side consists of a collection of entities. An identification variable can represent a member of this collection. To access a collection member, the path expression in the variable's declaration navigates through the relationships in the abstract schema. (For more information on path expressions, see Path Expressions.) Because a path expression can be based on another path expression, the navigation can traverse several relationships. See Traversing Multiple Relationships.

A collection member declaration must include the IN operator but can omit the optional AS operator.

In the following example, the entity represented by the abstract schema named Player has a relationship field called teams. The identification variable called t represents a single member of the teams collection:

FROM Player p, IN (p.teams) t

39.5.3.5 Joins

The JOIN operator is used to traverse over relationships between entities and is functionally similar to the IN operator.

In the following example, the query joins over the relationship between customers and orders:

SELECT c
FROM Customer c JOIN c.orders o
WHERE c.status = 1 AND o.totalPrice > 10000

The INNER keyword is optional:

SELECT c
FROM Customer c INNER JOIN c.orders o
WHERE c.status = 1 AND o.totalPrice > 10000

These examples are equivalent to the following query, which uses the IN operator:

SELECT c
FROM Customer c, IN (c.orders) o
WHERE c.status = 1 AND o.totalPrice > 10000

You can also join a single-valued relationship:

SELECT t
FROM Team t JOIN t.league l
WHERE l.sport = :sport

A LEFT JOIN or LEFT OUTER JOIN retrieves a set of entities where matching values in the join condition may be absent. The OUTER keyword is optional:

SELECT c.name, o.totalPrice
FROM CustomerOrder o LEFT JOIN o.customer c

A FETCH JOIN is a join operation that returns associated entities as a side effect of running the query. In the following example, the query returns a set of departments and, as a side effect, the associated employees of the departments, even though the employees were not explicitly retrieved by the SELECT clause:

SELECT d
FROM Department d LEFT JOIN FETCH d.employees
WHERE d.deptno = 1

39.5.4 Path Expressions

Path expressions are important constructs in the syntax of the query language for several reasons. First, path expressions define navigation paths through the relationships in the abstract schema. These path definitions affect both the scope and the results of a query. Second, path expressions can appear in any of the main clauses of a query (SELECT, DELETE, HAVING, UPDATE, WHERE, FROM, GROUP BY, ORDER BY). Finally, although much of the query language is a subset of SQL, path expressions are extensions not found in SQL.

39.5.4.1 Examples of Path Expressions

Here, the WHERE clause contains a single_valued_path_expression; the p is an identification variable, and salary is a persistent field of Player:

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p
WHERE p.salary BETWEEN :lowerSalary AND :higherSalary

Here, the WHERE clause also contains a single_valued_path_expression; t is an identification variable, league is a single-valued relationship field, and sport is a persistent field of league:

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p, IN (p.teams) t
WHERE t.league.sport = :sport

Here, the WHERE clause contains a collection_valued_path_expression; p is an identification variable, and teams designates a collection-valued relationship field:

SELECT DISTINCT p
FROM Player p
WHERE p.teams IS EMPTY

39.5.4.2 Expression Types

The type of a path expression is the type of the object represented by the ending element, which can be one of the following:

Persistent field

Single-valued relationship field

Collection-valued relationship field

For example, the type of the expression p.salary is double because the terminating persistent field (salary) is a double.

In the expression p.teams, the terminating element is a collection-valued relationship field (teams). This expression's type is a collection of the abstract schema type named Team. Because Team is the abstract schema name for the Team entity, this type maps to the entity. For more information on the type mapping of abstract schemas, see Return Types.

39.5.4.3 Navigation

A path expression enables the query to navigate to related entities. The terminating elements of an expression determine whether navigation is allowed. If an expression contains a single-valued relationship field, the navigation can continue to an object that is related to the field. However, an expression cannot navigate beyond a persistent field or a collection-valued relationship field. For example, the expression p.teams.league.sport is illegal because teams is a collection-valued relationship field. To reach the sport field, the FROM clause could define an identification variable named t for the teams field:

FROM Player AS p, IN (p.teams) t
WHERE t.league.sport = 'soccer'

39.5.5 WHERE Clause

The WHERE clause specifies a conditional expression that limits the values returned by the query. The query returns all corresponding values in the data store for which the conditional expression is TRUE. Although usually specified, the WHERE clause is optional. If the WHERE clause is omitted, the query returns all values. The high-level syntax for the WHERE clause is as follows:

where_clause ::= WHERE conditional_expression

39.5.5.1 Literals

There are four kinds of literals: string, numeric, Boolean, and enum.

String literals: A string literal is enclosed in single quotes:

'Duke'

If a string literal contains a single quote, you indicate the quote by using two single quotes:

'Duke''s'

Like a Java String, a string literal in the query language uses the Unicode character encoding.

Numeric literals: There are two types of numeric literals: exact and approximate.

An exact numeric literal is a numeric value without a decimal point, such as 65, –233, and +12. Using the Java integer syntax, exact numeric literals support numbers in the range of a Java long.

An approximate numeric literal is a numeric value in scientific notation, such as 57., –85.7, and +2.1. Using the syntax of the Java floating-point literal, approximate numeric literals support numbers in the range of a Java double.

Boolean literals: A Boolean literal is either TRUE or FALSE. These keywords are not case-sensitive.

Enum literals: The Java Persistence query language supports the use of enum literals using the Java enum literal syntax. The enum class name must be specified as a fully qualified class name:

SELECT e
FROM Employee e
WHERE e.status = com.example.EmployeeStatus.FULL_TIME

39.5.5.2 Input Parameters

An input parameter can be either a named parameter or a positional parameter.

A named input parameter is designated by a colon (:) followed by a string; for example, :name.

A positional input parameter is designated by a question mark (?) followed by an integer. For example, the first input parameter is ?1, the second is ?2, and so forth.

The following rules apply to input parameters.

They can be used only in a WHERE or HAVING clause.

Positional parameters must be numbered, starting with the integer 1.

Named parameters and positional parameters may not be mixed in a single query.

Named parameters are case-sensitive.

39.5.5.3 Conditional Expressions

A WHERE clause consists of a conditional expression, which is evaluated from left to right within a precedence level. You can change the order of evaluation by using parentheses.

39.5.5.4 Operators and Their Precedence

Table 39-2 lists the query language operators in order of decreasing precedence.

Table 39-2 Query Language Order Precedence

Type | Precedence Order

Navigation

|

. (a period)

Arithmetic

|

+ – (unary)

* / (multiplication and division)

+ – (addition and subtraction)

Comparison

|

=

>

>=

<

<=

<> (not equal)

[NOT] BETWEEN

[NOT] LIKE

[NOT] IN

IS [NOT] NULL

IS [NOT] EMPTY

[NOT] MEMBER OF

Logical

|

NOT

AND

OR

39.5.5.5 BETWEEN Expressions

A BETWEEN expression determines whether an arithmetic expression falls within a range of values.

These two expressions are equivalent:

p.age BETWEEN 15 AND 19
p.age >= 15 AND p.age <= 19

The following two expressions also are equivalent:

p.age NOT BETWEEN 15 AND 19
p.age < 15 OR p.age > 19

If an arithmetic expression has a NULL value, the value of the BETWEEN expression is unknown.

39.5.5.6 IN Expressions

An IN expression determines whether a string belongs to a set of string literals or whether a number belongs to a set of number values.

The path expression must have a string or numeric value. If the path expression has a NULL value, the value of the IN expression is unknown.

In the following example, the expression is TRUE if the country is UK , but FALSE if the country is Peru:

o.country IN ('UK', 'US', 'France')

You may also use input parameters:

o.country IN ('UK', 'US', 'France', :country)

39.5.5.7 LIKE Expressions

A LIKE expression determines whether a wildcard pattern matches a string.

The path expression must have a string or numeric value. If this value is NULL, the value of the LIKE expression is unknown. The pattern value is a string literal that can contain wildcard characters. The underscore (_) wildcard character represents any single character. The percent (%) wildcard character represents zero or more characters. The ESCAPE clause specifies an escape character for the wildcard characters in the pattern value. Table 39-3 shows some sample LIKE expressions.

Table 39-3 LIKE Expression Examples

Expression | TRUE | FALSE

address.phone LIKE '12%3'

|

'123'

'12993'

|

'1234'

asentence.word LIKE 'l_se'

|

'lose'

|

'loose'

aword.underscored LIKE '\_%' ESCAPE '\'

|

'_foo'

|

'bar'

address.phone NOT LIKE '12%3'

|

'1234'

|

'123'

'12993'

39.5.5.8 NULL Comparison Expressions

A NULL comparison expression tests whether a single-valued path expression or an input parameter has a NULL value. Usually, the NULL comparison expression is used to test whether a single-valued relationship has been set:

SELECT t
FROM Team t
WHERE t.league IS NULL

This query selects all teams where the league relationship is not set. Note that the following query is not equivalent:

SELECT t
FROM Team t
WHERE t.league = NULL

The comparison with NULL using the equals operator (=) always returns an unknown value, even if the relationship is not set. The second query will always return an empty result.

39.5.5.9 Empty Collection Comparison Expressions

The IS [NOT] EMPTY comparison expression tests whether a collection-valued path expression has no elements. In other words, it tests whether a collection-valued relationship has been set.

If the collection-valued path expression is NULL, the empty collection comparison expression has a NULL value.

Here is an example that finds all orders that do not have any line items:

SELECT o
FROM CustomerOrder o
WHERE o.lineItems IS EMPTY

39.5.5.10 Collection Member Expressions

The [NOT] MEMBER [OF] collection member expression determines whether a value is a member of a collection. The value and the collection members must have the same type.

If either the collection-valued or single-valued path expression is unknown, the collection member expression is unknown. If the collection-valued path expression designates an empty collection, the collection member expression is FALSE.

The OF keyword is optional.

The following example tests whether a line item is part of an order:

SELECT o
FROM CustomerOrder o
WHERE :lineItem MEMBER OF o.lineItems

39.5.5.11 Subqueries

Subqueries may be used in the WHERE or HAVING clause of a query. Subqueries must be surrounded by parentheses.

The following example finds all customers who have placed more than ten orders:

SELECT c
FROM Customer c
WHERE (SELECT COUNT(o) FROM c.orders o)> 10

Subqueries may contain EXISTS, ALL, and ANY expressions.

EXISTS expressions: The [NOT] EXISTS expression is used with a subquery and is true only if the result of the subquery consists of one or more values; otherwise, it is false.

The following example finds all employees whose spouses are also employees:

SELECT DISTINCT emp
FROM Employee emp
WHERE EXISTS (
    SELECT spouseEmp
    FROM Employee spouseEmp
    WHERE spouseEmp = emp.spouse)

ALL and ANY expressions: The ALL expression is used with a subquery and is true if all the values returned by the subquery are true or if the subquery is empty.

The ANY expression is used with a subquery and is true if some of the values returned by the subquery are true. An ANY expression is false if the subquery result is empty or if all the values returned are false. The SOME keyword is synonymous with ANY.

The ALL and ANY expressions are used with the =, <, <=, >, >=, and <> comparison operators.

The following example finds all employees whose salaries are higher than the salaries of the managers in the employee's department:

SELECT emp
FROM Employee emp
WHERE emp.salary > ALL (
    SELECT m.salary
    FROM Manager m
    WHERE m.department = emp.department)

39.5.5.12 Functional Expressions

The query language includes several string, arithmetic, and date/time functions that may be used in the SELECT, WHERE, or HAVING clause of a query. The functions are listed in Table 39-4, Table 39-5, and Table 39-6.

In Table 39-4, the start and length arguments are of type int and designate positions in the String argument. The first position in a string is designated by 1.

Table 39-4 String Expressions

Function Syntax | Return Type

CONCAT(String, String)

|

String

LENGTH(String)

|

int

LOCATE(String, String [, start])

|

int

SUBSTRING(String, start, length)

|

String

TRIM([[LEADING|TRAILING|BOTH] char) FROM] (String)

|

String

LOWER(String)

|

String

UPPER(String)

|

String

The CONCAT function concatenates two strings into one string.

The LENGTH function returns the length of a string in characters as an integer.

The LOCATE function returns the position of a given string within a string. This function returns the first position at which the string was found as an integer. The first argument is the string to be located. The second argument is the string to be searched. The optional third argument is an integer that represents the starting string position. By default, LOCATE starts at the beginning of the string. The starting position of a string is 1. If the string cannot be located, LOCATE returns 0.

The SUBSTRING function returns a string that is a substring of the first argument based on the starting position and length.

The TRIM function trims the specified character from the beginning and/or end of a string. If no character is specified, TRIM removes spaces or blanks from the string. If the optional LEADING specification is used, TRIM removes only the leading characters from the string. If the optional TRAILING specification is used, TRIM removes only the trailing characters from the string. The default is BOTH, which removes the leading and trailing characters from the string.

The LOWER and UPPER functions convert a string to lowercase or uppercase, respectively.

In Table 39-5, the number argument can be an int, a float, or a double.

Table 39-5 Arithmetic Expressions

Function Syntax | Return Type

ABS(number)

|

int, float, or double

MOD(int, int)

|

int

SQRT(double)

|

double

SIZE(Collection)

|

int

The ABS function takes a numeric expression and returns a number of the same type as the argument.

The MOD function returns the remainder of the first argument divided by the second.

The SQRT function returns the square root of a number.

The SIZE function returns an integer of the number of elements in the given collection.

In Table 39-6, the date/time functions return the date, time, or timestamp on the database server.

Table 39-6 Date/Time Expressions

Function Syntax | Return Type

CURRENT_DATE

|

java.sql.Date

CURRENT_TIME

|

java.sql.Time

CURRENT_TIMESTAMP

|

java.sql.Timestamp

39.5.5.13 Case Expressions

Case expressions change based on a condition, similar to the case keyword of the Java programming language. The CASE keyword indicates the start of a case expression, and the expression is terminated by the END keyword. The WHEN and THEN keywords define individual conditions, and the ELSE keyword defines the default condition should none of the other conditions be satisfied.

The following query selects the name of a person and a conditional string, depending on the subtype of the Person entity. If the subtype is Student, the string kid is returned. If the subtype is Guardian or Staff, the string adult is returned. If the entity is some other subtype of Person, the string unknown is returned:

SELECT p.name
CASE TYPE(p)
    WHEN Student THEN 'kid'
    WHEN Guardian THEN 'adult'
    WHEN Staff THEN 'adult'
    ELSE 'unknown'
END
FROM Person p

The following query sets a discount for various types of customers. Gold-level customers get a 20% discount, silver-level customers get a 15% discount, bronze-level customers get a 10% discount, and everyone else gets a 5% discount:

UPDATE Customer c
SET c.discount = 
    CASE c.level
        WHEN 'Gold' THEN 20
        WHEN 'SILVER' THEN 15
        WHEN 'Bronze' THEN 10
        ELSE 5
    END

39.5.5.14 NULL Values

If the target of a reference is not in the persistent store, the target is NULL. For conditional expressions containing NULL, the query language uses the semantics defined by SQL92. Briefly, these semantics are as follows.

If a comparison or arithmetic operation has an unknown value, it yields a NULL value.

Two NULL values are not equal. Comparing two NULL values yields an unknown value.

The IS NULL test converts a NULL persistent field or a single-valued relationship field to TRUE. The IS NOT NULL test converts them to FALSE.

Boolean operators and conditional tests use the three-valued logic defined by Table 39-7 and Table 39-8. (In these tables, T stands for TRUE, F for FALSE, and U for unknown.)

Table 39-7 AND Operator Logic

AND | T | F | U

T

|

T

|

F

|

U

F

|

F

|

F

|

F

U

|

U

|

F

|

U

Table 39-8 OR Operator Logic

OR | T | F | U

T

|

T

|

T

|

T

F

|

T

|

F

|

U

U

|

T

|

U

|

U

39.5.5.15 Equality Semantics

In the query language, only values of the same type can be compared. However, this rule has one exception: Exact and approximate numeric values can be compared. In such a comparison, the required type conversion adheres to the rules of Java numeric promotion.

The query language treats compared values as if they were Java types and not as if they represented types in the underlying data store. For example, a persistent field that could be either an integer or a NULL must be designated as an Integer object and not as an int primitive. This designation is required because a Java object can be NULL, but a primitive cannot.

Two strings are equal only if they contain the same sequence of characters. Trailing blanks are significant; for example, the strings 'abc' and 'abc ' are not equal.

Two entities of the same abstract schema type are equal only if their primary keys have the same value. Table 39-9 shows the operator logic of a negation, and Table 39-10 shows the truth values of conditional tests.

Table 39-9 NOT Operator Logic

NOT Value | Value

T

|

F

F

|

T

U

|

U

Table 39-10 Conditional Test

Conditional Test | T | F | U

Expression IS TRUE

|

T

|

F

|

F

Expression IS FALSE

|

F

|

T

|

F

Expression is unknown

|

F

|

F

|

T

39.5.6 SELECT Clause

The SELECT clause defines the types of the objects or values returned by the query.

39.5.6.1 Return Types

The return type of the SELECT clause is defined by the result types of the select expressions contained within it. If multiple expressions are used, the result of the query is an Object[], and the elements in the array correspond to the order of the expressions in the SELECT clause and in type to the result types of each expression.

A SELECT clause cannot specify a collection-valued expression. For example, the SELECT clause p.teams is invalid because teams is a collection. However, the clause in the following query is valid because t is a single element of the teams collection:

SELECT t
FROM Player p, IN (p.teams) t

The following query is an example of a query with multiple expressions in the SELECT clause:

SELECT c.name, c.country.name
FROM customer c
WHERE c.lastname = 'Coss' AND c.firstname = 'Roxane'

This query returns a list of Object[] elements; the first array element is a string denoting the customer name, and the second array element is a string denoting the name of the customer's country.

The result of a query may be the result of an aggregate function, listed in Table 39-11.

Table 39-11 Aggregate Functions in Select Statements

Name | Return Type | Description

AVG

|

Double

|

Returns the mean average of the fields

COUNT

|

Long

|

Returns the total number of results

MAX

|

The type of the field

|

Returns the highest value in the result set

MIN

|

The type of the field

|

Returns the lowest value in the result set

SUM

|

Long (for integral fields)

Double (for floating-point fields)

BigInteger (for BigInteger fields)

BigDecimal (for BigDecimal fields)

|

Returns the sum of all the values in the result set

For select method queries with an aggregate function (AVG, COUNT, MAX, MIN, or SUM) in the SELECT clause, the following rules apply.

The AVG, MAX, MIN, and SUM functions return null if there are no values to which the function can be applied.

The COUNT function returns 0 if there are no values to which the function can be applied.

The following example returns the average order quantity:

SELECT AVG(o.quantity)
FROM CustomerOrder o

The following example returns the total cost of the items ordered by Roxane Coss:

SELECT SUM(l.price)
FROM CustomerOrder o JOIN o.lineItems l JOIN o.customer c
WHERE c.lastname = 'Coss' AND c.firstname = 'Roxane'

The following example returns the total number of orders:

SELECT COUNT(o)
FROM CustomerOrder o

The following example returns the total number of items that have prices in Hal Incandenza's order:

SELECT COUNT(l.price)
FROM CustomerOrder o JOIN o.lineItems l JOIN o.customer c
WHERE c.lastname = 'Incandenza' AND c.firstname = 'Hal'

39.5.6.2 The DISTINCT Keyword

The DISTINCT keyword eliminates duplicate return values. If a query returns a java.util.Collection, which allows duplicates, you must specify the DISTINCT keyword to eliminate duplicates.

39.5.6.3 Constructor Expressions

Constructor expressions allow you to return Java instances that store a query result element instead of an Object[].

The following query creates a CustomerDetail instance per Customer matching the WHERE clause. A CustomerDetail stores the customer name and customer's country name. So the query returns a List of CustomerDetail instances:

SELECT NEW com.example.CustomerDetail(c.name, c.country.name)
FROM customer c
WHERE c.lastname = 'Coss' AND c.firstname = 'Roxane'

39.5.7 ORDER BY Clause

As its name suggests, the ORDER BY clause orders the values or objects returned by the query.

If the ORDER BY clause contains multiple elements, the left-to-right sequence of the elements determines the high-to-low precedence.

The ASC keyword specifies ascending order, the default, and the DESC keyword indicates descending order.

When using the ORDER BY clause, the SELECT clause must return an orderable set of objects or values. You cannot order the values or objects for values or objects not returned by the SELECT clause. For example, the following query is valid because the ORDER BY clause uses the objects returned by the SELECT clause:

SELECT o
FROM Customer c JOIN c.orders o JOIN c.address a
WHERE a.state = 'CA'
ORDER BY o.quantity, o.totalcost

The following example is not valid, because the ORDER BY clause uses a value not returned by the SELECT clause:

SELECT p.product_name
FROM CustomerOrder o, IN(o.lineItems) l JOIN o.customer c
WHERE c.lastname = 'Faehmel' AND c.firstname = 'Robert'
ORDER BY o.quantity

39.5.8 GROUP BY and HAVING Clauses

The GROUP BY clause allows you to group values according to a set of properties.

The following query groups the customers by their country and returns the number of customers per country:

SELECT c.country, COUNT(c)
FROM Customer c GROUP BY c.country

The HAVING clause is used with the GROUP BY clause to further restrict the returned result of a query.

The following query groups orders by the status of their customer and returns the customer status plus the average totalPrice for all orders where the corresponding customers have the same status. In addition, it considers only customers with status 1, 2, or 3, so orders of other customers are not taken into account:

SELECT c.status, AVG(o.totalPrice)
FROM CustomerOrder o JOIN o.customer c
GROUP BY c.status HAVING c.status IN (1, 2, 3)

3 Resource Creation

A resource is a program object that provides connections to such systems as database servers and messaging systems. Java EE components can access a wide variety of resources, including databases, mail sessions, Java Message Service objects, and URLs. The Java EE 7 platform provides mechanisms that allow you to access all these resources in a similar manner. This chapter examines several types of resources and explains how to create them.

The following topics are addressed here:

Resources and JNDI Naming

DataSource Objects and Connection Pools

Creating Resources Administratively

3.1 Resources and JNDI Naming

In a distributed application, components need to access other components and resources, such as databases. For example, a servlet might invoke remote methods on an enterprise bean that retrieves information from a database. In the Java EE platform, the Java Naming and Directory Interface (JNDI) naming service enables components to locate other components and resources.

A resource is a program object that provides connections to systems, such as database servers and messaging systems. (A Java Database Connectivity resource is sometimes referred to as a data source.) Each resource object is identified by a unique, people-friendly name, called the JNDI name. For example, the JNDI name of the preconfigured JDBC resource for the Java DB database that is shipped with GlassFish Server is java:comp/DefaultDataSource.

An administrator creates resources in a JNDI namespace. In GlassFish Server, you can use either the Administration Console or the asadmin command to create resources. Applications then use annotations to inject the resources. If an application uses resource injection, GlassFish Server invokes the JNDI API, and the application is not required to do so. However, it is also possible for an application to locate resources by making direct calls to the JNDI API.

A resource object and its JNDI name are bound together by the naming and directory service. To create a new resource, a new name/object binding is entered into the JNDI namespace. You inject resources by using the @Resource annotation in an application.

You can use a deployment descriptor to override the resource mapping that you specify in an annotation. Using a deployment descriptor allows you to change an application by repackaging it rather than by both recompiling the source files and repackaging. However, for most applications a deployment descriptor is not necessary.

3.2 DataSource Objects and Connection Pools

To store, organize, and retrieve data, most applications use a relational database. Java EE 7 components may access relational databases through the JDBC API. For information on this API, see http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/technotes/guides/jdbc/.

In the JDBC API, databases are accessed by using DataSource objects. A DataSource has a set of properties that identify and describe the real-world data source that it represents. These properties include such information as the location of the database server, the name of the database, the network protocol to use to communicate with the server, and so on. In GlassFish Server, a data source is called a JDBC resource.

Applications access a data source by using a connection, and a DataSource object can be thought of as a factory for connections to the particular data source that the DataSource instance represents. In a basic DataSource implementation, a call to the getConnection method returns a connection object that is a physical connection to the data source.

A DataSource object may be registered with a JNDI naming service. If so, an application can use the JNDI API to access that DataSource object, which can then be used to connect to the data source it represents.

DataSource objects that implement connection pooling also produce a connection to the particular data source that the DataSource class represents. The connection object that the getConnection method returns is a handle to a PooledConnection object rather than a physical connection. An application uses the connection object in the same way that it uses a connection. Connection pooling has no effect on application code except that a pooled connection, like all connections, should always be explicitly closed. When an application closes a connection that is pooled, the connection is returned to a pool of reusable connections. The next time getConnection is called, a handle to one of these pooled connections will be returned if one is available. Because connection pooling avoids creating a new physical connection every time one is requested, applications can run significantly faster.

A JDBC connection pool is a group of reusable connections for a particular database. Because creating each new physical connection is time consuming, the server maintains a pool of available connections to increase performance. When it requests a connection, an application obtains one from the pool. When an application closes a connection, the connection is returned to the pool.

Applications that use the Persistence API specify the DataSource object they are using in the jta-data-source element of the persistence.xml file:

<jta-data-source>jdbc/MyOrderDB</jta-data-source>

This is typically the only reference to a JDBC object for a persistence unit. The application code does not refer to any JDBC objects.

3.3 Creating Resources Administratively

Before you deploy or run many applications, you may need to create resources for them. An application can include a glassfish-resources.xml file that can be used to define resources for that application and others. You can then use the asadmin command, specifying as the argument a file named glassfish-resources.xml, to create the resources administratively, as shown.

asadmin add-resources glassfish-resources.xml

The glassfish-resources.xml file can be created in any project using NetBeans IDE or by hand. Some of the JMS examples use this approach to resource creation. A file for creating the resources needed for the JMS simple producer example can be found in the jms/simple/producer/src/main/setup directory.

You could also use the asadmin create-jms-resource command to create the resources for this example. When you are done using the resources, you would use the asadmin list-jms-resources command to display their names, and the asadmin delete-jms-resource command to remove them, regardless of the way you created the resources.

52 Resource Adapters and Contracts

This chapter examines resource adapters and explains how communications between Java EE servers and EIS systems are mediated by them.

The following topics are addressed here:

What Is a Resource Adapter?

Metadata Annotations

Common Client Interface

Using Resource Adapters with Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE (CDI)

Further Information about Resource Adapters

52.1 What Is a Resource Adapter?

A resource adapter is a Java EE component that implements the Java EE Connector Architecture for a specific EIS. Examples of EISs include enterprise resource planning, mainframe transaction processing, and database systems. In a Java EE server, the Java Message Server and JavaMail also act as EISs that you access using resource adapters. As illustrated in Figure 52-1, the resource adapter facilitates communication between a Java EE application and an EIS.

Figure 52-1 Resource Adapters

Description of "Figure 52-1 Resource Adapters"

Stored in a Resource Adapter Archive (RAR) file, a resource adapter can be deployed on any Java EE server, much like a Java EE application. A RAR file may be contained in an Enterprise Archive (EAR) file, or it may exist as a separate file.

A resource adapter is analogous to a JDBC driver. Both provide a standard API through which an application can access a resource that is outside the Java EE server. For a resource adapter, the target system is an EIS; for a JDBC driver, it is a DBMS. Resource adapters and JDBC drivers are rarely created by application developers. In most cases, both types of software are built by vendors that sell tools, servers, or integration software.

The resource adapter mediates communication between the Java EE server and the EIS by means of contracts. The application contract defines the API through which a Java EE component, such as an enterprise bean, accesses the EIS. This API is the only view that the component has of the EIS. The system contracts link the resource adapter to important services that are managed by the Java EE server. The resource adapter itself and its system contracts are transparent to the Java EE component.

52.1.1 Management Contracts

The Java EE Connector Architecture defines system contracts that enable resource adapter lifecycle and thread management.

52.1.1.1 Lifecycle Management

The Connector Architecture specifies a lifecycle management contract that allows an application server to manage the lifecycle of a resource adapter. This contract provides a mechanism for the application server to bootstrap a resource adapter instance during the deployment or application server startup. This contract also provides a means for the application server to notify the resource adapter instance when it is undeployed or when an orderly shutdown of the application server takes place.

52.1.1.2 Work Management Contract

The Connector Architecture work management contract ensures that resource adapters use threads in the proper, recommended manner. This contract also enables an application server to manage threads for resource adapters.

Resource adapters that improperly use threads can jeopardize the entire application server environment. For example, a resource adapter might create too many threads or might not properly release threads it has created. Poor thread handling inhibits application server shutdown and impacts the application server's performance because creating and destroying threads are expensive operations.

The work management contract establishes a means for the application server to pool and reuse threads, similar to pooling and reusing connections. By adhering to this contract, the resource adapter does not have to manage threads itself. Instead, the resource adapter has the application server create and provide needed threads. When it is finished with a given thread, the resource adapter returns the thread to the application server. The application server manages the thread, either returning it to a pool for later reuse or destroying it. Handling threads in this manner results in increased application server performance and more efficient use of resources.

In addition to moving thread management to the application server, the Connector Architecture provides a flexible model for a resource adapter that uses threads.

The requesting thread can choose to block (stop its own execution) until the work thread completes.

The requesting thread can block while it waits to get the work thread. When the application server provides a work thread, the requesting thread and the work thread execute in parallel.

The resource adapter can opt to submit the work for the thread to a queue. The thread executes the work from the queue at some later point. The resource adapter continues its own execution from the point it submitted the work to the queue, no matter when the thread executes it.

With the latter two approaches, the submitting thread and the work thread may execute simultaneously or independently. For these approaches, the contract specifies a listener mechanism to notify the resource adapter that the thread has completed its operation. The resource adapter can also specify the execution context for the thread, and the work management contract controls the context in which the thread executes.

52.1.2 Generic Work Context Contract

The work management contract between the application server and a resource adapter enables a resource adapter to do a task, such as communicating with the EIS or delivering messages, by delivering Work instances for execution.

A generic work context contract enables a resource adapter to control the contexts in which the Work instances that it submits are executed by the application server's WorkManager. A generic work context mechanism also enables an application server to support message inflow and delivery schemes. It also provides a richer contextual Work execution environment to the resource adapter while still maintaining control over concurrent behavior in a managed environment.

The generic work context contract standardizes the transaction context and the security context.

52.1.3 Outbound and Inbound Contracts

The Connector Architecture defines the following outbound contracts, system-level contracts between an application server and an EIS that enable outbound connectivity to an EIS.

The connection management contract supports connection pooling, a technique that enhances application performance and scalability. Connection pooling is transparent to the application, which simply obtains a connection to the EIS.

The transaction management contract extends the connection management contract and provides support for management of both local and XA transactions.

A local transaction is limited in scope to a single EIS system, and the EIS resource manager itself manages such a transaction. An XA transaction or global transaction can span multiple resource managers. This form of transaction requires transaction coordination by an external transaction manager, typically bundled with an application server. A transaction manager uses a two-phase commit protocol to manage a transaction that spans multiple resource managers or EISs, and uses one-phase commit optimization if only one resource manager is participating in an XA transaction.

The security management contract provides mechanisms for authentication, authorization, and secure communication between a Java EE server and an EIS to protect the information in the EIS.

A work security map matches EIS identities to the application server domain's identities.

Inbound contracts are system contracts between a Java EE server and an EIS that enable inbound connectivity from the EIS: pluggability contracts for message providers and contracts for importing transactions.

52.2 Metadata Annotations

Java EE Connector Architecture provides a set of annotations to minimize the need for deployment descriptors.

The @Connector annotation can be used by the resource adapter developer to specify that the JavaBeans component is a resource adapter JavaBeans component. This annotation is used for providing metadata about the capabilities of the resource adapter. Optionally, you can provide a JavaBeans component implementing the ResourceAdapter interface, as in the following example:

@Connector(
    displayName = "TrafficResourceAdapter",
    vendorName = "Java EE Tutorial", 
    version = "7.0"
)
public class TrafficResourceAdapter implements ResourceAdapter, 
                                               Serializable {
    ...
}

The @ConnectionDefinition annotation defines a set of connection interfaces and classes pertaining to a particular connection type, as in the following example:

@ConnectionDefinition(
    connectionFactory = ConnectionFactory.class,
    connectionFactoryImpl = TradeConnectionFactory.class,
    connection = Connection.class,
    connectionImpl = TradeConnection.class
)
public class TradeManagedConnectionFactory ... {
    ...
}

The @AdministeredObject annotation designates a JavaBeans component as an administered object.

The @Activation annotation contains configuration information pertaining to inbound connectivity from an EIS instance, as in the following example:

@Activation(
        messageListeners = { TrafficListener.class }
)
public class TrafficActivationSpec implements ActivationSpec, 
                                              Serializable {
    ...
    @ConfigProperty()
    /* port to listen to requests from the EIS */
    private String port;
    ...
}

The @ConfigProperty annotation can be used on JavaBeans components to provide additional configuration information that may be used by the deployer and resource adapter provider. The preceding example code shows several @ConfigProperty annotations.

The @ConnectionFactoryDefinition annotation is a resource definition annotation that is used to define a connector connection factory and register it in JNDI under the name specified in the mandatory name annotation element. The mandatory interfaceName annotation element specifies the fully qualified name of the connection factory interface class. The transactionSupport annotation element specifies the level of transaction support the connection factory needs to support. The minPoolSize and maxPoolSize annotation elements specify the minimum or maximum number of connections that should be allocated for a connection pool that backs this connection factory resource. Additional properties associated with the connection factory being defined can be specified through the properties element.

Since repeated annotations are not allowed, the @ConnectionFactoryDefinitions annotation acts as a container for multiple connector connection factory definitions. The value annotation element contains the multiple connector connection factory definitions.

The @AdministeredObjectDefinition annotation is a resource definition annotation that is used to define an administered object and register it in JNDI under the name specified in the mandatory name annotation element. The mandatory fully qualified name of the administered object's class must be indicated by the className element. Additional properties that must be configured in the administered object can be specified through the properties element.

Since repeated annotations are not allowed, the @AdministeredObjectDefinitions annotation acts as a container for multiple administered object definitions. The value annotation element contains the multiple administered object definitions.

The specification allows a resource adapter to be developed in mixed-mode form, that is the ability for a resource adapter developer to use both metadata annotations and deployment descriptors in applications. An application assembler or deployer may use the deployment descriptor to override the metadata annotations specified by the resource adapter developer.

The deployment descriptor for a resource adapter, if present, is named ra.xml. The metadata-complete attribute defines whether the deployment descriptor for the resource adapter module is complete or whether the class files available to the module and packaged with the resource adapter need to be examined for annotations that specify deployment information.

For the complete list of annotations and JavaBeans components provided in the Java EE 7 platform, see the Java EE Connector Architecture 1.7 specification.

52.3 Common Client Interface

This section explains how components use the Connector Architecture Common Client Interface (CCI) API and a resource adapter to access data from an EIS. The CCI API defines a set of interfaces and classes whose methods allow a client to perform typical data access operations. The CCI interfaces and classes are as follows.

ConnectionFactory: Provides an application component with a Connection instance to an EIS.

Connection: Represents the connection to the underlying EIS.

ConnectionSpec: Provides a means for an application component to pass connection-request-specific properties to the ConnectionFactory when making a connection request.

Interaction: Provides a means for an application component to execute EIS functions, such as database stored procedures.

InteractionSpec: Holds properties pertaining to an application component's interaction with an EIS.

Record: The superinterface for the various kinds of record instances. Record instances can be MappedRecord, IndexedRecord, or ResultSet instances, all of which inherit from the Record interface.

RecordFactory: Provides an application component with a Record instance.

IndexedRecord: Represents an ordered collection of Record instances based on the java.util.List interface.

A client or application component that uses the CCI to interact with an underlying EIS does so in a prescribed manner. The component must establish a connection to the EIS's resource manager, and it does so using the ConnectionFactory. The Connection object represents the connection to the EIS and is used for subsequent interactions with the EIS.

The component performs its interactions with the EIS, such as accessing data from a specific table, using an Interaction object. The application component defines the Interaction object by using an InteractionSpec object. When it reads data from the EIS, such as from database tables, or writes to those tables, the application component does so by using a particular type of Record instance: a MappedRecord, an IndexedRecord, or a ResultSet instance.

Note, too, that a client application that relies on a CCI resource adapter is very much like any other Java EE client that uses enterprise bean methods.

52.4 Using Resource Adapters with Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE (CDI)

For details about CDI, see Chapter 23, "Introduction to Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE" and Chapter 25, "Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE: Advanced Topics."

Do not specify the following classes in the resource adapter as CDI managed beans (that is, do not inject them), because the behavior of these classes as CDI managed beans has not been portably defined.

Resource adapter beans: These beans are classes that are annotated with the javax.resource.spi.Connector annotation or are declared as corresponding elements in the resource adapter deployment descriptor, ra.xml.

Managed connection factory beans: These beans are classes that are annotated with the javax.resource.spi.ConnectorDefinition annotation or the javax.resource.spi.ConnectorDefinitions annotation or are declared as corresponding elements in ra.xml.

Activation specification beans: These beans are classes that are annotated with the javax.resource.spi.Activation annotation or are declared as corresponding elements in ra.xml.

Administered object beans: These beans are classes that are annotated with the javax.resource.spi.AdministeredObject annotation or are declared as corresponding elements in ra.xml.

Other types of classes in the resource adapter can be CDI managed beans and will behave in a portable manner.

52.5 Further Information about Resource Adapters

For more information about resource adapters and annotations, see

Java EE 7 Platform Specification (JSR 342):

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=342

Java EE Connector Architecture 1.7 specification:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=322

EJB 3.2 specification:

http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=345

Common Annotations for the Java Platform:

http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=250

50 Java EE Security: Advanced Topics

This chapter provides advanced information on securing Java EE applications.

The following topics are addressed here:

Working with Digital Certificates

Authentication Mechanisms

Using the JDBC Realm for User Authentication

Securing HTTP Resources

Securing Application Clients

Securing Enterprise Information Systems Applications

Configuring Security Using Deployment Descriptors

Further Information about Advanced Security Topics

50.1 Working with Digital Certificates

Digital certificates for GlassFish Server have already been generated and can be found in the directory domain-dir/config/. These digital certificates are self-signed and are intended for use in a development environment; they are not intended for production purposes. For production purposes, generate your own certificates and have them signed by a Certificate Authority (CA).

To use the Secure Sockets Layer (SSL), an application or web server must have an associated certificate for each external interface, or IP address, that accepts secure connections. The theory behind this design is that a server should provide some kind of reasonable assurance that its owner is who you think it is, particularly before receiving any sensitive information. It may be useful to think of a certificate as a "digital driver's license" for an Internet address. The certificate states with which company the site is associated, along with some basic contact information about the site owner or administrator.

The digital certificate is cryptographically signed by its owner and is difficult for anyone else to forge. For sites involved in e-commerce or in any other business transaction in which authentication of identity is important, a certificate can be purchased from a well-known CA such as VeriSign or Thawte. If your server certificate is self-signed, you must install it in the GlassFish Server keystore file (keystore.jks). If your client certificate is self-signed, you should install it in the GlassFish Server truststore file (cacerts.jks).

Sometimes, authentication is not really a concern. For example, an administrator might simply want to ensure that data being transmitted and received by the server is private and cannot be snooped by anyone eavesdropping on the connection. In such cases, you can save the time and expense involved in obtaining a CA certificate and simply use a self-signed certificate.

SSL uses public-key cryptography, which is based on key pairs. Key pairs contain one public key and one private key. Data encrypted with one key can be decrypted only with the other key of the pair. This property is fundamental to establishing trust and privacy in transactions. For example, using SSL, the server computes a value and encrypts it by using its private key. The encrypted value is called a digital signature. The client decrypts the encrypted value by using the server's public key and compares the value to its own computed value. If the two values match, the client can trust that the signature is authentic, because only the private key could have been used to produce such a signature.

Digital certificates are used with HTTPS to authenticate web clients. The HTTPS service of most web servers will not run unless a digital certificate has been installed. Use the procedure outlined in the next section, Creating a Server Certificate, to set up a digital certificate that can be used by your application or web server to enable SSL.

One tool that can be used to set up a digital certificate is keytool, a key and certificate management utility that ships with the JDK. This tool enables users to administer their own public/private key pairs and associated certificates for use in self-authentication, whereby the user authenticates himself or herself to other users or services, or data integrity and authentication services, using digital signatures. The tool also allows users to cache the public keys, in the form of certificates, of their communicating peers.

For a better understanding of keytool and public-key cryptography, see Further Information about Advanced Security Topics for a link to the keytool documentation.

50.1.1 Creating a Server Certificate

A server certificate has already been created for GlassFish Server and can be found in the domain-dir/config/ directory. The server certificate is in keystore.jks. The cacerts.jks file contains all the trusted certificates, including client certificates.

If necessary, you can use keytool to generate certificates. The keytool utility stores the keys and certificates in a file termed a keystore, a repository of certificates used for identifying a client or a server. Typically, a keystore is a file that contains one client's or one server's identity. The keystore protects private keys by using a password.

If you don't specify a directory when specifying the keystore file name, the keystores are created in the directory from which the keytool command is run. This can be the directory where the application resides, or it can be a directory common to many applications.

The general steps for creating a server certificate are as follows.

Create the keystore.

Export the certificate from the keystore.

Sign the certificate.

Import the certificate into a truststore: a repository of certificates used for verifying the certificates. A truststore typically contains more than one certificate.

The next section provides specific information on using the keytool utility to perform these steps.

50.1.1.1 To Use keytool to Create a Server Certificate

Run keytool to generate a new key pair in the default development keystore file, keystore.jks. This example uses the alias server-alias to generate a new public/private key pair and wrap the public key into a self-signed certificate inside keystore.jks. The key pair is generated by using an algorithm of type RSA, with a default password of changeit. For more information and other examples of creating and managing keystore files, read the keytool documentation.

Note:

RSA is public-key encryption technology developed by RSA Data Security, Inc.

From the directory in which you want to create the key pair, run keytool as shown in the following steps.

Generate the server certificate.

Enter the keytool command all on one line:

java-home/bin/keytool -genkey -alias server-alias -keyalg RSA 
-keypass changeit -storepass changeit -keystore keystore.jks

When you press Enter, keytool prompts you to enter the server name, organizational unit, organization, locality, state, and country code.

You must enter the server name in response to keytool's first prompt, in which it asks for first and last names. For testing purposes, this can be localhost.

Export the generated server certificate in keystore.jks into the file server.cer.

Enter the keytool command all on one line:

java-home/bin/keytool -export -alias server-alias -storepass changeit 
-file server.cer -keystore keystore.jks

If you want to have the certificate signed by a CA, read the example in the keytool documentation.

To add the server certificate to the truststore file, cacerts.jks, run keytool from the directory where you created the keystore and server certificate.

Use the following parameters:

java-home/bin/keytool -import -v -trustcacerts -alias server-alias 
-file server.cer -keystore cacerts.jks -keypass changeit 
-storepass changeit 

Information on the certificate, such as that shown next, will appear:

Owner: CN=localhost, OU=My Company, O=Software, L=Santa Clara, ST=CA, C=US
Issuer: CN=localhost, OU=My Company, O=Software, L=Santa Clara, ST=CA, C=US
Serial number: 3e932169 
Valid from: Mon Nov 26 18:15:47 EST 2012 until: Sun Feb 24 18:15:47 EST 2013
Certificate fingerprints:
         MD5: 52:9F:49:68:ED:78:6F:39:87:F3:98:B3:6A:6B:0F:90
         SHA1: EE:2E:2A:A6:9E:03:9A:3A:1C:17:4A:28:5E:97:20:78:3F:
         SHA256: 80:05:EC:7E:50:50:5D:AA:A3:53:F1:11:9B:19:EB:0D:20:67:C1:12:
AF:42:EC:CD:66:8C:BD:99:AD:D9:76:95
         Signature algorithm name: SHA256withRSA         Version: 3
         ...
Trust this certificate? [no]:

Enter yes, then press the Enter or Return key.

The following information appears:

Certificate was added to keystore
[Storing cacerts.jks]

50.1.2 Adding Users to the Certificate Realm

In the certificate realm, user identity is set up in the GlassFish Server security context and populated with user data obtained from cryptographically verified client certificates. For step-by-step instructions for creating this type of certificate, see Working with Digital Certificates.

50.1.3 Using a Different Server Certificate with GlassFish Server

Follow the steps in Creating a Server Certificate to create your own server certificate, have it signed by a CA, and import the certificate into keystore.jks.

Make sure that when you create the certificate, you follow these rules.

When you create the server certificate, keytool prompts you to enter your first and last name. In response to this prompt, you must enter the name of your server. For testing purposes, this can be localhost.

If you want to replace the existing keystore.jks, you must either change your keystore's password to the default password (changeit) or change the default password to your keystore's password.

50.1.3.1 To Specify a Different Server Certificate

To specify that GlassFish Server should use the new keystore for authentication and authorization decisions, you must set the JVM options for GlassFish Server so that they recognize the new keystore. To use a different keystore from the one provided for development purposes, follow these steps.

Start GlassFish Server if you haven't already done so. Information on starting the GlassFish Server can be found in Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server.

Open the GlassFish Server Administration Console in a web browser at http://localhost:4848.

Expand Configurations, then expand server-config, then click JVM Settings.

Click the JVM Options tab.

Change the following JVM options so that they point to the location and name of the new keystore. The current settings are shown below:

-Djavax.net.ssl.keyStore=${com.sun.aas.instanceRoot}/config/keystore.jks
-Djavax.net.ssl.trustStore=${com.sun.aas.instanceRoot}/config/cacerts.jks

If you've changed the keystore password from its default value, you need to add the password option as well:

-Djavax.net.ssl.keyStorePassword=your-new-password 

Click Save, then restart GlassFish Server.

50.2 Authentication Mechanisms

This section discusses the client authentication and mutual authentication mechanisms.

50.2.1 Client Authentication

With client authentication, the web server authenticates the client by using the client's public key certificate. Client authentication is a more secure method of authentication than either basic or form-based authentication. It uses HTTP over SSL (HTTPS), in which the server authenticates the client using the client's public key certificate. SSL technology provides data encryption, server authentication, message integrity, and optional client authentication for a TCP/IP connection. You can think of a public key certificate as the digital equivalent of a passport. The certificate is issued by a trusted organization, a certificate authority (CA), and provides identification for the bearer.

Before using client authentication, make sure that the client has a valid public key certificate. For more information on creating and using public key certificates, read Working with Digital Certificates.

The following example shows how to declare client authentication in your deployment descriptor:

<login-config>
    <auth-method>CLIENT-CERT</auth-method>
</login-config>

50.2.2 Mutual Authentication

With mutual authentication, the server and the client authenticate each other. Mutual authentication is of two types:

Certificate-based (see Figure 50-1)

User name/password-based (see Figure 50-2)

When using certificate-based mutual authentication, the following actions occur.

A client requests access to a protected resource.

The web server presents its certificate to the client.

The client verifies the server's certificate.

If successful, the client sends its certificate to the server.

The server verifies the client's credentials.

If successful, the server grants access to the protected resource requested by the client.

Figure 50-1 shows what occurs during certificate-based mutual authentication.

Figure 50-1 Certificate-Based Mutual Authentication

Description of "Figure 50-1 Certificate-Based Mutual Authentication"

In user name/password-based mutual authentication, the following actions occur.

A client requests access to a protected resource.

The web server presents its certificate to the client.

The client verifies the server's certificate.

If successful, the client sends its user name and password to the server.

The server verifies the client's credentials

If the verification is successful, the server grants access to the protected resource requested by the client.

Figure 50-2 shows what occurs during user name/password-based mutual authentication.

Figure 50-2 User Name/Password-Based Mutual Authentication

Description of "Figure 50-2 User Name/Password-Based Mutual Authentication"

50.2.2.1 Enabling Mutual Authentication over SSL

This section discusses setting up client-side authentication. Enabling both server-side and client-side authentication is called mutual, or two-way, authentication. In client authentication, clients are required to submit certificates issued by a certificate authority that you choose to accept.

There are at least two ways to enable mutual authentication over SSL.

The preferred method is to set the method of authentication in the web.xml application deployment descriptor to CLIENT-CERT. This enforces mutual authentication by modifying the deployment descriptor of the given application. In this way, client authentication is enabled only for a specific resource controlled by the security constraint, and the check is performed only when the application requires client authentication.

A less commonly used method is to set the clientAuth property in the certificate realm to true if you want the SSL stack to require a valid certificate chain from the client before accepting a connection. A false value (which is the default) will not require a certificate chain unless the client requests a resource protected by a security constraint that uses CLIENT-CERT authentication. When you enable client authentication by setting the clientAuth property to true, client authentication will be required for all the requests going through the specified SSL port. If you turn clientAuth on, it is on all of the time, which can severely degrade performance.

When client authentication is enabled in both of these ways, client authentication will be performed twice.

50.2.2.2 Creating a Client Certificate for Mutual Authentication

If you have a certificate signed by a trusted Certificate Authority (CA) such as Verisign, and the GlassFish Server cacerts.jks file already contains a certificate verified by that CA, you do not need to complete this step. You need to install your certificate in the GlassFish Server certificate file only when your certificate is self-signed.

From the directory where you want to create the client certificate, run keytool as outlined here. When you press Enter, keytool prompts you to enter the server name, organizational unit, organization, locality, state, and country code.

You must enter the server name in response to keytool's first prompt, in which it asks for first and last names. For testing purposes, this can be localhost. If this example is to verify mutual authentication and you receive a runtime error stating that the HTTPS host name is wrong, re-create the client certificate, being sure to use the same host name you will use when running the example. For example, if your machine name is duke, then enter duke as the certificate CN or when prompted for first and last names. When accessing the application, enter a URL that points to the same location (for example, https://duke:8181/mutualauth/hello). This is necessary because during SSL handshake, the server verifies the client certificate by comparing the certificate name to the host name from which it originates.

To create a keystore named client_keystore.jks that contains a client certificate named client.cer, follow these steps.

Create a backup copy of the server truststore file. To do this,

Change to the directory containing the server's keystore and truststore files, domain-dir\config.

Copy cacerts.jks to cacerts.backup.jks.

Copy keystore.jks to keystore.backup.jks.

Do not put client certificates in the cacerts.jks file. Any certificate you add to the cacerts file effectively can be a trusted root for any and all certificate chains. After you have completed development, delete the development version of the cacerts file and replace it with the original copy.

Generate the client certificate. Enter the following command from the directory where you want to generate the client certificate:

java-home\bin\keytool -genkey -alias client-alias -keyalg RSA 
-keypass changeit -storepass changeit -keystore client_keystore.jks

Export the generated client certificate into the file client.cer:

java-home\bin\keytool -export -alias client-alias -storepass changeit 
-file client.cer -keystore client_keystore.jks

Add the certificate to the truststore file domain-dir/config/cacerts.jks. Run keytool from the directory where you created the keystore and client certificate. Use the following parameters:

java-home\bin\keytool -import -v -trustcacerts -alias client-alias 
-file client.cer -keystore domain-dir/config/cacerts.jks 
-keypass changeit -storepass changeit

The keytool utility returns a message like this one:

Owner: CN=localhost, OU=My Company, O=Software, L=Santa Clara, ST=CA, C=US
Issuer: CN=localhost, OU=My Company, O=Software, L=Santa Clara, ST=CA, C=US
Serial number: 3e39e66a
Valid from: Tue Nov 27 12:22:47 EST 2012 until: Mon Feb 25 12:22:47 EST 2013
Certificate fingerprints:
    MD5: 5A:B0:4C:88:4E:F8:EF:E9:E5:8B:53:BD:D0:AA:8E:5A
    SHA1:90:00:36:5B:E0:A7:A2:BD:67:DB:EA:37:B9:61:3E:26:B3:89:46:32
    Signature algorithm name: SHA1withRSA
    Version: 3
Trust this certificate? [no]: yes
Certificate was added to keystore
[Storing cacerts.jks]

Restart GlassFish Server.

50.3 Using the JDBC Realm for User Authentication

An authentication realm, sometimes called a security policy domain or security domain, is a scope over which an application server defines and enforces a common security policy. A realm contains a collection of users, who may or may not be assigned to a group. GlassFish Server comes preconfigured with the file, certificate, and administration realms. An administrator can also set up LDAP, JDBC, digest, or custom realms.

An application can specify in its deployment descriptor which realm to use. If the application does not specify a realm, GlassFish Server uses its default realm, the file realm. If an application specifies that a JDBC realm is to be used for user authentication, GlassFish Server will retrieve user credentials from a database. The application server uses the database information and the enabled JDBC realm option in the configuration file.

A database provides an easy way to add, edit, or delete users at runtime and enables users to create their own accounts without any administrative assistance. Using a database has an additional benefit: providing a place to securely store any extra user information. A realm can be thought of as a database of user names and passwords that identify valid users of a web application or set of web applications with an enumeration of the list of roles associated with each valid user. Access to specific web application resources is granted to all users in a particular role, instead of enumerating a list of associated users. A user name can have any number of roles associated with it.

Two of the tutorial case studies, Chapter 58, "Duke's Tutoring Case Study Example," and Chapter 59, "Duke's Forest Case Study Example," use a JDBC realm for user authentication.

50.3.1 To Configure a JDBC Authentication Realm

GlassFish Server enables administrators to specify a user's credentials (user name and password) in the JDBC realm instead of in the connection pool. This prevents other applications from browsing the database tables for user credentials. By default, storing passwords as clear text is not supported in the JDBC realm. Under normal circumstances, passwords should not be stored as clear text.

Create the database tables in which user credentials for the realm will be stored.

Add user credentials to the database tables you created.

Create a JDBC connection pool for the database.

You can use the Administration Console or the command line to create a connection pool.

Create a JDBC resource for the database.

You can use the Administration Console or the command line to create a JDBC resource.

Create a realm.

This step needs to associate the resource with the realm, define the tables and columns for users and groups used for authentication, and define the digest algorithm that will be used for storing passwords in the database.

You can use the Administration Console or the command line to create a realm.

Modify the deployment descriptor for your application to specify the JDBC realm.

For an enterprise application in an EAR file, modify the glassfish-application.xml file.

For a web application in a WAR file, modify the web.xml file.

For an enterprise bean in an EJB JAR file, modify the glassfish-ejb-jar.xml file.

For example, for a hypothetical application, the web.xml file could specify the jdbcRealm realm, as follows:

<login-config>
    <auth-method>FORM</auth-method>
    <realm-name>jdbcRealm</realm-name>
    <form-login-config>
        <form-login-page>/login.xhtml</form-login-page>
        <form-error-page>/login.xhtml</form-error-page>
    </form-login-config>
</login-config>
<security-constraint>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <web-resource-name>Secure Pages</web-resource-name>
        <description/>
        <url-pattern>/admin/*</url-pattern>
    </web-resource-collection>
    <auth-constraint>
        <role-name>ADMINS</role-name>
    </auth-constraint>
</security-constraint>

Form-based login is specified for all web pages under /admin. Access to those pages will be allowed only to users in the ADMINS role.

Assign security roles to users or groups of users in the realm.

To assign a security role to a group or to a user, add a security-role-mapping element to the application server-specific deployment descriptor, in this case glassfish-web.xml:

<security-role-mapping>
    <role-name>USERS</role-name>
    <group-name>USERS</group-name>
</security-role-mapping>
<security-role-mapping>
    <role-name>ADMINS</role-name>
    <group-name>ADMINS</group-name>
</security-role-mapping>

Since GlassFish Server users are assigned to groups during the user creation process, this is more efficient than mapping security roles to individual users.

50.4 Securing HTTP Resources

When a request URI is matched by multiple constrained URL patterns, the constraints that apply to the request are those that are associated with the best matching URL pattern. The servlet matching rules defined in Chapter 12, "Mapping Requests To Servlets," in the Java Servlet 3.1 Specification, are used to determine the best matching URL pattern to the request URI. No protection requirements apply to a request URI that is not matched by a constrained URL pattern. The HTTP method of the request plays no role in selecting the best matching URL pattern for a request.

When HTTP methods are listed within a constraint definition, the protections defined by the constraint are applied to the listed methods only.

When HTTP methods are not listed within a constraint definition, the protections defined by the constraint apply to the complete set of HTTP methods, including HTTP extension methods.

When constraints with different protection requirements apply to the same combination of URL patterns and HTTP methods, the rules for combining the protection requirements are as defined in Section 13.8.1, "Combining Constraints," in the Java Servlet 3.1 Specification.

Follow these guidelines to properly secure a web application.

Do not list HTTP methods within constraint definitions. This is the simplest way to ensure that you are not leaving HTTP methods unprotected. For example:

<!-- SECURITY CONSTRAINT #1 -->
<security-constraint>
    <display-name>Do not enumerate Http Methods</display-name>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <url-pattern>/company/*</url-pattern>
    </web-resource-collection>
    <auth-constraint>
        <role-name>sales</role-name>
    </auth-constraint>
</security-constraint>

If you list methods in a constraint, all non-listed methods of the effectively infinite set of possible HTTP methods, including extension methods, will be unprotected. Use such a constraint only if you are certain that this is the protection scheme you intend to define. The following example shows a constraint that lists the GET method and thus defines no protection on any of the other possible HTTP methods:

<!-- SECURITY CONSTRAINT #2 -->
<security-constraint>
    <display-name>
        Protect GET only, leave all other methods unprotected
    </display-name>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <url-pattern>/company/*</url-pattern>
        <http-method>GET</http-method>
    </web-resource-collection>
    <auth-constraint>
        <role-name>sales</role-name>
    </auth-constraint>
</security-constraint>

If you need to apply specific types of protection to specific HTTP methods, make sure that you define constraints to cover every method that you want to permit, with or without constraint, at the corresponding URL patterns. If there are any methods that you do not want to permit, you must also create a constraint that denies access to those methods at the same patterns; for an example, see security constraint #5 in the next bullet.

For example, to permit GET and POST, where POST requires authentication and GET is permitted without constraint, you could define the following constraints:

<!-- SECURITY CONSTRAINT #3 -->
<security-constraint>
    <display-name>Allow unprotected GET</display-name>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <url-pattern>/company/*</url-pattern>
        <http-method>GET</http-method>
    </web-resource-collection>
</security-constraint>

<!-- SECURITY CONSTRAINT #4 -->
<security-constraint>
    <display-name>Require authentication for POST</display-name>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <url-pattern>/company/*</url-pattern>
        <http-method>POST</http-method>
    </web-resource-collection>
    <auth-constraint>
        <role-name>sales</role-name>
    </auth-constraint>
</security-constraint>

The simplest way to ensure that you deny all HTTP methods except those that you want to be permitted is to use http-method-omission elements to omit those HTTP methods from the security constraint, and also to define an auth-constraint that names no roles. The security constraint will apply to all methods except those that were named in the omissions, and the constraint will apply only to the resources matched by the patterns in the constraint.

For example, the following constraint excludes access to all methods except GET and POST at the resources matched by the pattern /company/*:

<!-- SECURITY CONSTRAINT #5 -->
<security-constraint>
    <display-name>Deny all HTTP methods except GET and POST</display-name>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <url-pattern>/company/*</url-pattern>
        <http-method-omission>GET</http-method-omission>
        <http-method-omission>POST</http-method-omission>
    </web-resource-collection>
    <auth-constraint/>
</security-constraint>

If you want to extend these exclusions to the unconstrained parts of your application, also include the URL pattern / (forward slash):

<!-- SECURITY CONSTRAINT #6 -->
<security-constraint>
    <display-name>Deny all HTTP methods except GET and POST</display-name>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <url-pattern>/company/*</url-pattern>
        <url-pattern>/</url-pattern>
        <http-method-omission>GET</http-method-omission>
        <http-method-omission>POST</http-method-omission>
    </web-resource-collection>
    <auth-constraint/>
</security-constraint>

If, for your web application, you do not want any resource to be accessible unless you explicitly define a constraint that permits access to it, you can define an auth-constraint that names no roles and associate it with the URL pattern /. The URL pattern / is the weakest matching pattern. Do not list any HTTP methods in this constraint:

<!-- SECURITY CONSTRAINT #7 -->
<security-constraint>
    <display-name>
        Switch from Constraint to Permission model
        (where everything is denied by default)
    </display-name>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <url-pattern>/</url-pattern>
    </web-resource-collection>
    <auth-constraint/>
</security-constraint>

50.5 Securing Application Clients

The Java EE authentication requirements for application clients are the same as for other Java EE components, and the same authentication techniques can be used as for other Java EE application components. No authentication is necessary when accessing unprotected web resources.

When accessing protected web resources, the usual varieties of authentication can be used: HTTP basic authentication, HTTP login-form authentication, or SSL client authentication. Specifying an Authentication Mechanism in the Deployment Descriptor describes how to specify HTTP basic authentication and HTTP login-form authentication. Client Authentication describes how to specify SSL client authentication.

Authentication is required when accessing protected enterprise beans. The authentication mechanisms for enterprise beans are discussed in Securing Enterprise Beans.

An application client makes use of an authentication service provided by the application client container for authenticating its users. The container's service can be integrated with the native platform's authentication system so that a single sign-on capability is used. The container can authenticate the user either when the application is started or when a protected resource is accessed.

An application client can provide a class, called a login module, to gather authentication data. If so, the javax.security.auth.callback.CallbackHandler interface must be implemented, and the class name must be specified in its deployment descriptor. The application's callback handler must fully support Callback objects specified in the javax.security.auth.callback package.

50.5.1 Using Login Modules

An application client can use the Java Authentication and Authorization Service (JAAS) to create login modules for authentication. A JAAS-based application implements the javax.security.auth.callback.CallbackHandler interface so that it can interact with users to enter specific authentication data, such as user names or passwords, or to display error and warning messages.

Applications implement the CallbackHandler interface and pass it to the login context, which forwards it directly to the underlying login modules. A login module uses the callback handler both to gather input, such as a password or smart card PIN, from users and to supply information, such as status information, to users. Because the application specifies the callback handler, an underlying login module can remain independent of the various ways applications interact with users.

For example, the implementation of a callback handler for a GUI application might display a window to solicit user input, or the implementation of a callback handler for a command-line tool might simply prompt the user for input directly from the command line.

The login module passes an array of appropriate callbacks to the callback handler's handle method, such as a NameCallback for the user name and a PasswordCallback for the password; the callback handler performs the requested user interaction and sets appropriate values in the callbacks. For example, to process a NameCallback, the CallbackHandler might prompt for a name, retrieve the value from the user, and call the setName method of the NameCallback to store the name.

For more information on using JAAS for authentication in login modules, refer to the documentation listed in Further Information about Advanced Security Topics.

50.5.2 Using Programmatic Login

Programmatic login enables the client code to supply user credentials. If you are using an EJB client, you can use the com.sun.appserv.security.ProgrammaticLogin class with its convenient login and logout methods. Programmatic login is specific to a server.

50.6 Securing Enterprise Information Systems Applications

In Enterprise Information Systems (EIS) applications, components request a connection to an EIS resource. As part of this connection, the EIS can require a sign-on for the requester to access the resource. The application component provider has two choices for the design of the EIS sign-on.

Container-managed sign-on: The application component lets the container take the responsibility of configuring and managing the EIS sign-on. The container determines the user name and password for establishing a connection to an EIS instance. For more information, see Container-Managed Sign-On.

Component-managed sign-on: The application component code manages EIS sign-on by including code that performs the sign-on process to an EIS. For more information, see Component-Managed Sign-On.

You can also configure security for resource adapters. See Configuring Resource Adapter Security.

50.6.1 Container-Managed Sign-On

In container-managed sign-on, an application component does not have to pass any sign-on security information to the getConnection() method. The security information is supplied by the container, as shown in the following example (the method call is highlighted in bold):

// Business method in an application component
Context initctx = new InitialContext();
// Perform JNDI lookup to obtain a connection factory
javax.resource.cci.ConnectionFactory cxf =
    (javax.resource.cci.ConnectionFactory)initctx.lookup(
    "java:comp/env/eis/MainframeCxFactory");
// Invoke factory to obtain a connection. The security
// information is not passed in the getConnection method
javax.resource.cci.Connection cx = cxf.getConnection();
...

50.6.2 Component-Managed Sign-On

In component-managed sign-on, an application component is responsible for passing the needed sign-on security information for the resource to the getConnection method. For example, security information might be a user name and password, as shown here (the method call is highlighted in bold):

// Method in an application component
Context initctx = new InitialContext();

// Perform JNDI lookup to obtain a connection factory
javax.resource.cci.ConnectionFactory cxf =
    (javax.resource.cci.ConnectionFactory)initctx.lookup(
    "java:comp/env/eis/MainframeCxFactory");

// Get a new ConnectionSpec
com.myeis.ConnectionSpecImpl properties = //..

// Invoke factory to obtain a connection
properties.setUserName("...");
properties.setPassword("...");
javax.resource.cci.Connection cx =
    cxf.getConnection(properties);
...

50.6.3 Configuring Resource Adapter Security

A resource adapter is a system-level software component that typically implements network connectivity to an external resource manager. A resource adapter can extend the functionality of the Java EE platform either by implementing one of the Java EE standard service APIs, such as a JDBC driver, or by defining and implementing a resource adapter for a connector to an external application system. Resource adapters can also provide services that are entirely local, perhaps interacting with native resources. Resource adapters interface with the Java EE platform through the Java EE service provider interfaces (Java EE SPI). A resource adapter that uses the Java EE SPIs to attach to the Java EE platform will be able to work with all Java EE products.

To configure the security settings for a resource adapter, you need to edit the resource adapter descriptor file, ra.xml. Here is an example of the part of an ra.xml file that configures security properties for a resource adapter:

<authentication-mechanism>
    <authentication-mechanism-type>
        BasicPassword
    </authentication-mechanism-type>
    <credential-interface>
        javax.resource.spi.security.PasswordCredential
    </credential-interface>
</authentication-mechanism>
<reauthentication-support>false</reauthentication-support>

You can find out more about the options for configuring resource adapter security by reviewing as-install/lib/schemas/connector_1_7.xsd. You can configure the following elements in the resource adapter deployment descriptor file.

Authentication mechanisms: Use the authentication-mechanism element to specify an authentication mechanism supported by the resource adapter. This support is for the resource adapter, not for the underlying EIS instance.

There are two supported mechanism types:

BasicPassword, which supports the following interface:

javax.resource.spi.security.PasswordCredential

Kerbv5, which supports the following interface:

javax.resource.spi.security.GenericCredential

GlassFish Server does not currently support this mechanism type.

Reauthentication support: Use the reauthentication-support element to specify whether the resource adapter implementation supports reauthentication of existing Managed-Connection instances. Options are true or false.

Security permissions: Use the security-permission element to specify a security permission that is required by the resource adapter code. Support for security permissions is optional and is not supported in the current release of GlassFish Server. You can, however, manually update the server.policy file to add the relevant permissions for the resource adapter.

The security permissions listed in the deployment descriptor are different from those required by the default permission set as specified in the connector specification.

For more information on the implementation of the security permission specification, see the security policy file documentation listed in Further Information about Advanced Security Topics.

In addition to specifying resource adapter security in the ra.xml file, you can create a security map for a connector connection pool to map an application principal or a user group to a back-end EIS principal. The security map is usually used if one or more EIS back-end principals are used to execute operations (on the EIS) initiated by various principals or user groups in the application.

50.6.4 Mapping an Application Principal to EIS Principals

When using GlassFish Server, you can use security maps to map the caller identity of the application (principal or user group) to a suitable EIS principal in container-managed transaction-based scenarios. When an application principal initiates a request to an EIS, GlassFish Server first checks for an exact principal by using the security map defined for the connector connection pool to determine the mapped back-end EIS principal. If there is no exact match, GlassFish Server uses the wildcard character specification, if any, to determine the mapped back-end EIS principal. Security maps are used when an application user needs to execute an EIS operation that requires execution as a specific identity in the EIS.

To work with security maps, use the Administration Console. From the Administration Console, follow these steps to get to the security maps page.

In the navigation tree, expand the Resources node.

Expand the Connectors node.

Select the Connector Connection Pools node.

On the Connector Connection Pools page, click the name of the connection pool for which you want to create a security map.

Click the Security Maps tab.

Click New to create a new security map for the connection pool.

Enter a name by which you will refer to the security map, as well as the other required information.

Click Help for more information on the individual options.

50.7 Configuring Security Using Deployment Descriptors

The recommended way to configure security in the Java EE 7 platform is with annotations. If you wish to override the security settings at deployment time, you can use security elements in the web.xml deployment descriptor to do so. This section describes how to use the deployment descriptor to specify basic authentication and to override default principal-to-role mapping.

50.7.1 Specifying Security for Basic Authentication in the Deployment Descriptor

The elements of the deployment descriptor that add basic authentication to an example tell the server or browser to perform the following tasks.

Send a standard login dialog box to collect user name and password data.

Verify that the user is authorized to access the application.

If authorized, display the servlet to the user.

The following sample code shows the security elements for a deployment descriptor that could be used in the example of basic authentication found in the tut-install/examples/security/hello2_basicauth/ directory:

    <security-constraint>
        <display-name>SecurityConstraint</display-name>
        <web-resource-collection>
             <web-resource-name>WRCollection</web-resource-name>
            <url-pattern>/greeting</url-pattern>
        </web-resource-collection>
        <auth-constraint>
            <role-name>TutorialUser</role-name>
        </auth-constraint>
        <user-data-constraint>
             <transport-guarantee>CONFIDENTIAL</transport-guarantee>
        </user-data-constraint>
    </security-constraint>
    <login-config>
        <auth-method>BASIC</auth-method>
        <realm-name>file</realm-name>
    </login-config>
    <security-role>
        <role-name>TutorialUser</role-name>
    </security-role>

This deployment descriptor specifies that the request URI /greeting can be accessed only by users who have entered their user names and passwords and have been authorized to access this URL because they have been verified to be in the role TutorialUser. The user name and password data will be sent over a protected transport in order to keep it from being read in transit.

50.7.2 Specifying Non-Default Principal-to-Role Mapping in the Deployment Descriptor

To map a role name permitted by the application or module to principals (users) and groups defined on the server, use the security-role-mapping element in the runtime deployment descriptor file (glassfish-application.xml, glassfish-web.xml, or glassfish-ejb-jar.xml). The entry needs to declare a mapping between a security role used in the application and one or more groups or principals defined for the applicable realm of GlassFish Server. An example for the glassfish-web.xml file is shown below:

<glassfish-web-app>
    <security-role-mapping>
        <role-name>DIRECTOR</role-name>
        <principal-name>schwartz</principal-name>
    </security-role-mapping>
    <security-role-mapping>
        <role-name>DEPT-ADMIN</role-name>
        <group-name>dept-admins</group-name>
    </security-role-mapping>
</glassfish-web-app>

The role name can be mapped to either a specific principal (user), a group, or both. The principal or group names referenced must be valid principals or groups in the current default realm of GlassFish Server. The role-name in this example must exactly match the role-name in the security-role element of the corresponding web.xml file or the role name defined in the @DeclareRoles and/or @RolesAllowed annotations.

50.8 Further Information about Advanced Security Topics

For more information about the security topics covered in this chapter, see

Documentation on the keytool command:

http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/technotes/tools/solaris/keytool.html

Java Authentication and Authorization Service (JAAS) Reference Guide:

http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/technotes/guides/security/jaas/JAASRefGuide.html

Java Authentication and Authorization Service (JAAS): LoginModule Developer's Guide:

http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/technotes/guides/security/jaas/JAASLMDevGuide.html

Documentation on security policy file syntax:

http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/technotes/guides/security/PolicyFiles.html#FileSyntax

49 Getting Started Securing Enterprise Applications

This chapter describes how to administer security for enterprise applications.

The following topics are addressed here:

Basic Security Tasks for Enterprise Applications

Securing Enterprise Beans

Examples: Securing Enterprise Beans

49.1 Basic Security Tasks for Enterprise Applications

System administrators, application developers, bean providers, and deployers are responsible for administering security for enterprise applications. The basic security tasks are as follows:

Setting up a database of users and assigning them to the proper group

Setting up identity propagation

Setting GlassFish Server properties that enable the applications to run properly, such as setting default principal-to-role mapping

Annotating the classes and methods of an enterprise application to provide information about which methods need to have restricted access

The sections on the security examples in this chapter and the previous chapter explain how to perform these tasks.

49.2 Securing Enterprise Beans

Enterprise beans are Java EE components that implement EJB technology. Enterprise beans run in the EJB container, a runtime environment within GlassFish Server. Although transparent to the application developer, the EJB container provides system-level services, such as transactions and security to its enterprise beans, which form the core of transactional Java EE applications.

Enterprise bean methods can be secured in either of the following ways.

Declarative security (preferred): Expresses an application component's security requirements using either deployment descriptors or annotations. The presence of an annotation in the business method of an enterprise bean class that specifies method permissions is all that is needed for method protection and authentication in some situations. This section discusses this simple and efficient method of securing enterprise beans.

Because of some limitations to the simplified method of securing enterprise beans, you would want to continue to use the deployment descriptor to specify security information in some instances. An authentication mechanism must be configured on the server for the simple solution to work. Basic authentication is GlassFish Server's default authentication method.

This tutorial explains how to invoke user name/password authentication of authorized users by decorating the enterprise application's business methods with annotations that specify method permissions.

To make the deployer's task easier, the application developer can define security roles. A security role is a grouping of permissions that a given type of application users must have in order to successfully use the application. For example, in a payroll application, some users will want to view their own payroll information (employee), some will need to view others' payroll information (manager), and some will need to be able to change others' payroll information (payrollDept). The application developer would determine the potential users of the application and which methods would be accessible to which users. The application developer would then decorate classes or methods of the enterprise bean with annotations that specify the types of users authorized to access those methods. Using annotations to specify authorized users is described in Specifying Authorized Users by Declaring Security Roles.

When one of the annotations is used to define method permissions, the deployment system will automatically require user name/password authentication. In this type of authentication, a user is prompted to enter a user name and password, which will be compared against a database of known users. If the user is found and the password matches, the roles that the user is assigned will be compared against the roles that are authorized to access the method. If the user is authenticated and found to have a role that is authorized to access that method, the data will be returned to the user.

Using declarative security is discussed in Securing an Enterprise Bean Using Declarative Security.

Programmatic security: For an enterprise bean, code embedded in a business method that is used to access a caller's identity programmatically and that uses this information to make security decisions. Programmatic security is useful when declarative security alone is not sufficient to express the security model of an application.

In general, security management should be enforced by the container in a manner that is transparent to the enterprise beans' business methods. The programmatic security APIs described in this chapter should be used only in the less frequent situations in which the enterprise bean business methods need to access the security-context information, such as when you want to grant access based on the time of day or other nontrivial condition checks for a particular role.

Programmatic security is discussed in Securing an Enterprise Bean Programmatically.

Some of the material in this chapter assumes that you have already read Chapter 32, "Enterprise Beans", Chapter 33, "Getting Started with Enterprise Beans", and Chapter 47, "Introduction to Security in the Java EE Platform".

This section discusses securing a Java EE application where one or more modules, such as EJB JAR files, are packaged into an EAR file, the archive file that holds the application. Security annotations will be used in the Java programming class files to specify authorized users and basic, or user name/password, authentication.

Enterprise beans often provide the business logic of a web application. In these cases, packaging the enterprise bean within the web application's WAR module simplifies deployment and application organization. Enterprise beans may be packaged within a WAR module as Java class files or within a JAR file that is bundled within the WAR module. When a servlet or JavaServer Faces page handles the web front end and the application is packaged into a WAR module as a Java class file, security for the application can be handled in the application's web.xml file. The EJB in the WAR file can have its own deployment descriptor, ejb-jar.xml, if required. Securing web applications using web.xml is discussed in Chapter 48, "Getting Started Securing Web Applications".

The following sections describe declarative and programmatic security mechanisms that can be used to protect enterprise bean resources. The protected resources include enterprise bean methods that are called from application clients, web components, or other enterprise beans.

For more information on this topic, read the Enterprise JavaBeans 3.2 specification. This document can be downloaded from http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=345. Chapter 12 of this specification, "Security Management," discusses security management for enterprise beans.

49.2.1 Securing an Enterprise Bean Using Declarative Security

Declarative security enables the application developer to specify which users are authorized to access which methods of the enterprise beans and to authenticate these users with basic, or user name/password, authentication. Frequently, the person who is developing an enterprise application is not the same person who is responsible for deploying the application. An application developer who uses declarative security to define method permissions and authentication mechanisms is passing along to the deployer a security view of the enterprise beans contained in the EJB JAR. When a security view is passed on to the deployer, he or she uses this information to define method permissions for security roles. If you don't define a security view, the deployer will have to determine what each business method does to determine which users are authorized to call each method.

A security view consists of a set of security roles, a semantic grouping of permissions that a given type of users of an application must have to successfully access the application. Security roles are meant to be logical roles, representing a type of user. You can define method permissions for each security role. A method permission is a permission to invoke a specified group of methods of an enterprise bean's business interface, home interface, component interface, and/or web service endpoints. After method permissions are defined, user name/password authentication will be used to verify the identity of the user.

It is important to keep in mind that security roles are used to define the logical security view of an application. They should not be confused with the user groups, users, principals, and other concepts that exist in GlassFish Server. An additional step is required to map the roles defined in the application to users, groups, and principals that are the components of the user database in the file realm of GlassFish Server. These steps are outlined in Mapping Roles to Users and Groups.

The following sections show how an application developer uses declarative security to either secure an application or to create a security view to pass along to the deployer.

49.2.1.1 Specifying Authorized Users by Declaring Security Roles

This section discusses how to use annotations to specify the method permissions for the methods of a bean class. For more information on these annotations, refer to the Common Annotations for the Java Platform specification at http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=250.

Method permissions can be specified on the class, the business methods of the class, or both. Method permissions can be specified on a method of the bean class to override the method permissions value specified on the entire bean class. The following annotations are used to specify method permissions.

@DeclareRoles: Specifies all the roles that the application will use, including roles not specifically named in a @RolesAllowed annotation. The set of security roles the application uses is the total of the security roles defined in the @DeclareRoles and @RolesAllowed annotations.

The @DeclareRoles annotation is specified on a bean class, where it serves to declare roles that can be tested (for example, by calling isCallerInRole) from within the methods of the annotated class. When declaring the name of a role used as a parameter to the isCallerInRole(String roleName) method, the declared name must be the same as the parameter value.

The following example code demonstrates the use of the @DeclareRoles annotation:

@DeclareRoles("BusinessAdmin")
public class Calculator {
    ...
}

The syntax for declaring more than one role is as shown in the following example:

@DeclareRoles({"Administrator", "Manager", "Employee"})

@RolesAllowed("list-of-roles"): Specifies the security roles permitted to access methods in an application. This annotation can be specified on a class or on one or more methods. When specified at the class level, the annotation applies to all methods in the class. When specified on a method, the annotation applies to that method only and overrides any values specified at the class level.

To specify that no roles are authorized to access methods in an application, use the @DenyAll annotation. To specify that a user in any role is authorized to access the application, use the @PermitAll annotation.

When used in conjunction with the @DeclareRoles annotation, the combined set of security roles is used by the application.

The following example code demonstrates the use of the @RolesAllowed annotation:

@DeclareRoles({"Administrator", "Manager", "Employee"})
public class Calculator {

    @RolesAllowed("Administrator")
    public void setNewRate(int rate) {
        ...
    }
}

@PermitAll: Specifies that all security roles are permitted to execute the specified method or methods. The user is not checked against a database to ensure that he or she is authorized to access this application.

This annotation can be specified on a class or on one or more methods. Specifying this annotation on the class means that it applies to all methods of the class. Specifying it at the method level means that it applies to only that method.

The following example code demonstrates the use of the @PermitAll annotation:

import javax.annotation.security.*;
@RolesAllowed("RestrictedUsers")
public class Calculator {

    @RolesAllowed("Administrator")
    public void setNewRate(int rate) {
        //...
    }
    @PermitAll
    public long convertCurrency(long amount) {
        //...
    }
}

@DenyAll: Specifies that no security roles are permitted to execute the specified method or methods. This means that these methods are excluded from execution in the Java EE container.

The following example code demonstrates the use of the @DenyAll annotation:

import javax.annotation.security.*;
@RolesAllowed("Users")
public class Calculator {
    @RolesAllowed("Administrator")
    public void setNewRate(int rate) {
        //...
    }
    @DenyAll
    public long convertCurrency(long amount) {
        //...
    }
}

The following code snippet demonstrates the use of the @DeclareRoles annotation with the isCallerInRole method. In this example, the @DeclareRoles annotation declares a role that the enterprise bean PayrollBean uses to make the security check by using isCallerInRole("payroll") to verify that the caller is authorized to change salary data:

@DeclareRoles("payroll")
@Stateless public class PayrollBean implements Payroll {
    @Resource SessionContext ctx;

    public void updateEmployeeInfo(EmplInfo info) {

        oldInfo = ... read from database;

        // The salary field can be changed only by callers
        // who have the security role "payroll"
        Principal callerPrincipal = ctx.getCallerPrincipal();
        if (info.salary != oldInfo.salary && !ctx.isCallerInRole("payroll")) {
            throw new SecurityException(...);
        }
        ...
    }
    ...
}

The following example code illustrates the use of the @RolesAllowed annotation:

@RolesAllowed("admin")
public class SomeClass {
    public void aMethod () {...}
    public void bMethod () {...}
    ...
}

@Stateless public class MyBean extends SomeClass implements A  {

    @RolesAllowed("HR")
    public void aMethod () {...}

    public void cMethod () {...}
    ...
}

In this example, assuming that aMethod, bMethod, and cMethod are methods of business interface A, the method permissions values of methods aMethod and bMethod are @RolesAllowed("HR") and @RolesAllowed("admin"), respectively. The method permissions for method cMethod have not been specified.

To clarify, the annotations are not inherited by the subclass itself. Instead, the annotations apply to methods of the superclass that are inherited by the subclass.

49.2.1.2 Specifying an Authentication Mechanism and Secure Connection

When method permissions are specified, basic user name/password authentication will be invoked by GlassFish Server.

To use a different type of authentication or to require a secure connection using SSL, specify this information in an application deployment descriptor.

49.2.2 Securing an Enterprise Bean Programmatically

Programmatic security, code that is embedded in a business method, is used to access a caller's identity programmatically and uses this information to make security decisions within the method itself.

49.2.2.1 Accessing an Enterprise Bean Caller's Security Context

In general, security management should be enforced by the container in a manner that is transparent to the enterprise bean's business methods. The security API described in this section should be used only in the less frequent situations in which the enterprise bean business methods need to access the security context information, such as when you want to restrict access to a particular time of day.

The javax.ejb.EJBContext interface provides two methods that allow the bean provider to access security information about the enterprise bean's caller.

getCallerPrincipal allows the enterprise bean methods to obtain the current caller principal's name. The methods might, for example, use the name as a key to information in a database.

The following code sample illustrates the use of the getCallerPrincipal method:

@Stateless public class EmployeeServiceBean implements EmployeeService {
    @Resource SessionContext ctx;
    @PersistenceContext EntityManager em;

    public void changePhoneNumber(...) {
        ...
        // obtain the caller principal
        callerPrincipal = ctx.getCallerPrincipal();

        // obtain the caller principal's name
        callerKey = callerPrincipal.getName();

        // use callerKey as primary key to find EmployeeRecord
        EmployeeRecord myEmployeeRecord =
            em.find(EmployeeRecord.class, callerKey);

        // update phone number
        myEmployeeRecord.setPhoneNumber(...);

        ...
    }
}

In this example, the enterprise bean obtains the principal name of the current caller and uses it as the primary key to locate an EmployeeRecord entity. This example assumes that application has been deployed such that the current caller principal contains the primary key used for the identification of employees (for example, employee number).

isCallerInRole allows the developer to code the security checks that cannot be easily defined using method permissions. Such a check might impose a role-based limit on a request, or it might depend on information stored in the database.

The enterprise bean code can use the isCallerInRole method to test whether the current caller has been assigned to a given security role. Security roles are defined by the bean provider or the application assembler and are assigned by the deployer to principals or principal groups that exist in the operational environment.

The following code sample illustrates the use of the isCallerInRole method:

@Stateless public class PayrollBean implements Payroll {
     @Resource SessionContext ctx;

     public void updateEmployeeInfo(EmplInfo info) {

         oldInfo = ... read from database;

         // The salary field can be changed only by callers
         // who have the security role "payroll"
         if (info.salary != oldInfo.salary &&
             !ctx.isCallerInRole("payroll")) {
                 throw new SecurityException(...);
         }
         ...
     }
     ...
 }

You would use programmatic security in this way to dynamically control access to a method, for example, when you want to deny access except during a particular time of day. An example application that uses the getCallerPrincipal and isCallerInRole methods is described in The converter-secure Example: Securing an Enterprise Bean with Programmatic Security.

49.2.3 Propagating a Security Identity (Run-As)

You can specify whether a caller's security identity should be used for the execution of specified methods of an enterprise bean or whether a specific run-as identity should be used. Figure 49-1 illustrates this concept.

Figure 49-1 Security Identity Propagation

Description of "Figure 49-1 Security Identity Propagation"

In this illustration, an application client is making a call to an enterprise bean method in one EJB container. This enterprise bean method, in turn, makes a call to an enterprise bean method in another container. The security identity during the first call is the identity of the caller. The security identity during the second call can be any of the following options.

By default, the identity of the caller of the intermediate component is propagated to the target enterprise bean. This technique is used when the target container trusts the intermediate container.

A specific identity is propagated to the target enterprise bean. This technique is used when the target container expects access using a specific identity.

To propagate an identity to the target enterprise bean, configure a run-as identity for the bean, as described in Configuring a Component's Propagated Security Identity. Establishing a run-as identity for an enterprise bean does not affect the identities of its callers, which are the identities tested for permission to access the methods of the enterprise bean. The run-as identity establishes the identity that the enterprise bean will use when it makes calls.

The run-as identity applies to the enterprise bean as a whole, including all the methods of the enterprise bean's business interface, local and remote interfaces, component interface, and web service endpoint interfaces, the message listener methods of a message-driven bean, the timeout method of an enterprise bean, and all internal methods of the bean that might be called in turn.

49.2.3.1 Configuring a Component's Propagated Security Identity

You can configure an enterprise bean's run-as, or propagated, security identity by using the @RunAs annotation, which defines the role of the application during execution in a Java EE container. The annotation can be specified on a class, allowing developers to execute an application under a particular role. The role must map to the user/group information in the container's security realm. The @RunAs annotation specifies the name of a security role as its parameter.

The following code demonstrates the use of the @RunAs annotation:

@RunAs("Admin")
public class Calculator {
    //....
}

You will have to map the run-as role name to a given principal defined in GlassFish Server if the given roles are associated with more than one user principal.

49.2.3.2 Trust between Containers

When an enterprise bean is designed so that either the original caller identity or a designated identity is used to call a target bean, the target bean will receive the propagated identity only. The target bean will not receive any authentication data.

There is no way for the target container to authenticate the propagated security identity. However, because the security identity is used in authorization checks (for example, method permissions or with the isCallerInRole method), it is vitally important that the security identity be authentic. Because no authentication data is available to authenticate the propagated identity, the target must trust that the calling container has propagated an authenticated security identity.

By default, GlassFish Server is configured to trust identities that are propagated from different containers. Therefore, you do not need to take any special steps to set up a trust relationship.

49.2.4 Deploying Secure Enterprise Beans

The deployer is responsible for ensuring that an assembled application is secure after it has been deployed in the target operational environment. If a security view has been provided to the deployer through the use of security annotations and/or a deployment descriptor, the security view is mapped to the mechanisms and policies used by the security domain in the target operational environment, which in this case is GlassFish Server. If no security view is provided, the deployer must set up the appropriate security policy for the enterprise bean application.

Deployment information is specific to a web or application server.

49.3 Examples: Securing Enterprise Beans

The following examples show how to secure enterprise beans using declarative and programmatic security.

49.3.1 The cart-secure Example: Securing an Enterprise Bean with Declarative Security

This section discusses how to configure an enterprise bean for basic user name/password authentication. When a bean that is constrained in this way is requested, the server requests a user name and password from the client and verifies that the user name and password are valid by comparing them against a database of authorized users in GlassFish Server.

If the topic of authentication is new to you, see Specifying Authentication Mechanisms.

This example demonstrates security by starting with the unsecured enterprise bean application, cart, which is found in the tut-install/examples/ejb/cart/ directory and is discussed in The cart Example.

In general, the following steps are necessary to add user name/password authentication to an existing application that contains an enterprise bean. In the example application included with this tutorial, these steps have been completed for you and are listed here simply to show what needs to be done should you wish to create a similar application.

Create an application like the one in The cart Example. The example in this tutorial starts with this example and demonstrates adding basic authentication of the client to this application. The example application discussed in this section can be found at tut-install/examples/security/cart-secure/.

If you have not already done so, complete the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples to configure your system for running the tutorial applications.

Modify the source code for the enterprise bean, CartBean.java, to specify which roles are authorized to access which protected methods. This step is discussed in Annotating the Bean.

Build, package, and deploy the enterprise bean; then build and run the client application by following the steps in To Run the cart-secure Example Using NetBeans IDE or To Run the cart-secure Example Using Maven.

49.3.1.1 Annotating the Bean

The source code for the original cart application was modified as shown in the following code snippet (modifications in bold). The resulting file can be found in the file tut-install/examples/security/cart-secure/cart-secure-ejb/src/main/java/javaeetutorial/cart/ejb/CartBean.java.

The code snippet is as follows:

package javaeetutorial.cartsecure.ejb;

import java.io.Serializable;
import java.util.ArrayList;
import java.util.List;
import javaeetutorial.cart.util.BookException;
import javaeetutorial.cart.util.IdVerifier;
import javax.ejb.Remove;
import javax.ejb.Stateful;
import javax.annotation.security.DeclareRoles;
import javax.annotation.security.RolesAllowed;

@Stateful
@DeclareRoles("TutorialUser")
public class CartBean implements Cart, Serializable {
    List<String> contents;
    String customerId;
    String customerName;

    @Override
    public void initialize(String person) throws BookException {
        if (person == null) {
            throw new BookException("Null person not allowed.");
        } else {
            customerName = person;
        }

        customerId = "0";
        contents = new ArrayList<>();
    }

    @Override
    public void initialize(String person, String id) throws BookException {
        if (person == null) {
            throw new BookException("Null person not allowed.");
        } else {
            customerName = person;
        }

        IdVerifier idChecker = new IdVerifier();

        if (idChecker.validate(id)) {
            customerId = id;
        } else {
            throw new BookException("Invalid id: " + id);
        }

        contents = new ArrayList<>();
    }

    @Override
    @RolesAllowed("TutorialUser")
    public void addBook(String title) {
        contents.add(title);
    }

    @Override
    @RolesAllowed("TutorialUser")
    public void removeBook(String title) throws BookException {
        boolean result = contents.remove(title);

        if (result == false) {
            throw new BookException("\"" + title + "\" not in cart.");
        }
    }

    @Override
    @RolesAllowed("TutorialUser")
    public List<String> getContents() {
        return contents;
    }

    @Override
    @Remove()
    @RolesAllowed("TutorialUser")
    public void remove() {
        contents = null;
    }
}

The @RolesAllowed annotation is specified on methods for which you want to restrict access. In this example, only users in the role of TutorialUser will be allowed to add and remove books from the cart and to list the contents of the cart. A @RolesAllowed annotation implicitly declares a role that will be referenced in the application; therefore, no @DeclareRoles annotation is required. The presence of the @RolesAllowed annotation also implicitly declares that authentication will be required for a user to access these methods. If no authentication method is specified in the deployment descriptor, the type of authentication will be user name/password authentication.

49.3.1.2 To Run the cart-secure Example Using NetBeans IDE

Follow the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples.

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/security

Select the cart-secure folder.

Select the Open Required Projects check box.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the cart-secure project and select Build.

This step builds and packages the application into cart-secure.ear, located in the cart-secure-ear/target/ directory, and deploys this EAR file to your GlassFish Server instance, retrieves the client stubs, and runs the client.

In the Login for user: dialog box, enter the user name and password of a file realm user created in GlassFish Server and assigned to the group TutorialUser; then click OK.

If the user name and password you enter are authenticated, the output of the application client appears in the Output tab:

...
Retrieving book title from cart: Infinite Jest
Retrieving book title from cart: Bel Canto
Retrieving book title from cart: Kafka on the Shore
Removing "Gravity's Rainbow" from cart.
Caught a BookException: "Gravity's Rainbow" not in cart.
Java Result: 1
...

If the user name and password are not authenticated, the dialog box reappears until you enter correct values.

49.3.1.3 To Run the cart-secure Example Using Maven

Follow the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples.

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/security/cart-secure/

To build the application, package it into an EAR file in the cart-secure-ear/target subdirectory, deploy it, and run it, enter the following command at the terminal window or command prompt:

mvn install

In the Login for user: dialog box, enter the user name and password of a file realm user created in GlassFish Server and assigned to the group TutorialUser; then click OK.

If the user name and password you enter are authenticated, the output of the application client appears in the Output tab:

...
Retrieving book title from cart: Infinite Jest
Retrieving book title from cart: Bel Canto
Retrieving book title from cart: Kafka on the Shore
Removing "Gravity's Rainbow" from cart.
Caught a BookException: "Gravity's Rainbow" not in cart.
Java Result: 1
...

If the user name and password are not authenticated, the dialog box reappears until you enter correct values.

49.3.2 The converter-secure Example: Securing an Enterprise Bean with Programmatic Security

This example demonstrates how to use the getCallerPrincipal and isCallerInRole methods with an enterprise bean. This example starts with a very simple EJB application, converter, and modifies the methods of the ConverterBean so that currency conversion will occur only when the requester is in the role of TutorialUser.

This example can be found in the tut-install/examples/security/converter-secure directory. This example is based on the unsecured enterprise bean application, converter, which is discussed in Chapter 33, "Getting Started with Enterprise Beans" and is found in the tut-install/examples/ejb/converter/ directory. This section builds on the example by adding the necessary elements to secure the application by using the getCallerPrincipal and isCallerInRole methods, which are discussed in more detail in Accessing an Enterprise Bean Caller's Security Context.

In general, the following steps are necessary when using the getCallerPrincipal and isCallerInRole methods with an enterprise bean. In the example application included with this tutorial, many of these steps have been completed for you and are listed here simply to show what needs to be done should you wish to create a similar application.

Create a simple enterprise bean application.

Set up a user on GlassFish Server in the file realm, in the group TutorialUser, and set up default principal to role mapping. To do this, follow the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples.

Modify the bean to add the getCallerPrincipal and isCallerInRole methods.

If the application contains a web client that is a servlet, specify security for the servlet, as described in Specifying Security for Basic Authentication Using Annotations.

Build, package, deploy, and run the application.

49.3.2.1 Modifying ConverterBean

The source code for the original ConverterBean class was modified to add the if..else clause that tests whether the caller is in the role of TutorialUser. If the user is in the correct role, the currency conversion is computed and displayed. If the user is not in the correct role, the computation is not performed, and the application displays the result as 0. The code example can be found in tut-install/examples/security/converter-secure/converter-secure-ejb/src/main/java/javaeetutorial/converter/ejb/ConverterBean.java.

The code snippet (with modifications shown in bold) is as follows:

package javaeetutorial.convertersecure.ejb;

import java.math.BigDecimal;
import java.security.Principal;
import javax.ejb.Stateless;
import javax.annotation.Resource;
import javax.ejb.SessionContext;
import javax.annotation.security.DeclareRoles;
import javax.annotation.security.RolesAllowed;

@Stateless()
@DeclareRoles("TutorialUser")
public class ConverterBean{

    @Resource SessionContext ctx;
    private final BigDecimal yenRate = new BigDecimal("104.34");
    private final BigDecimal euroRate = new BigDecimal("0.007");

    @RolesAllowed("TutorialUser")
     public BigDecimal dollarToYen(BigDecimal dollars) {
        BigDecimal result = new BigDecimal("0.0");
        Principal callerPrincipal = ctx.getCallerPrincipal(); 
        if (ctx.isCallerInRole("TutorialUser")) {
            result = dollars.multiply(yenRate);
            return result.setScale(2, BigDecimal.ROUND_UP);
        } else {
            return result.setScale(2, BigDecimal.ROUND_UP); 
        }
    }

    @RolesAllowed("TutorialUser")
    public BigDecimal yenToEuro(BigDecimal yen) {
        BigDecimal result = new BigDecimal("0.0");
        Principal callerPrincipal = ctx.getCallerPrincipal(); 
        if (ctx.isCallerInRole("TutorialUser")) {
             result = yen.multiply(euroRate);
             return result.setScale(2, BigDecimal.ROUND_UP);
        } else {
             return result.setScale(2, BigDecimal.ROUND_UP); 
        }
    }
}

49.3.2.2 Modifying ConverterServlet

The following annotations specify security for the converter web client, ConverterServlet:

@WebServlet(urlPatterns = {"/"})
@ServletSecurity(
@HttpConstraint(transportGuarantee = TransportGuarantee.CONFIDENTIAL,
    rolesAllowed = {"TutorialUser"}))

49.3.2.3 To Run the converter-secure Example Using NetBeans IDE

Follow the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples.

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/security

Select the converter-secure folder.

Click Open Project.

Right-click the converter-secure project and select Build.

This command builds and deploys the example application to your GlassFish Server instance.

49.3.2.4 To Run the converter-secure Example Using Maven

Follow the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples.

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/security/converter-secure/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, converter-secure.war, that is located in the target directory, and deploys the WAR file.

49.3.2.5 To Run the converter-secure Example

Open a web browser to the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/converter-secure

An Authentication Required dialog box appears.

Enter a user name and password combination that corresponds to a user who has already been created in the file realm of GlassFish Server and has been assigned to the group TutorialUser; then click OK.

Enter 100 in the input field and click Submit.

A second page appears, showing the converted values.

48 Getting Started Securing Web Applications

The ways to implement security for Java EE web applications are discussed in a general way in Securing Containers. This chapter provides more detail and a few examples that explore these security services as they relate to web components.

A web application is accessed using a web browser over a network, such as the Internet or a company's intranet. As discussed in Distributed Multitiered Applications, the Java EE platform uses a distributed multitiered application model, and web applications run in the web tier.

Web applications contain resources that can be accessed by many users. These resources often traverse unprotected, open networks, such as the Internet. In such an environment, a substantial number of web applications will require some type of security.

Securing applications and their clients in the business tier and the EIS tier is discussed in Chapter 49, "Getting Started Securing Enterprise Applications".

The following topics are addressed here:

Overview of Web Application Security

Securing Web Applications

Using Programmatic Security with Web Applications

Examples: Securing Web Applications

48.1 Overview of Web Application Security

In the Java EE platform, web components provide the dynamic extension capabilities for a web server. Web components can be Java servlets or JavaServer Faces pages.

Certain aspects of web application security can be configured when the application is installed, or deployed, to the web container. Annotations and/or deployment descriptors are used to relay information to the deployer about security and other aspects of the application. Specifying this information in annotations or in the deployment descriptor helps the deployer set up the appropriate security policy for the web application. Any values explicitly specified in the deployment descriptor override any values specified in annotations.

Security for Java EE web applications can be implemented in the following ways.

Declarative security can be implemented using either metadata annotations or an application's deployment descriptor. See Overview of Java EE Security for more information.

Declarative security for web applications is described in Securing Web Applications.

Programmatic security is embedded in an application and can be used to make security decisions when declarative security alone is not sufficient to express the security model of an application. Declarative security alone may not be sufficient when conditional login in a particular work flow, instead of for all cases, is required in the middle of an application. See Overview of Java EE Security for more information.

Servlet 3.1 provides the authenticate, login, and logout methods of the HttpServletRequest interface. With the addition of the authenticate, login, and logout methods to the Servlet specification, an application deployment descriptor is no longer required for web applications but may still be used to further specify security requirements beyond the basic default values.

Programmatic security is discussed in Using Programmatic Security with Web Applications.

Message security works with web services and incorporates security features, such as digital signatures and encryption, into the header of a SOAP message, working in the application layer, ensuring end-to-end security. Message security is not a component of Java EE 7 and is mentioned here for informational purposes only.

Some of the material in this chapter builds on material presented earlier in this tutorial. In particular, this chapter assumes that you are familiar with the information in the following chapters:

Chapter 6, "Getting Started with Web Applications"

Chapter 7, "JavaServer Faces Technology"

Chapter 17, "Java Servlet Technology"

Chapter 47, "Introduction to Security in the Java EE Platform"

48.2 Securing Web Applications

Web applications are created by application developers who give, sell, or otherwise transfer the application to an application deployer for installation into a runtime environment. Application developers communicate how to set up security for the deployed application by using annotations or deployment descriptors. This information is passed on to the deployer, who uses it to define method permissions for security roles, set up user authentication, and set up the appropriate transport mechanism. If the application developer doesn't define security requirements, the deployer will have to determine the security requirements independently.

Some elements necessary for security in a web application cannot be specified as annotations for all types of web applications. This chapter explains how to secure web applications using annotations wherever possible. It explains how to use deployment descriptors where annotations cannot be used.

48.2.1 Specifying Security Constraints

A security constraint is used to define the access privileges to a collection of resources using their URL mapping.

If your web application uses a servlet, you can express the security constraint information by using annotations. Specifically, you use the @HttpConstraint and, optionally, the @HttpMethodConstraint annotations within the @ServletSecurity annotation to specify a security constraint.

If your web application does not use a servlet, however, you must specify a security-constraint element in the deployment descriptor file. The authentication mechanism cannot be expressed using annotations, so if you use any authentication method other than BASIC (the default), a deployment descriptor is required.

The following subelements can be part of a security-constraint.

Web resource collection (web-resource-collection): A list of URL patterns (the part of a URL after the host name and port you want to constrain) and HTTP operations (the methods within the files that match the URL pattern you want to constrain) that describe a set of resources to be protected. Web resource collections are discussed in Specifying a Web Resource Collection.

Authorization constraint (auth-constraint): Specifies whether authentication is to be used and names the roles authorized to perform the constrained requests. For more information about authorization constraints, see Specifying an Authorization Constraint.

User data constraint (user-data-constraint): Specifies how data is protected when transported between a client and a server. User data constraints are discussed in Specifying a Secure Connection.

48.2.1.1 Specifying a Web Resource Collection

A web resource collection consists of the following subelements.

web-resource-name is the name you use for this resource. Its use is optional.

url-pattern is used to list the request URI to be protected. Many applications have both unprotected and protected resources. To provide unrestricted access to a resource, do not configure a security constraint for that particular request URI.

The request URI is the part of a URL after the host name and port. For example, let's say that you have an e-commerce site with a catalog that you would want anyone to be able to access and browse, and a shopping cart area for customers only. You could set up the paths for your web application so that the pattern /cart/* is protected but nothing else is protected. Assuming that the application is installed at context path /myapp, the following are true.

http://localhost:8080/myapp/index.xhtml is not protected.

http://localhost:8080/myapp/cart/index.xhtml is protected.

A user will be prompted to log in the first time he or she accesses a resource in the cart/ subdirectory.

http-method or http-method-omission is used to specify which methods should be protected or which methods should be omitted from protection. An HTTP method is protected by a web-resource-collection under any of the following circumstances:

If no HTTP methods are named in the collection (which means that all are protected)

If the collection specifically names the HTTP method in an http-method subelement

If the collection contains one or more http-method-omission elements, none of which names the HTTP method

48.2.1.2 Specifying an Authorization Constraint

An authorization constraint (auth-constraint) contains the role-name element. You can use as many role-name elements as needed here.

An authorization constraint establishes a requirement for authentication and names the roles authorized to access the URL patterns and HTTP methods declared by this security constraint. If there is no authorization constraint, the container must accept the request without requiring user authentication. If there is an authorization constraint but no roles are specified within it, the container will not allow access to constrained requests under any circumstances. Each role name specified here must either correspond to the role name of one of the security-role elements defined for this web application or be the specially reserved role name *, which indicates all roles in the web application. Role names are case sensitive. The roles defined for the application must be mapped to users and groups defined on the server, except when default principal-to-role mapping is used.

For more information about security roles, see Declaring Security Roles. For information on mapping security roles, see Mapping Roles to Users and Groups.

For a servlet, the @HttpConstraint and @HttpMethodConstraint annotations accept a rolesAllowed element that specifies the authorized roles.

48.2.1.3 Specifying a Secure Connection

A user data constraint (user-data-constraint in the deployment descriptor) contains the transport-guarantee subelement. A user data constraint can be used to require that a protected transport-layer connection, such as HTTPS, be used for all constrained URL patterns and HTTP methods specified in the security constraint. The choices for transport guarantee are CONFIDENTIAL, INTEGRAL, or NONE. If you specify CONFIDENTIAL or INTEGRAL as a security constraint, it generally means that the use of SSL is required and applies to all requests that match the URL patterns in the web resource collection, not just to the login dialog box.

The strength of the required protection is defined by the value of the transport guarantee, as follows.

Specify CONFIDENTIAL when the application requires that data be transmitted so as to prevent other entities from observing the contents of the transmission.

Specify INTEGRAL when the application requires that the data be sent between client and server in such a way that it cannot be changed in transit.

Specify NONE to indicate that the container must accept the constrained requests on any connection, including an unprotected one.

Note:

In practice, Java EE servers treat the CONFIDENTIAL and INTEGRAL transport guarantee values identically.

The user data constraint is handy to use in conjunction with basic and form-based user authentication. When the login authentication method is set to BASIC or FORM, passwords are not protected, meaning that passwords sent between a client and a server on an unprotected session can be viewed and intercepted by third parties. Using a user data constraint with the user authentication mechanism can alleviate this concern. Configuring a user authentication mechanism is described in Specifying an Authentication Mechanism in the Deployment Descriptor.

To guarantee that data is transported over a secure connection, ensure that SSL support is configured for your server. SSL support is already configured for GlassFish Server.

Note:

After you switch to SSL for a session, you should never accept any non-SSL requests for the rest of that session. For example, a shopping site might not use SSL until the checkout page, and then it might switch to using SSL to accept your card number. After switching to SSL, you should stop listening to non-SSL requests for this session. The reason for this practice is that the session ID itself was not encrypted on the earlier communications. This is not so bad when you're only doing your shopping, but after the credit card information is stored in the session, you don't want anyone to use that information to fake the purchase transaction against your credit card. This practice could be easily implemented by using a filter.

48.2.1.4 Specifying Security Constraints for Resources

You can create security constraints for resources within your application. For example, you could allow users with the role of PARTNER full access to all resources at the URL pattern /acme/wholesale/* and allow users with the role of CLIENT full access to all resources at the URL pattern /acme/retail/*. This is the recommended way to protect resources if you do not want to protect some HTTP methods while leaving other HTTP methods unprotected. An example of a deployment descriptor that would demonstrate this functionality is the following:

<!-- SECURITY CONSTRAINT #1 -->
<security-constraint>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <web-resource-name>wholesale</web-resource-name>
        <url-pattern>/acme/wholesale/*</url-pattern>
    </web-resource-collection>
    <auth-constraint>
        <role-name>PARTNER</role-name>
    </auth-constraint>
    <user-data-constraint>
        <transport-guarantee>CONFIDENTIAL</transport-guarantee>
    </user-data-constraint>
</security-constraint>

<!-- SECURITY CONSTRAINT #2 -->
<security-constraint>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <web-resource-name>retail</web-resource-name>
        <url-pattern>/acme/retail/*</url-pattern>
    </web-resource-collection>
    <auth-constraint>
        <role-name>CLIENT</role-name>
    </auth-constraint>
    <user-data-constraint>
        <transport-guarantee>CONFIDENTIAL</transport-guarantee>
    </user-data-constraint>
</security-constraint>

48.2.2 Specifying Authentication Mechanisms

A user authentication mechanism specifies

The way a user gains access to web content

With basic authentication, the realm in which the user will be authenticated

With form-based authentication, additional attributes

When an authentication mechanism is specified, the user must be authenticated before access is granted to any resource that is constrained by a security constraint. There can be multiple security constraints applying to multiple resources, but the same authentication method will apply to all constrained resources in an application.

Before you can authenticate a user, you must have a database of user names, passwords, and roles configured on your web or application server. For information on setting up the user database, see Managing Users and Groups in GlassFish Server.

The Java EE platform supports the following authentication mechanisms:

Basic authentication

Form-based authentication

Digest authentication

Client authentication

Mutual authentication

Basic, form-based, and digest authentication are discussed in this section. Client and mutual authentication are discussed in Chapter 50, "Java EE Security: Advanced Topics".

HTTP basic authentication and form-based authentication are not very secure authentication mechanisms. Basic authentication sends user names and passwords over the Internet as Base64-encoded text. Form-based authentication sends this data as plain text. In both cases, the target server is not authenticated. Therefore, these forms of authentication leave user data exposed and vulnerable. If someone can intercept the transmission, the user name and password information can easily be decoded.

However, when a secure transport mechanism, such as SSL, or security at the network level, such as the Internet Protocol Security (IPsec) protocol or virtual private network (VPN) strategies, is used in conjunction with basic or form-based authentication, some of these concerns can be alleviated. To specify a secure transport mechanism, use the elements described in Specifying a Secure Connection.

48.2.2.1 HTTP Basic Authentication

Specifying HTTP basic authentication requires that the server request a user name and password from the web client and verify that the user name and password are valid by comparing them against a database of authorized users in the specified or default realm.

Basic authentication is the default when you do not specify an authentication mechanism.

When basic authentication is used, the following actions occur.

A client requests access to a protected resource.

The web server returns a dialog box that requests the user name and password.

The client submits the user name and password to the server.

The server authenticates the user in the specified realm and, if successful, returns the requested resource.

Figure 48-1 shows what happens when you specify HTTP basic authentication.

Figure 48-1 HTTP Basic Authentication

Description of "Figure 48-1 HTTP Basic Authentication"

48.2.2.2 Form-Based Authentication

Form-based authentication allows the developer to control the look and feel of the login authentication screens by customizing the login screen and error pages that an HTTP browser presents to the end user. When form-based authentication is declared, the following actions occur.

A client requests access to a protected resource.

If the client is unauthenticated, the server redirects the client to a login page.

The client submits the login form to the server.

The server attempts to authenticate the user.

If authentication succeeds, the authenticated user's principal is checked to ensure that it is in a role that is authorized to access the resource. If the user is authorized, the server redirects the client to the resource by using the stored URL path.

If authentication fails, the client is forwarded or redirected to an error page.

Figure 48-2 shows what happens when you specify form-based authentication.

Figure 48-2 Form-Based Authentication

Description of "Figure 48-2 Form-Based Authentication"

The section The hello1-formauth Example: Form-Based Authentication with a JavaServer Faces Application is an example application that uses form-based authentication.

When you create a form-based login, be sure to maintain sessions using cookies or SSL session information.

For authentication to proceed appropriately, the action of the login form must always be j_security_check. This restriction is made so that the login form will work no matter which resource it is for and to avoid requiring the server to specify the action field of the outbound form. The following code snippet shows how the form should be coded into the HTML page:

<form method="POST" action="j_security_check">
<input type="text" name="j_username">
<input type="password" name="j_password">
</form>

48.2.2.3 Digest Authentication

Like basic authentication, digest authentication authenticates a user based on a user name and a password. However, unlike basic authentication, digest authentication does not send user passwords over the network. Instead, the client sends a one-way cryptographic hash of the password and additional data. Although passwords are not sent on the wire, digest authentication requires that clear-text password equivalents be available to the authenticating container so that it can validate received authenticators by calculating the expected digest.

48.2.3 Specifying an Authentication Mechanism in the Deployment Descriptor

To specify an authentication mechanism, use the login-config element. It can contain the following subelements.

The auth-method subelement configures the authentication mechanism for the web application. The element content must be either NONE, BASIC, DIGEST, FORM, or CLIENT-CERT.

The realm-name subelement indicates the realm name to use when the basic authentication scheme is chosen for the web application.

The form-login-config subelement specifies the login and error pages that should be used when form-based login is specified.

Note:

Another way to specify form-based authentication is to use the authenticate, login, and logout methods of HttpServletRequest, as discussed in Authenticating Users Programmatically.

When you try to access a web resource that is constrained by a security-constraint element, the web container activates the authentication mechanism that has been configured for that resource. The authentication mechanism specifies how the user will be prompted to log in. If the login-config element is present and the auth-method element contains a value other than NONE, the user must be authenticated to access the resource. If you do not specify an authentication mechanism, authentication of the user is not required.

The following example shows how to declare form-based authentication in your deployment descriptor:

<login-config>
    <auth-method>FORM</auth-method>
    <realm-name>file</realm-name>
    <form-login-config>
        <form-login-page>/login.xhtml</form-login-page>
        <form-error-page>/error.xhtml</form-error-page>
    </form-login-config>
</login-config>

The login and error page locations are specified relative to the location of the deployment descriptor. Examples of login and error pages are shown in Creating the Login Form and the Error Page.

The following example shows how to declare digest authentication in your deployment descriptor:

<login-config>
    <auth-method>DIGEST</auth-method>
</login-config>

48.2.4 Declaring Security Roles

You can declare security role names used in web applications by using the security-role element of the deployment descriptor. Use this element to list all the security roles that you have referenced in your application.

The following snippet of a deployment descriptor declares the roles that will be used in an application using the security-role element and specifies which of these roles is authorized to access protected resources using the auth-constraint element:

<security-constraint>
    <web-resource-collection>
        <web-resource-name>Protected Area</web-resource-name>
        <url-pattern>/security/protected/*</url-pattern>
        <http-method>PUT</http-method>
        <http-method>DELETE</http-method>
        <http-method>GET</http-method>
        <http-method>POST</http-method>
    </web-resource-collection>
    <auth-constraint>
        <role-name>manager</role-name>
    </auth-constraint>
</security-constraint>

 <!-- Security roles used by this web application -->
<security-role>
    <role-name>manager</role-name>
</security-role>
<security-role>
    <role-name>employee</role-name>
</security-role>

In this example, the security-role element lists all the security roles used in the application: manager and employee. This enables the deployer to map all the roles defined in the application to users and groups defined in GlassFish Server.

The auth-constraint element specifies the role, manager, that can access the HTTP methods PUT, DELETE, GET, and POST located in the directory specified by the url-pattern element (/security/protected/*).

The @ServletSecurity annotation cannot be used in this situation because its constraints apply to all URL patterns specified by the @WebServlet annotation.

48.3 Using Programmatic Security with Web Applications

Programmatic security is used by security-aware applications when declarative security alone is not sufficient to express the security model of the application.

48.3.1 Authenticating Users Programmatically

The following methods of the HttpServletRequest interface enable you to authenticate users for a web application programmatically.

authenticate allows an application to instigate authentication of the request caller by the container from within an unconstrained request context. A login dialog box displays and collects the user name and password for authentication purposes.

login allows an application to collect user name and password information as an alternative to specifying form-based authentication in an application deployment descriptor.

logout allows an application to reset the caller identity of a request.

The following example code shows how to use the login and logout methods:

package test;

import java.io.IOException;
import java.io.PrintWriter;
import java.math.BigDecimal;
import javax.ejb.EJB;
import javax.servlet.ServletException;
import javax.servlet.annotation.WebServlet;
import javax.servlet.http.HttpServlet;
import javax.servlet.http.HttpServletRequest;
import javax.servlet.http.HttpServletResponse;

@WebServlet(name="TutorialServlet", urlPatterns={"/TutorialServlet"})
public class TutorialServlet extends HttpServlet {
    @EJB
    private ConverterBean converterBean;

    /**
     * Processes requests for both HTTP <code>GET</code> 
     *    and <code>POST</code> methods.
     * @param request servlet request
     * @param response servlet response
     * @throws ServletException if a servlet-specific error occurs
     * @throws IOException if an I/O error occurs
     */
    protected void processRequest(HttpServletRequest request, 
            HttpServletResponse response)
    throws ServletException, IOException {
        response.setContentType("text/html;charset=UTF-8");
        PrintWriter out = response.getWriter();
        try {

            out.println("<html>");
            out.println("<head>");
            out.println("<title>Servlet TutorialServlet</title>");
            out.println("</head>");
            out.println("<body>");
            request.login("TutorialUser", "TutorialUser");
            BigDecimal result = 
                converterBean.dollarToYen(new BigDecimal("1.0"));
            out.println("<h1>Servlet TutorialServlet result of dollarToYen= "
                + result + "</h1>");
            out.println("</body>");
            out.println("</html>");
        } catch (Exception e) {
            throw new ServletException(e);
        } finally {
            request.logout();
            out.close();
        }
    }
}

The following example code shows how to use the authenticate method:

package com.example.test;

import java.io.*;
import javax.servlet.*;
import javax.servlet.http.*;

public class TestServlet extends HttpServlet {

    protected void processRequest(HttpServletRequest request, 
            HttpServletResponse response)
            throws ServletException, IOException {
        response.setContentType("text/html;charset=UTF-8");
        PrintWriter out = response.getWriter();
        try {
            request.authenticate(response);
            out.println("Authenticate Successful");
        } finally {
            out.close();
        }
    }

48.3.2 Checking Caller Identity Programmatically

In general, security management should be enforced by the container in a manner that is transparent to the web component. The security API described in this section should be used only in the less frequent situations in which the web component methods need to access the security context information.

Servlet 3.1 specifies the following methods that enable you to access security information about the component's caller.

getRemoteUser determines the user name with which the client authenticated. The getRemoteUser method returns the name of the remote user (the caller) associated by the container with the request. If no user has been authenticated, this method returns null.

isUserInRole determines whether a remote user is in a specific security role. If no user has been authenticated, this method returns false. This method expects a String user role-name parameter.

The security-role-ref element should be declared in the deployment descriptor with a role-name subelement containing the role name to be passed to the method. Using security role references is discussed in Declaring and Linking Role References.

getUserPrincipal determines the principal name of the current user and returns a java.security.Principal object. If no user has been authenticated, this method returns null. Calling the getName method on the Principal returned by getUserPrincipal returns the name of the remote user.

Your application can make business-logic decisions based on the information obtained using these APIs.

48.3.3 Example Code for Programmatic Security

The following code demonstrates the use of programmatic security for the purposes of programmatic login. This servlet does the following.

It displays information about the current user.

It prompts the user to log in.

It prints out the information again to demonstrate the effect of the login method.

It logs the user out.

It prints out the information again to demonstrate the effect of the logout method.

package enterprise.programmatic_login;

import java.io.*;
import java.net.*;
import javax.annotation.security.DeclareRoles;
import javax.servlet.*;
import javax.servlet.http.*;

@DeclareRoles("javaee7user")
public class LoginServlet extends HttpServlet {

    /** 
     * Processes requests for both HTTP GET and POST methods.
     * @param request servlet request
     * @param response servlet response
     */
    protected void processRequest(HttpServletRequest request, 
                 HttpServletResponse response)
            throws ServletException, IOException {
        response.setContentType("text/html;charset=UTF-8");
        PrintWriter out = response.getWriter();
        try {
            String userName = request.getParameter("txtUserName");
            String password = request.getParameter("txtPassword");
            
            out.println("Before Login" + "<br><br>");
            out.println("IsUserInRole?.." 
                        + request.isUserInRole("javaee7user")+"<br>");
            out.println("getRemoteUser?.." + request.getRemoteUser()+"<br>");
            out.println("getUserPrincipal?.." 
                        + request.getUserPrincipal()+"<br>");
            out.println("getAuthType?.." + request.getAuthType()+"<br><br>");
            
            try {
                request.login(userName, password); 
            } catch(ServletException ex) {
                out.println("Login Failed with a ServletException.." 
                    + ex.getMessage());
                return;
            }
            out.println("After Login..."+"<br><br>");
            out.println("IsUserInRole?.." 
                        + request.isUserInRole("javaee7user")+"<br>");
            out.println("getRemoteUser?.." + request.getRemoteUser()+"<br>");
            out.println("getUserPrincipal?.." 
                        + request.getUserPrincipal()+"<br>");
            out.println("getAuthType?.." + request.getAuthType()+"<br><br>");
            
            request.logout();
            out.println("After Logout..."+"<br><br>");
            out.println("IsUserInRole?.." 
                        + request.isUserInRole("javaee7user")+"<br>");
            out.println("getRemoteUser?.." + request.getRemoteUser()+"<br>");
            out.println("getUserPrincipal?.."
                        + request.getUserPrincipal()+"<br>");
            out.println("getAuthType?.." + request.getAuthType()+"<br>");
        } finally {
            out.close();
        }
    }
    ...
}

48.3.4 Declaring and Linking Role References

A security role reference is a mapping between the name of a role that is called from a web component using isUserInRole(String role) and the name of a security role that has been defined for the application. If no security-role-ref element is declared in a deployment descriptor and the isUserInRole method is called, the container defaults to checking the provided role name against the list of all security roles defined for the web application. Using the default method instead of using the security-role-ref element limits your flexibility to change role names in an application without also recompiling the servlet making the call.

The security-role-ref element is used when an application uses the HttpServletRequest.isUserInRole(String role). The value passed to the isUserInRole method is a String representing the role name of the user. The value of the role-name element must be the String used as the parameter to the HttpServletRequest.isUserInRole(String role). The role-link must contain the name of one of the security roles defined in the security-role elements. The container uses the mapping of security-role-ref to security-role when determining the return value of the call.

For example, to map the security role reference cust to the security role with role name bankCustomer, the elements would look like this:

<servlet>
...
    <security-role-ref>
        <role-name>cust</role-name>
        <role-link>bankCustomer</role-link>
    </security-role-ref>
...
</servlet>

If the servlet method is called by a user in the bankCustomer security role, isUserInRole("cust") returns true.

The role-link element in the security-role-ref element must match a role-name defined in the security-role element of the same web.xml deployment descriptor, as shown here:

<security-role>
    <role-name>bankCustomer</role-name>
</security-role>

A security role reference, including the name defined by the reference, is scoped to the component whose deployment descriptor contains the security-role-ref deployment descriptor element.

48.4 Examples: Securing Web Applications

Some basic setup is required before any of the example applications will run correctly. The examples use annotations, programmatic security, and/or declarative security to demonstrate adding security to existing web applications.

Here are some other locations where you will find examples of securing various types of applications:

The cart-secure Example: Securing an Enterprise Bean with Declarative Security

The converter-secure Example: Securing an Enterprise Bean with Programmatic Security

GlassFish samples: https://glassfish-samples.java.net/

48.4.1 To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples

To set up your system for running the security examples, you need to configure a user database that the application can use for authenticating users. Before continuing, follow these steps.

Make sure that GlassFish Server has been started (see Starting and Stopping GlassFish Server).

Add an authorized user to GlassFish Server. For the examples in this chapter and in Chapter 49, "Getting Started Securing Enterprise Applications", add a user to the file realm of GlassFish Server, and assign the user to the group TutorialUser.

From the Administration Console, expand the Configurations node, then expand the server-config node.

Expand the Security node.

Expand the Realms node.

Select the File node.

On the Edit Realm page, click Manage Users.

On the File Users page, click New.

In the User ID field, enter a user ID.

In the Group List field, enter TutorialUser.

In the New Password and Confirm New Password fields, enter a password.

Click OK.

Be sure to write down the user name and password for the user you create so that you can use it for testing the example applications. Authentication is case sensitive for both the user name and password, so write down the user name and password exactly. This topic is discussed more in Managing Users and Groups in GlassFish Server.

Set up Default Principal to Role Mapping in GlassFish Server.

From the Administration Console, expand the Configurations node, then expand the server-config node.

Select the Security node.

Select the Default Principal to Role Mapping Enabled check box.

Click Save.

48.4.2 The hello2-basicauth Example: Basic Authentication with a Servlet

This example explains how to use basic authentication with a servlet. With basic authentication of a servlet, the web browser presents a standard login dialog box that is not customizable. When a user submits his or her name and password, the server determines whether the user name and password are those of an authorized user and sends the requested web resource if the user is authorized to view it.

In general, the following steps are necessary for adding basic authentication to an unsecured servlet, such as the ones described in Chapter 6, "Getting Started with Web Applications". In the example application included with this tutorial, many of these steps have been completed for you and are listed here simply to show what needs to be done should you wish to create a similar application. This application can be found in the tut-install/examples/security/hello2-basicauth/ directory.

Follow the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples.

Create a web module for the servlet example, hello2, as described in Chapter 6, "Getting Started with Web Applications".

Add the appropriate security annotations to the servlet. The security annotations are described in Specifying Security for Basic Authentication Using Annotations.

Build, package, and deploy the web application by following the steps in To Build, Package, and Deploy the hello2-basicauth Example Using NetBeans IDE or To Build, Package, and Deploy the hello2-basicauth Example Using Maven.

Run the web application by following the steps described in To Run the hello2-basicauth Example.

48.4.2.1 Specifying Security for Basic Authentication Using Annotations

The default authentication mechanism used by GlassFish Server is basic authentication. With basic authentication, GlassFish Server spawns a standard login dialog box to collect user name and password data for a protected resource. Once the user is authenticated, access to the protected resource is permitted.

To specify security for a servlet, use the @ServletSecurity annotation. This annotation allows you to specify both specific constraints on HTTP methods and more general constraints that apply to all HTTP methods for which no specific constraint is specified. Within the @ServletSecurity annotation, you can specify the following annotations:

The @HttpMethodConstraint annotation, which applies to a specific HTTP method

The more general @HttpConstraint annotation, which applies to all HTTP methods for which there is no corresponding @HttpMethodConstraint annotation

Both the @HttpMethodConstraint and @HttpConstraint annotations within the @ServletSecurity annotation can specify the following:

A transportGuarantee element that specifies the data protection requirements (that is, whether or not SSL/TLS is required) that must be satisfied by the connections on which requests arrive. Valid values for this element are NONE and CONFIDENTIAL.

A rolesAllowed element that specifies the names of the authorized roles.

For the hello2-basicauth application, the GreetingServlet has the following annotations:

@WebServlet(name = "GreetingServlet", urlPatterns = {"/greeting"})
@ServletSecurity(
@HttpConstraint(transportGuarantee = TransportGuarantee.CONFIDENTIAL,
    rolesAllowed = {"TutorialUser"}))

These annotations specify that the request URI /greeting can be accessed only by users who have been authorized to access this URL because they have been verified to be in the role TutorialUser. The data will be sent over a protected transport in order to keep the user name and password data from being read in transit.

If you use the @ServletSecurity annotation, you do not need to specify security settings in the deployment descriptor. Use the deployment descriptor to specify settings for nondefault authentication mechanisms, for which you cannot use the @ServletSecurity annotation.

48.4.2.2 To Build, Package, and Deploy the hello2-basicauth Example Using NetBeans IDE

Follow the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples.

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/security

Select the hello2-basicauth folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the hello2-basicauth project and select Build.

This command builds and deploys the example application to your GlassFish Server instance.

48.4.2.3 To Build, Package, and Deploy the hello2-basicauth Example Using Maven

Follow the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples.

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/security/hello2-basicauth/

Enter the following command:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, hello2-basicauth.war, that is located in the target directory, then deploys the WAR file.

48.4.2.4 To Run the hello2-basicauth Example

In a web browser, enter the following URL:

https://localhost:8181/hello2-basicauth/greeting

You may be prompted to accept the security certificate for the server. If so, accept the security certificate. If the browser warns that the certificate is invalid because it is self-signed, add a security exception for the application.

An Authentication Required dialog box appears. Its appearance varies, depending on the browser you use.

Enter a user name and password combination that corresponds to a user who has already been created in the file realm of GlassFish Server and has been assigned to the group TutorialUser; then click OK.

Basic authentication is case sensitive for both the user name and password, so enter the user name and password exactly as defined for GlassFish Server.

The server returns the requested resource if all the following conditions are met.

A user with the user name you entered is defined for GlassFish Server.

The user with the user name you entered has the password you entered.

The user name and password combination you entered is assigned to the group TutorialUser in GlassFish Server.

The role of TutorialUser, as defined for the application, is mapped to the group TutorialUser, as defined for GlassFish Server.

Enter a name in the field and click Submit.

Because you have already been authorized, the name you enter in this step does not have any limitations. You have unlimited access to the application now.

The application responds by saying "Hello" to the name you entered.

48.4.3 The hello1-formauth Example: Form-Based Authentication with a JavaServer Faces Application

This example explains how to use form-based authentication with a JavaServer Faces application. With form-based authentication, you can customize the login screen and error pages that are presented to the web client for authentication of the user name and password. When a user submits his or her name and password, the server determines whether the user name and password are those of an authorized user and, if authorized, sends the requested web resource.

This example, hello1-formauth, adds security to the basic JavaServer Faces application shown in A Web Module That Uses JavaServer Faces Technology: The hello1 Example.

In general, the steps necessary for adding form-based authentication to an unsecured JavaServer Faces application are similar to those described in The hello2-basicauth Example: Basic Authentication with a Servlet. The major difference is that you must use a deployment descriptor to specify the use of form-based authentication, as described in Specifying Security for the Form-Based Authentication Example. In addition, you must create a login form page and a login error page, as described in Creating the Login Form and the Error Page.

This application can be found in the tut-install/examples/security/hello1-formauth/ directory.

48.4.3.1 Creating the Login Form and the Error Page

When using form-based login mechanisms, you must specify a page that contains the form you want to use to obtain the user name and password, as well as a page to display if login authentication fails. This section discusses the login form and the error page used in this example. Specifying Security for the Form-Based Authentication Example shows how you specify these pages in the deployment descriptor.

The login page can be an HTML page or a servlet, and it must return an HTML page containing a form that conforms to specific naming conventions (see the Java Servlet 3.1 specification for more information on these requirements). To do this, include the elements that accept user name and password information between <form></form> tags in your login page. The content of an HTML page or servlet for a login page should be coded as follows:

<form method="post" action="j_security_check">
    <input type="text" name="j_username">
    <input type="password" name= "j_password">
</form>

The full code for the login page used in this example can be found at tut-install/examples/security/hello1-formauth/src/main/webapp/login.html. Here is the code for this page:

<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <title>Login Form</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <h2>Hello, please log in:</h2>
        <form method="post" action="j_security_check">
            <table role="presentation">
                <tr>
                    <td>Please type your user name: </td> 
                    <td><input type="text" name="j_username" 
                               size="20"/></td> 
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Please type your password: </td>
                    <td><input type="password" name="j_password"
                               size="20"/></td> 
                </tr>
            </table>
            <p></p>
            <input type="submit" value="Submit"/>
            &nbsp;
            <input type="reset" value="Reset"/>
        </form>
    </body>
</html>

The login error page is displayed if the user enters a user name and password combination that is not authorized to access the protected URI. For this example, the login error page can be found at tut-install/examples/security/hello1-formauth/src/main/webapp/error.html. For this example, the login error page explains the reason for receiving the error page and provides a link that will allow the user to try again. Here is the code for this page:

<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <title>Login Error</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <h2>Invalid user name or password.</h2>

        <p>Please enter a user name or password that is authorized to access 
           this application. For this application, this means a user that 
           has been created in the <code>file</code> realm and has been 
           assigned to the <em>group</em> of <code>TutorialUser</code>.</p>
        <p><a href="login.html">Return to login page</a></p>
    </body>
</html>

48.4.3.2 Specifying Security for the Form-Based Authentication Example

This example takes a very simple servlet-based web application and adds form-based security. To specify form-based instead of basic authentication for a JavaServer Faces example, you must use the deployment descriptor.

The following sample code shows the security elements added to the deployment descriptor for this example, which can be found in tut-install/examples/security/hello1-formauth/src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml:

    <security-constraint>
        <display-name>Constraint1</display-name>
        <web-resource-collection>
            <web-resource-name>wrcoll</web-resource-name>
            <description/>
            <url-pattern>/*</url-pattern>
        </web-resource-collection>
        <auth-constraint>
            <description/>
            <role-name>TutorialUser</role-name>
        </auth-constraint>
    </security-constraint>

    <login-config>
        <auth-method>FORM</auth-method>
        <realm-name>file</realm-name>
        <form-login-config>
            <form-login-page>/login.xhtml</form-login-page>
            <form-error-page>/error.xhtml</form-error-page>
        </form-login-config>
    </login-config>

    <security-role>
        <description/>
        <role-name>TutorialUser</role-name>
    </security-role>

48.4.3.3 To Build, Package, and Deploy the hello1-formauth Example Using NetBeans IDE

Follow the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples.

From the File menu, choose Open Project.

In the Open Project dialog box, navigate to:

tut-install/examples/security

Select the hello1-formauth folder.

Click Open Project.

In the Projects tab, right-click the hello1-formauth project and select Run.

This command builds and deploys the example application to your GlassFish Server instance, then opens it in a browser.

48.4.3.4 To Build, Package, and Deploy the hello1-formauth Example Using Maven and the asadmin Command

Follow the steps in To Set Up Your System for Running the Security Examples.

In a terminal window, go to:

tut-install/examples/security/hello1-formauth/

Enter the following command at the terminal window or command prompt:

mvn install

This command builds and packages the application into a WAR file, hello1-formauth.war, that is located in the target directory, then deploys the WAR file to GlassFish Server.

48.4.3.5 To Run the hello1-formauth Example

To run the web client for hello1-formauth, follow these steps.

Open a web browser to the following URL:

http://localhost:8080/hello1-formauth/

In the login form, enter a user name and password combination that corresponds to a user who has already been created in the file realm of GlassFish Server and has been assigned to the group TutorialUser.

Form-based authentication is case sensitive for both the user name and password, so enter the user name and password exactly as defined for GlassFish Server.

Click Submit.

If you entered My_Name as the name and My_Pwd for the password, the server returns the requested resource if all the following conditions are met.

A user with the user name My_Name is defined for GlassFish Server.

The user with the user name My_Name has a password My_Pwd defined for GlassFish Server.

The user My_Name with the password My_Pwd is assigned to the group TutorialUser on GlassFish Server.

The role TutorialUser, as defined for the application, is mapped to the group TutorialUser, as defined for GlassFish Server.

When these conditions are met and the server has authenticated the user, the application appears.

Enter your name and click Submit.

Because you have already been authorized, the name you enter in this step does not have any limitations. You have unlimited access to the application now.

The application responds by saying "Hello" to you.

Next Steps

For additional testing and to see the login error page generated, close and reopen your browser, enter the application URL, and enter a user name and password that are not authorized.